Good evening, ladies and gentlemen.
Good evening.
Welcome to the uh March 9th meeting of
the governing body. Welcome everyone.
Madame Clerk, would you take the role,
please?
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> present. Dr. Aldrich
>> present.
>> Mayor Collins
>> Dr. Emmens
>> present.
>> Mr. Esabel
>> here.
>> Mr. Leborn
>> present.
>> Mr. Moody
>> here.
>> Dr. Renie
>> present.
>> Mr. Crave
>> Mr. White
>> present.
>> All members are present. We do have a
quorum.
>> Please join me in the pledge of
allegiance.
Allegiance
to the flag of the United States of
America and to the republic for which it
stands. One nation under God,
indivisible, with liberty and justice
for all.
Consent agenda. All agenda items listed
with the designation of CA are
considered to be routine items by the
governing body and will be enacted by
one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body so requests
in support by two other members is
received. Any item removed from the
consent agenda will be considered in its
normal sequence on the agenda.
>> All right. Are there any items a member
of this governing body would like to
remove from the consent agenda?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um item number 20.
>> All right. The senior grandparents,
do we have concurrences?
>> Concur.
>> Okay.
>> Also item number 22.
>> Concur. Concur.
And item number 26. Mayor
>> concur.
>> The
>> 26
>> liquor licenses.
>> We have a second concurrence.
>> Concur.
>> Okay. 26 is removed. Anyone else,
>> Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes.
>> Number 21.
Concur.
>> Concur.
>> I would ask if someone would remove
number 18 because uh the final PL being
on the consent agenda would happen
before the zone change and the uh would
be finalized which would be out of
order.
>> Number 18.
>> Concur.
>> Thank you.
>> Not much of a consent agenda left.
Anybody else?
>> All right. I didn't entertain a motion,
please.
Moved by Mr. Crave, second by Mr. White.
>> All those in favor of what's left,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> I. Those opposed. All right. The consent
agenda is approved with 18, 20, 22, 26,
and 21 removed. If you're here for those
items, they'll be considered in the
normal sequence on our agenda. Thank
you.
>> Number seven, ordinance. Mr.
>> Mayor,
>> yes. I'd like to move to suspend the
rules to take
um number 22 to move it up in the
agenda.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second. [snorts]
>> It's a non-debatable motion. Requires
twothirds.
>> Item number 22 is a resolution for the
Pro Rodeo Hall of Fame or Association uh
headquarters Hall of Fame. Uh we have a
motion by Dr. Renie. Who was the second?
>> Okay.
As uh Dr. Renie said, it's a
non-debatable motion. We're asking to
suspend the rules, I suppose, to bring
number 22 to the next item on the
agenda.
>> Correct.
>> Um so all of those in favor, please
signify by saying I
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> The uh motion is approved. We'll suspend
the the rules. Take item number 22
first, please.
resolution in support of the
Professional Rodeo Cowboy Association,
PRCA, and Professional Rodeo Hall of
Fame and Museum of the American Cowboy.
>> All right. I think we've all read and
heard about this item. It's exciting for
the city of Cheyenne. Um it is an um an
expression of support from this
governing body uh to lead's effort to
bring the PRCA to Cheyenne. Um at this
time we'll go out to the audience and
see if anybody in the audience would
like to talk to us about this uh effort
this evening.
Katherine and Betsy, welcome ladies.
You got it. Just pull it down so you can
talk right into it.
>> Yes, I'm a little shorter. Good evening,
Mr. Mayor.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening, city council.
>> My name is Katherine Wilkinson and I am
a lobbyist has been hired for once in a
blue moon opportunity. Um, we'd like to
speak to you on behalf of Project Blue
Moon, which is a very exciting
opportunity with the relocation of the
PRCA to Cheyenne, Wyoming. So, I'm here
with Betsy Hail tonight. We just wanted
to thank you all for your support for
this incredible opportunity that we hope
will make uh a splash in Cheyenne. So,
Cheyenne Leans took the initiative to go
out to the PRCA, the Professional Rodeo
Cowboy Association, to see if they might
be interested in coming to Cheyenne. It
has been an incredible honor to work
with Betsy and her team. Um this has
been a private, public and state effort
to bring this opportunity. So I'd like
to tell you a little bit about the
funding um and wanted to thank you for
your contribution. So we have Cheyenne
Leans the board of directors has uh
voted on $15 million uh to have provide
matching funds for this organization.
The state of Wyoming legislature has
also provided 15 million funds out of
the special tourism and projects reserve
account 446 and that passed in the
budget um and was signed in law by the
governor as well. Um in addition to
Cheyenne leans and the 15 million for
the state of Wyoming uh we have about
$10 million in private corporate
sponsorships that are coming. We expect
more to come as well as running a six
penny ballot initiative that we're
hoping that the folks of Cheyenne would
like to contribute to. So, we um also
are very appreciative of Cheyenne's skin
in the game with the support that you
are showing to the PRCA. I will tell you
that they've received a lot of offers,
but they want to come here. They see it
as a very special place, and it's only
fitting that it's in the Cowboys state.
So, we just wanted to thank you very
much for your support and are happy to
provide you any information. uh Cheyenne
um is going to just benefit from this
tourism project and it's not just
Cheyenne but the state of Wyoming. So we
wanted to thank you for this effort.
>> Thank you.
>> And I turn it over to Betsy Hail in case
she has anything else.
>> Welcome Betsy.
>> Good evening city councilors and Mr.
Mayor. Betsy Hail, Cheyenne Lead, CEO.
First of all, I want to thank you so
much for all of your support uh over the
past year. Uh we have been working on
bringing this incredible professional uh
athletic association just like the NFL,
just like the major leagues home to the
Cowboy State and we could not have done
that and cannot do that without you.
We're not across the finish line quite
yet, but um this is certainly a model, a
business model that Cheyenne Leadeds has
used for the last 40 years uh by buying
land, building a business park, and then
finding great tenants. And so we feel
like this or association will be the the
great first cornerstone
uh project in the Hitching Post
District. So happy to stand for any
questions.
>> Betsy, could you tell the audience about
the Hitching Post District and the the
businesses that you expect to bring to
that area and the businesses you that
will not come to that area?
>> Show them that.
>> Well, thank you everyone. Um and we'll
we'll be brief because I know you got a
lot going on. Uh, but we wanted to um
look at where is there a location in
Cheyenne that could be really mobilized
and catalyzed for a a district that
would celebrate our western heritage
that we could live true to our our
western way of life. And um the Hitching
Post District really is a way for us to
honor the Hitching Post Hotel. It's an
it's an opportunity for us to celebrate
the legacy of that location. Uh but that
location was a little too small for what
we envisioned. And so there's about 415
acres here uh at the intersection of I25
and I 80 um that we'll be building roads
down into and um putting up the 35 acre
campus for the PRCA. So I hope you guys
can see that and we'll be happy to send
that over electronically.
>> Thank you. Does anyone in on the
governing body have any questions for
either of the ladies who are here to
talk to us this evening?
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins for you. I am just curious
if you have thought about or done any
projections on the amount of uh sales
tax revenue that might come into uh the
state of Wyoming and Larry County based
on this project.
>> Larry County and the city of Cheyenne uh
will receive about $800,000 of sales tax
once the museum and hall of fame are up
and going. That's on an
>> I don't have the state tax yet but
working on it.
>> And Betsy, that's on an annual basis,
right?
>> Yes. Yes, sir. Sorry,
>> Mr. White.
>> My apologies.
>> U Mr. Mayor through you. Betsy,
Katherine. Um and Katherine, I asked you
at committee if you could just tell the
folks here tonight what the what the uh
acreage square footage of this project
is going to be. If you could just
elaborate on that.
>> Sure, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, ma'am. Um the PRCA will go on about
35 acres of land and then the Hitching
Post District should be about 400 415
415 acres.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you. Uh
thank you guys. Um Mayor, Miss Ws, when
we first met and I proposed a
resolution. Um, do you propose that
there might be other western brand
companies that might actually come here
say like hat manufacturers, boot
manufacturers, etc. with this because I
was envisioning that
>> Mr. Mayor through you to councelor
Moody. Uh, yes, that's exactly what we
envision. um restaurants, retail, bars,
hotel, convention center, equestrian,
indoor arena, all of the things that
would be associated, as you pointed out,
um with this ability to gather in a
place that really tells the story of who
we are in Wyoming,
>> Dr.
No.
All right. Well, ladies, I just can't
say thank you enough. I know when you
get called this the blue moon uh that
you thought this was a once in a blue
moon opportunity for Cheyenne and just
the the initiative that went into um
finding a company and
making them a deal they couldn't refuse.
Uh I love it and so we're looking very
forward to uh seeing how this works out.
So thank you for your leadership on this
both of you.
>> Thank you to all of you as well.
>> Anybody else here this evening would
like to speak to uh the opportunity to
bring the PRCA to uh our great city.
Sir, if you want to come up, you have to
push the button and turn on the light
and introduce yourself if you would,
please.
>> Don ODM, Cheyenne, resident, I was
curious with all the millions of dollars
already committed and requesting more
sales tax.
Do they have an idea what the total cost
of this is going to be?
>> Um, I think we probably have a good
answer. I've heard that number around
$60 million, but uh they're they're not
in my head. I think the total project
will be about 60 million. Katherine,
>> Mr. Mayor, that is correct. We expect
the total project to be about $60
million.
>> Anyone else in the audience here
tonight?
>> All right. Hearing none, I would go to
Mr. Escoel for a motion. Sir,
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to adopt and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Second by the committee.
I'll give that to Mr. White. Um,
comments from members of this governing
body.
>> Mr. Escoel,
>> it was said that we don't do much to
promote our cowboy culture here and uh,
just by what you heard, that's proof
that we're definitely putting our money
where our mouth is and so can't wait to
see it and looking forward.
Anyone else?
>> Anyone else? All right, hearing none.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. By your vote, the city
council's uh voted to support the
relocation of the PRCA, the Hall of
Fame, and the museum to Cheyenne,
Wyoming. Next item, please.
>> Number seven, ordinance, third reading,
creating chapter 8.72, private displays
on public property to prohibit the
unauthorized use of public property for
specified private displays.
>> All right. We have before us an
ordinance that restricts uh private
displays on public rideaways and we'll
go out to the audience if anybody wants
to speak to that tonight.
Hearing none. Dr. Mr. Glam, did you want
to speak to this?
>> You I'm quick on the gun. So, [laughter]
>> um I just want to say that I oppose this
ordinance. Um I think it's silly and a
complete waste of time. Um, if it's on
private property, let the private
property owners deal with it. Um, I I
believe at the committee, um,
>> this is on public right away. It's not
private property. So,
>> right. I'm just saying if if there is a
memorial on private property, because I
know that that does happen occasionally.
Let them deal with it. But on the public
right away, um, I believe at the
committee there weren't any city
employees that thought this was an issue
necessarily. I know um Councilwoman
Aldridge said that possibly someone had
come to her and talked to her from the
city u one of the departments, but um I
just wanted to say I've talked to a few
community members and we just think it's
a silly waste of time for you guys, but
thank you.
>> Appreciate it.
>> Welcome back, sir.
>> Mr. Mayor, members of the council, good
evening. My name is Steven Love. I live
in W one here in Cheyenne, Wyoming. You
have heard a lot from me in the la past
few weeks. Um I hope to make that a
permanent happening in the weeks and
months to come. I think it's essential
that the voices of the people be heard
so that you can all vote with greater
perspective in these matters that all
affect our lives so deeply whether the
people take time to get up here and talk
about it or not. I'm glad I was here
heard at our last city council meeting.
There was an amendment put forward at
the public service committee by Dr.
Aldridge that I was very thankful for
and felt would have brought this to a
point where signing it into law would
not have been completely unreasonable
overreach. It would have removed unjust
fines imposed in the ordinance.
Unfortunately, the amendment failed to
receive [clears throat] a second,
leaving this in a state that I find to
be unreasonable and unacceptable at this
time. And frankly, without a
recommendation by the committee, I think
that other members of the council may
feel the same. This item that threatens
to impact the people of Cheyenne in a
very real way. This ordinance, if
codified, would create unnecessary
financial burden on individuals in our
community who have lost a loved one.
Please don't tax mourning. There is
enough grief with the loss of a loved
one without the government creating
more. Many in our community use these
memorials to remember loved ones who met
a tragic end on our roadways. Please
remember these community members, our
friends and family, tonight as you vote
on this ordinance. Don't allow for
unnecessary government overreach. Don't
let them be forgotten because one or two
members of our community wishes to
dictate to hundreds of others how to
mourn. Save your yays for an ordinance
that serves the people of Cheyenne
better. And vote no tonight for all
those whose lives have been lost and
their families who will never stop
mourning. Thank you.
>> Anybody else? Chelsea, welcome. You're
walking better today.
>> I am walking a little better. It's
slowly getting better. So,
>> glad to see it. Thank you. Um Chelsea
McCort, uh Cheyenne, Wyoming, Ward One.
Um I would like to also speak in
opposition of this. I'm going to
reiterate a few things I said at the
public service uh committee's meeting.
Um so despite this perception that these
are distracting,
there's been studies there particularly
looking at one in 2019 and 2011 that
show that roadside memorials are not
significantly distracting whatsoever. um
they do not affect speed of travel, they
are not perceived risk. Um
even those who thought that they were a
distraction when they were looked at
like their road behaviors were not
actually distracted. And so there's this
mental disconnect between the physical
fact that it really is not actually a
distraction. Um
uh there's also as as uh Mr. Love
mentioned there's not really any um
significant complaints or issues that
have occurred in the past um via city
employees um being people actually hit
visiting these roadside memorials. They
tend to be pretty safe because it's
related to death and so there's a mental
thing about being wary of it. Um I know
that there were discussions about
alternative options. Those cost money
that a lot of times morning families do
not have the opportunity to do it. They
cost time. They cannot be put up
immediately. Uh that's hard on a family
to be able to not have the instantaneous
representation of grief. My background
is in anthropology. That's bad. I can
just tell you basically. Um grieving
people are not going to be looking at
the city code. They're not going to be
verifying, especially when they see
displays on private property around the
town. They're going to see those and
think, hm, this is a display. Why can't
I have my display out? Not necessarily
realizing that they are in nuanced
private areas. Um it's hard to tell who
exactly is putting up the displays.
There may be an idea that this person is
doing it. You know, perhaps they think
it's the family. In reality, it's a
friend who's hosting the memorial. Um
there's a question of what do you do
when you find a memorial and clean it
up? Do you throw away those items that
may be significantly uh significant
momentos for the family? Um there's
there's just a lot of problems with the
way it needs some modifications. If if
this is something you want to do, for
instance, looking at Fort Collins, they
have a 30-day limit that you're allowed
to have the the private memorials up for
30 days. And then at that point, if
someone has complained about it, then
they remove it, they store the items,
they distribute it to the family if they
so wish. Um, it just needs modification.
It's bad for us as a culture and as a
society, for how we grieve and how we
perceive death and for the individuals
who have lost a loved one. It's hard on
them. It's devastating for them. So, I
speak in opposition. Thank you.
>> I see a lot of people standing in the
back, but I see quite a few open chairs
here. kind of like church guys, you
know, we got to just kind of kind of
squirt you in. We're going to be here a
long time tonight, so you might as well
come find a seat and and get comfortable
so that we can make it through this
evening. Anybody else on this ordinance?
>> Anyone else hearing? None. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the motion to approve failed
at the public service committee.
Therefore, there is no recommendation.
However, for the sake of discussion, I
move to approve on third and final
reading.
Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Second by Dr. Aldridge. Okay. Members of
the governing body, Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins, um through you. Um I
have so many thoughts about this, but as
I was thinking about this, it was not I
would remind my colleagues that have
been on the council um for more than a
year. Um that we had a similar request
come to us um several years ago by a
former council member who was wanting to
put up banners for veterans in the
public right of way. um all along Ridge
Road and Windmill had talked about doing
some uh going towards the VA hospital
and at that time this council um or that
council I should say um was um voted
against doing that because it was in the
public right away and there was a
concern about um if we allowed one type
of organization or one type of memorial
or banner in that we would have to allow
all in. And so I would just like to
remind my colleagues of that vote that
you voted on. Um I understand that
mourning is um in individualized that
it's um very dependent upon culture and
that it um is something that is
important to families and to community
members. Um and I'm all about memorials
if they're not in the public right
ofway. if um they would like to do that
on private property, if they would like
to do that through whatever mechanism
families choose. Um that's one reason
why we have cemeteries. Um but there are
also uh additional opportunities for
families um that are of little or no
cost um and or can be as costly as they
would like to whether it's um from a
simple tree planting to a bench to a
male limb. Um, so for that reason, I
would encourage us to, um, consider
this. While it may not have been brought
by a majority of, uh, people that we've
heard from, um, I think that, um, as
with any piece of legislation we bring
forward, um, as people come and talk to
council people, um, that's how many of
our ideas come forward is through that
legislation. Um, while my colleagues in
Ward 2 may not have many of these in
their ward, uh, right now in Ward three,
um, I can think of five right off the
top of my head. Um, and maybe we just
have more accidents in W three. Um, but
I would encourage my colleagues to, uh,
pass this on third and final reading.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, so I've been
against this res this ordinance since
the beginning. Um, and part of it is,
I'm just going to be very honest from an
emotional perspective, having lost a
child and, um, knowing that I wanted to
do something
to
keep that spirit alive.
Every day I drive by the um the memorial
that's on Nation Way twice a day, when I
go to work and when I come home from
work. every single day, five days a
week.
And I think it does, as Miss McCort
stated, it does help people think about,
I do need to slow down. I do need to be
cautious. I need to be cognizant of what
I'm doing.
Maybe we should look at some uh guidance
around what that looks like. you know,
if it's close close to a tree or
whatever. But I know that when you lose
someone,
not only are you dealing with grief, but
you're dealing with a significant
financial issue.
And there's a lot of people, I was
lucky. I was able to buy a bench in the
library for my son. Not everybody can do
that. And what we have on Nationway is a
very inexpensive, very well- cared for,
very loved, very meticulous
memorial for a family. And maybe that's
all they can afford. I don't know. I
don't know what their situation is. But
to me, that's that's very important. And
like we've said, there's no rules around
morning. It can there's no rules around
morning. So, I would encourage my uh
colleagues to vote no on this ordinance.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um I can make a
very principled perhaps legalistic
argument in favor of this ordinance and
it's this
um we tend to focus in all our
discussion on the memorials that are
there. uh the one on Nation Way in
particular, the other one um which has
the helmet stuck up on the stick. Um but
we need to set aside all of those and
all of their appearance and we need to
look at at what this really is. And what
this is is a decision when one of these
morals is established by a private
individual or a family to occupy
part of the public right away. And they
do that without asking anybody's
permission, without, you know, saying
okay, you know, is there somebody who
can say it's fine to put it there? No,
it just arrives.
uh and it arrives
most often in times of of grief and and
uh bereiement. Um but it it reflects
basically a decision that I want this
piece of property. I intend to build my
memorial here and I want it defended.
I don't want it taken away. I want it
protected by the city.
So the question is whether or not that
that is what we want to allow and
realize that
under the current circumstances without
any kind of uh prohibition you don't
have to do this for a person you could
do this for fuff fluffy or phto or
whatever else you wanted to build a
memorial to. So, um, there is maybe a
gap in the law that needs to be
addressed. All that being said, Mr.
Mayor, I'm going to vote no on this
ordinance. Um, I don't think it's a big
enough issue at this point to take our
time and energy and take all the energy
it's already consumed. So, thank you,
Mr. Mayor. Anyone else? Mr. Leeborn.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. One of the things
that's come up in regard to this
ordinance is uh our schedule of fines
and uh judgments from the court and uh I
believe I'm correct and maybe m Mr.
Brody can speak to this that state
statute gives us a maximum limit of the
ability to invoke a judgment against the
person in court which is uh 750 bucks in
6 months in jail. Now, am I correct that
that runs across our code in a way that
uh doesn't differentiate between, for
instance, this proposed ordinance and
lowering the fine or um others, of
course, excluding traffic uh offenses
that we do have a schedule for, but in
general, isn't that uh generally what
the judge has the opportunity to review?
Mr. Brody.
>> U Mr. Mayor, John Brody, city attorney.
Uh Councilman Leborn, I I would agree
that the predominant approach that the
city council has taken over the years is
to tie um all violations of ordinance to
what's called the general penalty. And
the general penalty is uh that penalty
that you referenced with a ceiling of
$750 and six months in jail or both. I
would say the court um I'm not aware of
the court ever imposing anything near
that uh those ceilings.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr.
Well, that's the point. I don't want
people to think that no matter what the
circumstances were in regard to this
particular ordinance or many other
ordinances that we have that that is
ever going to be the fine and that
someone is going to go to jail for it
because that's not the case. That's in
practice that has not ever happened at
least to my knowledge. And maybe uh
someday it might. But I think the point
being if we start going through the our
code and saying well this is the fine
for this and this is the fine for that
and this is the maximum uh jail time
although uh I think it's very rare that
anybody has to serve time in jail unless
there's other extenduating
circumstances. So, I just wanted to try
to speak to that a little bit because I
think it would really be a poor
precedent for us and that's why I didn't
support it in committee to change that
on a up and down basis depending on the
issue. We have that maximum set that I I
trust the judgment of our courts. I
think that our municipal court has never
abused any of their authority to throw
someone in jail for a minor offense.
But I hope everyone understands my
point. We can't have different fines and
fees. It's really not right for us to be
making that uh law for the court. The
court has got to use their judgment and
this is just a matter that goes clear
across our code for the maximum and then
the judge probably can consider the
offense, consider the past uh rulings
that have happened. So, I I just am
concerned that we would ever start um
doing a fine for this and a fine for
that and really making the court um
directing the court if there's if
there's a violation, I believe our
municipal court can handle it and they
always have. So, I just uh wanted to
make that clear. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Anyone else from the governing body on
this ordinance for private memorials on
public rights away?
>> All right, I hear none. Madame clerk,
will you take the vote?
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> no.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> no.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> Mr. Esel,
>> no.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> hi.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> no.
Dr. Renie,
>> Mr. Crave,
>> no.
>> Uh, the ordinance fails on third and
final reading.
>> Number eight, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for certain land located
north of Prairie Avenue, east of Powder
House Road, west of Rutter, and south of
Story Boulevard from AG agricultural to
NR3 neighborhood residential high
density. All right, we have before us
now a zone change that will support the
construction of a multifamily senior
housing development basically on the
corner of um Carlson and Powder House um
here in Cheyenne. So, we'll go out to
the audience. Does anybody have any
comments on the zone change? Anybody in
the audience?
>> Okay, hearing none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final final reading and I
so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave.
>> All right. Comments from members of the
governing body on the zone change.
>> Hearing none. Madam clerk.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. White.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Labbourne.
>> Yes.
>> Sorry, I skipped over. Mr. Escoel.
>> I.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes.
>> The ordinance for zone changes approved
on third and final reading.
>> Number nine, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
southeast of the intersection of South
Gley Highway and East Dea Lane from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park.
>> All right. This is a zone change that
will allow for a small expansion to the
bison business park in South Cheyenne.
Is anybody here today to talk to this
zone change?
[snorts]
>> Hearing none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. Comments for
members of the governing body on the
zone change?
>> Hearing none. Madam clerk?
>> Dr. Riny.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Esabel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Booty.
>> Hi.
>> This zone change is also approved on
third and final reading.
>> Number 10. Ordinance. Third reading.
Annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, various tracks of land
completely surrounded by current city
limits. Situate in western and southern
Cheyenne. Generally located east of I25,
south of the intersection of Westland
Road and Missile Drive, north of West
and East Allison Road and east of and
adjacent to North College Drive.
>> All right. So, I see a lot of new faces
here today and that's exciting. Thank
you all for being here. Um, many of you
have never come and testified before
city council before. So, welcome. The
the way this works is we have two
microphones, one on either side. Uh we'd
love for you to come up and introduce
yourself for the record and then we'll
give you three minutes to uh to testify.
Uh Rob, we run our meetings by Robert's
rules of order and so in order to keep
the decorum in the room, all your
comments should be directed to me as the
chairman of of the committee. We
shouldn't be going after individual
council people. And the same thing for
our council, those comments should be
addressed to me also. Okay? And u we'll
look forward to having a a civil
discussion and love to hear what you
guys have to say on the annexations
before us. And with that, we'll start
with Mr. Bloom uh who is our city
planner.
>> Mayor, members of the governing body,
Charles Bloom, plan development
director. Um just want to just give a
little bit of highlights about what's
going on with this annexation. This is
the 10th of our county pocket
annexations. This is the uh 10th time
we've annexed a grouping of properties
um based on the city council from 2022's
council goal, which was facilitated by
the mayor and the chief of staff at that
time to to come up with those goals. And
then it's been our task over the course
of the last few years to make code
modifications and go ahead and us to
make the annexations easier and to go
ahead and commence with the annexations.
Um this this property has been one that
we um probably had our first
interactions with through public comment
when uh Mr. David Nicely uh did reach
out to our department and we started
talking about concerns and questions
because they had just recently had a
home occupation permit that was approved
by the county um about 4 months prior to
that council goal being done. That was
August of 2021. uh that home occupation
was approved in such a manner to allow
for farming operations and also a farm
stand provided not have more than 25
customers daily. It was noted in that
approval that if it exceeded 25
customers daily, it would then need to
go through the county site plan process.
uh with it being a county development
adjacent to city streets, we frequently
deal with these uh situations where we
work with a county and ensure that they
have the most painless uh site plan
process they can when you're dealing
with multiple jurisdictions because in
those scenarios you you must deal with
our city engineering department. No
stabs at Tom, it's wonderful department.
Um but you still do need to look at
access with with county site plans.
Today we had a meeting with the nicelys
um and their legal representation and we
did discuss about how that has worked in
the past before. We I called it the tale
of two McDonald's. We have the
McDonald's that is located on South
Breley Highway at Jefferson where
they're making a significant investment
in that property and Jefferson is a
street that's in the city. For those of
you who have driven on Jefferson, it's
probably to get to the farm stand. Um,
you notice back seven years ago, it was
uh not a very well-improved road was
missing. Curb gutter, sidewalk on that
north side. There's some drainage issues
because of a natural spring there. Well,
the development for McDonald's was uh
doing a lot had a lot of investment. So
at that time it was reasonable for us to
require that in the right ofway they
install curb gutter sidewalk and they
control the drainage that's coming off
of their property. The tail of the other
McDonald's is just a family name of
McDonald. Uh they're located up on Ridge
and Greg Way. This is one that is
presently in development right now and
recently has a county site plan that was
approved prior to the annexation which
we are continuing to honor because
that's what we've done. and they're on
Greg Way, which is an unimproved gravel
road. All they're building is a storage
building and a shop. Uh it's an
expansion of an existing use nearby, not
very intense, low traffic counts, not
very much traffic that's warranted. We
again coordinated with the county with
through their site plan process. and our
city engineering department reviewed
that application and said, you know,
there's no real rational nexus or a
proportionality for us to require full
street standards. So, essentially what
happened with that McDonald property is
they signed a uh no protest agreement in
the event that the city um moves forward
with a local improvement district for
upgrade to those roads. local
improvement districts under the Wyoming
state statute. They are not handed down
or demanded by the governing body or the
mayor or any person in staff. They are
the direct result of a landowner
petition um that is sliced and diced in
numerous different ways that essentially
say 50% of the owners of the land, the
population of the land. It can be by
frontage, it can be by lot area. If they
petition the governing body to move
forward with that local improvement
district, then they can do that. provide
they have a majority that is the will of
the land owners. It can't be something
that is that is um basically
thrown upon them by the governing body
without a majority of land owners
consent.
Um, and that's just very important why I
wanted to mention that when we ask
someone to to sign a u a no protest
agreement for an improvement district
that they understand that it's not just
the city, it's also the the neighbors
that would would create the need for
that to actually come to fruition in the
future. Um, with this um proposed
annexation, we've had two properties
that are zoned a that have that have
popped up. Um, we've had the opportunity
to meet with both of them. the one
that's been the most uh vocal and the
most public and the one that's garnered
the most green ever in the council
chambers at the same time.
Congratulations. Um that's the Wildresh
one. And we've been trying to make sure
that we are making this process as easy
for them and predictable for them in the
future. Um knowing that what they they
have in the county right now probably
isn't exactly what the county approved.
And in talking with the county, there
are concerns um that they have
identified that they said, "Yes, we
weren't aware that these items were
happening here." But what we want to do
is we want to be able to move in, work
with them on um continuing the operation
of this farm as it is, allow for
livestock and chickens and and animals
to continue to be brought into the site,
you know, provided they aren't
constituting a nuisance or creating
excessive smells, flies, and stuff like
like that on the site. Um, we have
received the land use documentation form
as of Friday. And then this afternoon
around 11 11:00 a.m. we received a very
complete and very nice uh site plan
drawing packet that was prepared by um
Chelsea,
which is very nice. Um, which we're
we're working on um making sure that we
outline any any issues. Overall, it
looks good. Um I believe so far all all
that staff has seen that are that are
issues is wanting to make sure that we
um define what an agricultural pile is.
Is it manure? Is it feed? Is it farm
parts like building parts, structure
parts? Is what what is it? So is it a
mixture of all those things together? So
we can be sure of what those are. Um,
also there's a couple of corrections
that they had um, noted that just need
to be made based on the permanence and
the temporary umness of the building.
There are a couple of outstanding issues
that still do exist. Um, these are
issues that would have existed in the
city or the county. Um, a lot of those
are with the occupancy of the farm stand
structure itself and how it moved into a
position where it has electrical
[snorts]
connections without inspections, without
permits. Um so those are items that we
have um detailed or discussed a a plan
with them on what that would look like.
Um it doesn't require any removal of
sheetrock or inspection of anything in
the building. It's one just to identify
any major life safety or or health
issues that are there. Um with that
we're continue to move forward. We hope
that this uh annexation can be deemed
complete today, can be approved today so
we can complete the county pocket
annexation process. Um, but we're open
for any questions from the governing
body and I'm look forward to being able
to hopefully close this chapter. Thank
you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Uh, thank
you, Mr. Bloom. Um, I remember I was
rewatching the public services
committee. You said you defined a little
bit of what an urban farm is, but it's
only policy and it's not set precedent
law. Is that correct,
>> Mr. Blue?
>> Mayor Council Men Moody, that is
correct. Um, in our unified development
code, the way our definitions are
drafted is they are broad catchall
definitions. Some development codes are
very specific. They will go all the way
down to a specific use. That's a t-shirt
shop. This is a figurine shop. This is a
gift shop. you know, it will say all the
different types. Ours will say this is a
retail service. So, when someone comes
forward and says, "We have a t-shirt
shop." We're like, "Well, it's going to
fit into this category." And if there's
something that is very unclear, we will
uh basically create these policy
documents that are guides, which will be
published on the website that say this
is how we interpret and this is how it
falls into place. Um, other items we
don't specifically call out include uh
churches. Those are places of of
assembly. Um like a
a massage uh studio or something along
those lines. Those are personal care. So
there's all these other ones that just
fall into those because we defer to what
is the most similar use. The urban farm
was a little bit different, a little bit
different operations, different scale.
But through that policy document we put
together, we said this is what we've
captured as an urban farm from what's
been provided by the land owner. These
are the activities that are going and we
feel all of those activities fall within
these two permitted uses limited
agriculture and general agriculture. Um
and then we added in and it also
includes very limited sales that are
ancillary to the overall farming
process.
um that was envisioned to give them
comfort that if they wanted to continue
to move forward with site expansion in
the future that they would be able to do
that without any necessary public
hearings or running into a roadblock on
moving forward. They still will have to
go through a site plan process which
does look at how any uh expansion or
change like a new building or a massive
change in their operation they'd have to
go through to make sure it doesn't have
any adverse negative impacts on
neighbors. Those are impacts such as
traffic um which usually can be
mitigated through public improvements,
traffic control, deceleration lanes,
acceleration lanes, turn lanes, those
items. But also could be items such as
if they were bringing in say
45 head of cattle. That's a different
operation where number one, we'd reach
out to other state agencies to
understand what's appropriate. Um that
could include like like city county
health. It could include the Wyoming
Department of Agriculture to understand
if that is expected to create a nuisance
and enhance uh smells and flies and
those other items. Um so we would have
to go through that process to make sure
that they're not negatively affecting
the property owners that live nearby.
>> So Mr. Bloom, what is the effect of your
your policy statement then? basically
that until it's codified, that is the
the rule of the city um in in respect to
in this case an urban farm.
>> Mayor, members of council, that is
correct. That is the interpretation of
the city. Um that will be posted on the
website. Um it will be one that we'll
hang our hat on and once a code an
amendment or municipal code amendment is
made that will supersede that, it will
remain in effect to keep that
predictability in place for the land
owners.
>> Thank you, Dr.
Mr. Mayor through you. So, uh, Mr.
Bloom, if I recall from that meeting
that my colleague referenced, um, in the
agricultural
zone, which is already codified,
if someone is annexed in and they are
zoned in agriculture and they come in
with horses or cows or whatever, they
would be able to con
uh continue to have those animals on
their property if they're zoned A. Is
that correct,
>> Mr. Blue?
>> Mayor, through the members of council
and Dr. Ammons. Yes, that's 100%
accurate. Uh we presently have um added
horses to the incorporated city limits
with some of our past annexations. So,
they would be able to remain.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> followup.
>> So, just to be clear, it is currently
codified.
>> Mayor through to Dr. is yes as currently
>> Thank you.
>> Anyone else in the governing body with
staff? Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins through you. I just want
to be really clear on this because I
asked that question at the committee and
you had said that it was not codified
for urban farming. Um there so there is
a difference between urban farming and
just maintaining what is currently being
done. Is that correct,
>> Mr. Bloom?
>> Mayor through to Dr. Aldrich. Um great
question. What what I was believing I
was answering for Dr. Emmens was
specifically related related to
livestock residing on a property where
livestock residing on a property is
codified that is allowed. It can be a
hobby horse. It can be whatever whatever
you want that's allowed for agricultural
zone land. The urban farm definition per
se, the land use that is not codified
and that land use uh interpretation is
what's in that zoning policy statement
which said this is what we understand
where it is. This is where we understand
it falls into place in our use table.
Therefore, it's a permissible land use.
>> Dr. question, Mayor Collins. Um, if
things were to remain the same, if this
property remained in the county and
wanted to, in your example, go to 47
head of cows, which I I mean, that's a
lot. Um, that that would also
um trigger, if you will, um, changes
that may have may be called upon by the
county as well. Correct. I mean, we're
not we're there would be changes
required by the count or there could be
things possibly required by the county
at that point um or by the city if there
was a change of use to that degree.
>> Mr. Bloom,
>> mayor, members of C, mayor through you
to Dr. Aldrich, members of council, um
yes, it would be in the city or the
county. The county was clear that if it
exceeded the 25 customers in their
approval that it would trigger a site
plan.
Thank you.
>> Anyone else for staff?
>> Mr. Boon, thank you. All right, folks.
This is your turn. Um, so again, if you
want to come up and introduce yourself.
Um, and we'll uh we'll look forward to
uh hearing your testimony. We'll stay as
long as we need to hear all of you and
we look forward to it. Thank you. Tommy,
welcome.
>> I'm Tommy Nicely, 200 Walters, WFresh
Farm. I'm here to ask you to exclude my
farm from annexation.
I would like to start by offering the
first olive branch. I'm sorry. I'm sorry
that I have used blanket statements that
the ceiling city is unwilling to work
with us. In reality, it probably has
only been a handful of individuals that
have exacerbated the difficulty of this
situation.
We had our first meeting with city
officials a few hours ago. Meeting with
I think I counted six department heads.
Yes, six. That is how complex annexation
is and how it affects so many aspects of
our lives and even future planning.
I took comfort in finding the department
heads to be genuine individuals that
appear to be willing to work on a
solution.
three stood out to be not only
approachable but solution-minded
individuals. Mr. Cobb here is one of
those. Um
I found a lot of comfort and was
encouraged. It was nice to see that I
believe Cheyenne has the leadership
that if they are given the time and
adequate preparation and the information
that they require that they will be able
to find a very constructive way forward
that is not only beneficial to our farm
but to the city of Cheyenne.
Even so, as of today, we are still
unclear of all the regulations we will
be under and how I can continue to farm
as we have. It's unclear if we even have
the right to farm.
We need time to figure it out and so
does the city. We've repeatedly stressed
that we want to find a way forward, but
let's do so properly.
clear, well-written urban farm
ordinances or even changes to the a
zoning not only need to be written, but
they need to be publicly debated and
then they need to be adopted before
annexation can occur. I do believe we
can find a way to be incorporated into
Cheyenne. However, today is not the day.
More time is needed, more work is
needed. Mr. Bloom even said that the
work is not done.
You just awarded $1 million to the PRCA.
I believe the state is going to award
them 20 million to help move their
headquarters to Cheyenne
to quote
live true to our western way of life
unquote.
We are living true to our western way of
life. We do so happily and we do so for
free. We encourage our farm supporters
to live true to our western way of life
for free. And I encourage you, the city,
and proceed carefully.
Please don't annex my farm,
>> sir.
[applause]
Hey guys, I I appreciate your support,
but honestly, we don't do that here,
okay? Please, we're going to listen
respectfully and uh one way or the other
cuz we can't boo the people you don't
agree with. So, thank you very much.
Please, sir, come forward. Welcome.
>> Um, thank you very much, mayor. Uh,
members of the city council, my name is
Michael Jordan. I live here in the city
of Cheyenne. Um, I own a business in
Cheyenne. I own a couple of them. I also
own a couple agricultural business
throughout Wyoming as well as a couple
different states. And today I stand
before you just not as a citizen, as the
company that owns Bee Friendly Company.
I stand for you today not only as a
citizen, business owner, and defender of
the way of life that currently under
siege. We are told that progress
requires annexation, but I'm here to
remind the body that progress without
protection of our food and our right are
merely slow motion surrender of our
liberty. The nine most terrifying words
in the English language are, "I'm here
from the government and I'm here to help
you." That was Ronald Reagan's most
famous quote originally delivered in
August 12th, 1986, specifically
addressing American farmers argue that
the agriculture industry is a problem
and can be caused by government imposed
policies.
Our argument today is anchored in the
highest law of the land under the 14th
amendment of the United States
Constitution, the right for life. It is
suggested that is the mandated to
include the right of sustainability
maintain of a homestead and you're not
justified on a map that you're
unconstitutionally dividing and
conquering Wyoming rights of their
liberty and their property rights. The
federal government recognizes the
gratitude of this lefty under 7 United
States code 4201 the farmland protection
act policy. Federal agencies are
requiring to minimize the conversion of
farmlands to non-aggricultural use. Fur
furthermore, the 2018 Farm Bill 7USC
6923, the farmer to consumer direct
marketing that explicitly supports urban
agriculture and the right to produce and
look at the neighbors eye while you sell
them these products. Why is Cheyenne
moving to restrict the federal
government and moving forward on this
and incorporating not incorporating the
USDA, the AIPI and FM grants that allow
this to happen? Look at our state
statutes alone. The Wyoming state
statute 111401 through 11404.
The Wyoming right to farm ranch is our
property legal shield that protects the
forever guarantee. The right for farmers
to engage in agricultural operations
that are protected by very pillar of
this community. The state law is clear
and established farms cannot be declared
a nuisance and should be in the city
shall choose to expand along with the
Wyoming food a right and act of 114901
which provides our community without
governance or outreach that these laws
are ensured and our plain rights of food
production and producers remain free.
Right now, the Larmy County zoning
section 2 A1 and A2 protects any
liability of farm. The plan Cheyenne
comprehends explicitly calls the
protection of rural land and the perma
of UN of urban development. And yet here
we are. Well, the city supposedes to
draft the urban farm category for UDC
article 5 M
>> recently on the grounds. Yes,
>> your time is up. Could you conclude it
for us, please?
>> I certainly can. Um, I I hope that uh
it's kind of funny on this date that you
know you guys went on this because this
was the last date he could file for
$100,000 grant that you've now held mot
that he can't get. Uh, council members,
you have the power to uh uh honor the
anexection of properties, but we have
the spirit of HB76 that forces you to
say you can't do this anything for a
nuisance at previous urban farms. And I
appreciate your time and I hope you vote
against this annexation. Thank you very
much. Thank you, sir. Ma'am, did you
want to speak?
>> My name is Roxy Havl and I own track
number seven that you guys are trying to
annex and we just want to I don't have a
whole lot to say because you guys have
already heard everything we've said, but
I just wanted to get up here and let you
guys know that we are still opposed to
this. Um, we still don't have clear
writing of exactly what we can and
cannot do to our property. And I just
wanted to let you guys know that you
guys approving this data center that's
going in on college has actually
destroyed everything that we have ever
planned for this property. So I just
wanted to let you guys know that this is
affects our entire life and our future.
And so that's really all I have to say
that like just hope that you guys really
can consider this and and not vote us in
to this annexation since you've already
destroyed everything else. Thank you.
Ma'am,
>> good evening, Mr. Mayor and Council.
Thank you for taking the time to listen
to us. My name is Laura Lee and I live
in the Saddle Ridge neighborhood with my
family here in Cheyenne. We've known the
Nicely for a while and we've been a
Yresh customer. Um, we've gotten to know
the people in the area well. We're
concerned that in the city's reply to
question 123, the Wyoming right to farm
and act ranch act does not apply to
Yresh. As you know, farms are by nature
loud and contain things that may be
considered nuisances such as smells and
noise. Why has dogs, sheep, chickens,
and they have livestock guardian dogs
who are trained to protect their
animals.
City codes have rules about noise and
nuisances that wifer could undoubtedly
violate. If the state law does not
protect waifush, they will be fined and
penalized frequently. Nowhere does it
say for certain that the act supersedes
city codes. And again, I wanted to
reiterate what Tommy said about living
true to our western way of life and
being able to go and get the products
that we feel like we're on Little House
on the Prairie when we go and we get our
milk and our honey and everything else
that we get to get. That's I'm a retired
nurse and I'm a very into researching
all of the nutrition and I highly
recommend all of their products. Thank
you for your time. Thanks for being here
tonight,
Miss McCoy. How are you?
>> I'm good, thank you, mayor. My name is
Patricia McCoy and I live on the
southside. I'm here tonight because I'm
a frequent shopper at Wfresh. I rely on
their farm stand for my family's needs
and I want to voice my strong support
for them. I've followed the recent
discussions regarding their annexation
and I'm concerned that some of the
city's requirements don't align with the
reality of how this local business
operates. As a customer, safety is
important to me. I've taken my kids
there when they are little. I understand
the city has expressed life safety
concerns over electrical inspections.
However, it's my understanding that
WFresh has met every county requirement
to date when it comes to electrical.
Even when not legally required, they
went out of their way to have their work
done by a professional engineer and
reviewed by a licensed electrician. As a
member of the public, I appreciate that
they've gone above and beyond what was
asked of them to ensure their customers
are safe. Secondly, I'm concerned about
the city's intent to perform excessive
inspections. We all know how I feel
about inspections. [laughter]
Um, but this one is specifically
regarding septic systems. To anyone who
visits the stand, it's clear this is not
a permanent building. It's a mobile
structure on skids, similar to a food
cart or an RV. It isn't even connected
to a septic system.
Treating a mobile farm stand like a
permanent commercial development seems
like an unnecessary hurdle for a small
business that provides such a great
service to our neighborhood. Finally, I
am troubled by the idea that the city
might use the farm stands transition as
a reason to inspect every private
building on the property. These
buildings that the public, including
myself, never enters. Using a small
mobile farm stand trigger invasive
inspections of a person's entire private
property feels overreaching. I value
WFresh as a community asset and I hope
the council will work with them in a way
that is fair and grounded in the actual
nature of their setup. I want to see
WFresh continue to thrive in our city
and I hope you'll consider a more common
sense approach to these inspections.
Thank you,
>> sir. Welcome.
>> Thank you. Good [clears throat] evening.
I'm Scott Borisma, currently of Douglas
Wyoming, friends of Nisley's for over a
decade. I moved to Wyoming in part
because of the Food Freedom Act and the
opportunities it provided to people to
start small business with the customer
being the regulator. I mean, what kind
of thing is better than that than the
freedom to just go look in the eye, go
inspect the operation on their own. And
they've provided businesses for several
others around and through their stand
allowed us to support it. If those of
you with businesses on the council were
facing the unknowns that they're facing,
I don't know how they can handle it and
hand up to this stress right now. I am a
better speaker than this, but it just
just aggravates me to no end that we're
in this position. I ask you to please at
least give them an extension and not
annex them tonight. Thank you,
>> Scott. Thanks for coming down,
>> Kathy Sigiano.
Good evening, mayor and members of the
council. I'm here to speak tonight about
the situation involving why fresh
farmstand and forced annexation being
pursued by the city. What has been most
disappointing to many of us in this
community is not simply the policy
discussion around annexation. Reasonable
pe people can disagree on policy. What
has been troubling is the tone and
conduct that several members of this
body and even our mayor have directed
towards this family. This is a familyrun
farm stand that has done nothing but
work hard, serve the community, and
provide provide fresh local products to
residents. Yet, the way that they have
been spoken about in meetings and in
public comments has at times reduced
them to from being neighbors and a small
business owner to just obstacles.
That is not the kind of treatment that
reflects the values of Cheyenne. Whether
someone supports annexation or not,
basic respect should never be optional.
Public officials have a responsibility
to treat residents, especially those who
are simply trying to run a small
business and steward their prop private
property with dignity.
What we have seen instead are dismissive
remarks, accusations, and
characterizations that have felt
personal rather than professional. Those
are not just business owners on a map or
a line on a zoning document. These are
these are members of our community and
they are our neighbors and they deserve
fair treatment and civil discourse.
Government should never look like it is
bullying the citizens into submission
especially when those citizens are
simply asking for freedom to operate
their business and m maintain control of
their own private property.
This situation has left many residents
asking a simple question. If
hard-working local families can be
treated this way, what is the message
that is being sent to the rest of us?
Cheyenne should be a city that supports
local agriculture, small business, and
respectful dialogue, not one where
families feel pressured or disparaged
when they stand up for their property
rights. I urge this council to
reconsider not only the path forward on
annexation but also the tone conduct
that has been brought to us up to this
point. Our community deserves leadership
that reflects respect, fairness, and
humility. And I just want to say um Mr.
Wolf, you um through you mayor when he
was discussing the memorials, he made
great points about um not wanting people
to just come and take the property. And
that's just what we're asking and I
think that's what the nice less are
asking.
>> Thank you, Kathy.
Hello.
>> Hello. My name is Becky Boursma. Um
Scott Boursma is my husband and like you
said, we're from Douglas, Wyoming. We
also have a small farm and um sell
products at a local farm stand that is
within the city limits of Douglas. Um
I'm just here to also support the
Nisley's. Um, I guess I'm a little
I feel like
saying that there's plans in place, but
we don't get to know what they are is a
little is a little hard to swallow. I
guess at the very least, I would ask
that you don't annex them at this time.
Um, and like the lady just said, um,
when you discuss the memorials and you
talk about mourning, this is a type of
mourning. they're are losing their way
of life. Um, if you annex this and I
just um it needs more time at the very
least and um I just hope each of you
will take a second and say can I can I
give a straight face to the Nagley's and
say we did the we did the best that we
could. I think it needs more time and I
encourage you not to annex them and if
you still want to do that then I would
encourage you all to give them more time
please. Thank you.
>> Thanks for coming Becky.
Representative, welcome.
>> Thank you, Miss Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Uh, and council before us, uh, Jacob
Wasenberger, Ward One. I think I've
probably hashed this out several times
before, and I'm sure you guys have heard
me echo this, but when our founding
fathers have said it very clearly, one
who trades liberty for security deserves
neither. And one of the interesting
things is as far as this annexation
goes, that's one of the big things that
I keep hearing about on this topic is
that we're concerned for the safety. And
quite frankly, I mean, if people want to
have the ability to make those choices
for themselves, I mean, let the citizen
do that rather than than our government
doing that.
Um, [clears throat]
I mean, the free market will take care
of those type of issues. and it sounds
like they're doing a really good job. I
look forward to getting a chance to uh
talk with them a little bit more about
this particular issue.
But, uh, you know, I mean, as a as a
mayor and a city council of a city, I I
think, you know, that'd be a really
prideful thing, especially for the state
of Wyoming that, you know, hey, welcome
to Cheyenne. We've got a farm in our
city that's, you know, and they are
their own independent farm. I mean, we
just showed how much pride we've got for
having the rodeo team come here to
Wyoming. I I think that'd be something
pretty cool to have a lot of pride that
we've got a we've got an independent
farm here in our in our city. That's,
you know, welcome to Wyoming and the
cowboy way of life. So, I would just
like to ask the body to please vote no
on this uh annexation because I mean,
just the message that I get from the
people when I go out and talk to people
is pretty clear that it's just not
something that they really favor. And I'
really appreciate the body to take that
into consideration that
uh that it's just not been something
that a lot of people have been favorable
of. So uh please allow people to have
their freedom and uh please also realize
that that's what our founding father
said is when you trade liberty for
security, you deserve neither. Thank you
for your time,
>> representative. Thank you. Thanks for
your service section, sir.
>> Welcome. Thank you, Mr. Mayor, city
council. Um, my name is Gary Pew. I'm
resident of Cheyenne Ward One. Wyoming
believes in rights, not just in words,
in law. In 1979, the state passed
Wyming's right to farm and ranch act. It
declares that the rights of farmers and
ranchers shall never be shall be forever
guaranteed in this state. Not permitted,
not licensed, not approved, guaranteed.
Wyoming Fresh Farm operated on that land
before the surrounding neighborhood was
built. Under Wyoming law, that history
matters. A farm that produces or
predates a change in the surrounding
land use is protected. That isn't an
argument. It's a statute. But the city
of Cheyenne in its written response to
Werash has said that the right to farm
act does not appear to cover the
activities of Werush. The city has
decided on its own that this farm is not
a farm. Think about what that means. The
moment annexation occurs, the city has
[snorts] said livestock or are a right
in an egg zone. But its official
response is use the phrase approved
livestock. If something must be
approved, it is not a right. Wine Fresh
has been told it must file documentation
and keep updating it. Just to have a
year on and year off birds. Rotating
animals between seasons is about as
basic as farming gets. If you need
ongoing permission to do something, it's
not a right. It's a privilege subject to
revocation. Consider free speech. You
don't need a permit to write a book. The
moment government requires permission
before you exercise a right, it stops
being a right. Now, consider the Wyoming
Constitution, Article One. Section seven
says that, excuse [clears throat] me,
absolute arbitrary power over the
property of free people exists nowhere
in a republic. The legislature has
already declared agriculture vital to
Wyoming's economy and guaranteed farm
rights forever. A city cannot override
that declaration with declaration
without a zoning map change. Article 1,
section six guarantees due process
before any property is taken away and
the right to farm is a property right.
Article 19 commands the legislature to
protect stock owners.
Annexation that quietly dismantles those
protections directly defies that
command. So here's the concrete ask. If
annexation proceeds, the zoning
classification assigned to this property
must grant full unrestricted conforming
use rights to every agricultural
practice already underway. Any framework
requiring WFresh to seek approval for
standard farm operation, excuse me,
contradicts Wyoming law and sets up this
farm's elimination by paperwork.
Wyoming law is clear. The question is
whether this council intends to honor
it. Thank you.
Hello again, sir.
Don ODM Cheyenne
I'd just like to start with saying any
or or when we look at the the news these
days in the last few years at all the
health issues Americans and Wyoming have
from uh industrial farming and upside
down food pyramid that we were fed for
years. um any thing that inhibits or
limits
uh our ability as Cheyenne residents to
eat local, fresh, safe food is just
flatout wrong. And I would really ask
that you vote against this. And I have a
couple more reasons to add. Um
some of the language on this is just not
clear enough. Wfresh has been told that
you would probably not ever need
off-site
improvements if they were to expand on
their on their private property.
Probably is not good enough. There's no
definitive quantifiable
uh language that really protects them.
they could make an investment in their
farm and then the city decides, well, I
think we will require these
improvements. It's subjective. It's
unfair and in my opinion, it's
unconstitutional. Thank you for your
time.
>> You got the memo in the green today. I
see. Ma'am,
>> welcome.
Um, [clears throat]
my name is Danell Pew and I'm a
registered voter and resident of
Cheyenne's Ward One. The Nicely family
has farmed this land for years.
They have fed their neighbors.
They have been good stewards
of something that is rare in a city, a
living piece of working ground
that this community can see and touch
and eat from. When they learned
annexation was coming, they did not
fight. They asked questions,
143 of them. They attended every
meeting. They came to this chamber and
asked politely, then urgently for
written answers they could rely on. The
city gave them hedges. It gave them,
it's our belief, it is our
understanding. On the question of
connecting to the sanitation system
alone, they were told three different
things in the same day. And now the
council is posed to approve this forced
annexation. Here's what is true. Zoning
violations in Cheyenne can be criminal
offenses. Under state law, a municipal
court can impose fines and jail time per
violation.
Tommy nicely stood at the microphone and
she said that she did not want to be the
first person jailed for moving a
caterpillar tunnel without a sight plan.
This is not hyperbole. This is the
city's code. The family tried. The
process failed. You failed them. Wyoming
law gives citizens a remedy. Under
Wyoming law, a certified referendum
petition suspends this ordinance and
puts this question to the voters of
Cheyenne where it belongs. We will
circulate the petition. We will reach
the threshold and we will give the
city's voters the chance to do what this
city council did not. Protect their
home, save their farm. Thank you.
Mr. Brown.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor, and thank you,
city council. Exy Brown, Ward Two. I'm
here to uh respectfully ask that you
vote no on this annexation or that you
table this thing for at least the next
one to two years. And the reason I say
that
is because, and even uh Mr. Bloom made
one of my points that I was going to
make. There is no codified definition of
what an urban farm is. There's no clear
definition of what one is. And with all
the questions that are still out there
that haven't been answered and the may
and the buts and this might happens uh
coming from the answers they're getting,
uh it seems like we're just kind of
trying to make up the rules as we're
going along. Almost like we're flying by
the seat of our pants. And that ladies
and gentlemen is just not good
governance.
So what I recommend is that this needs
to be taken up with the legislature to
provide statute to have a clear and
concise definition of what an urban farm
is and what urban agriculture is. and
WHAM could work with the legislature on
this and also define or define what the
rules are and have parameters and a
framework to work in so that everybody
knows the rules. The council knows the
rules, the city departments know the
rules, and the people that own family
farms and that own urban farms and dairy
barns know the rules. Now folks, ladies
and gentlemen, most of you on here know
my feelings on annexation. If if people
are for it, proceed. Go ahead. But if
those are against it, I believe it is an
incumbent upon this body to not only
listen to the people, but do the will of
the people. And I think the will of the
people out here have spoke very loud and
clearly since the beginning of this. So,
ladies and gentlemen, I urge a no vote
or that this thing gets tabled for a
year or two so we can get the rules
clear, concise, and everybody knows what
rules we're playing by. Thank you.
>> Good evening.
[snorts]
>> Hi.
>> Can you pull that down? There you go.
>> Thank you. My name is Tatiana, Mr.
Mayor, city members, council members.
Thank you for listening to us today. Um,
I drive up from Colorado.
>> Can you pull that as close as you can
because we're having a real hard time
hearing you?
>> Yeah.
>> There you go. That's much better.
>> Sorry about that.
>> Do you want me to repeat myself? Nope.
No. Okay. I just wanted to um I drive up
from Colorado to come to the farm stand.
I have some food allergies that don't
allow me to drink like regular milk or
eat egg from the store. And thanks to um
Life Fresh Farm and all the farmers that
contribute to that farm stand, I'm able
to have uh milk and certain eggs and
other produce. Um one point I wanted to
talk about regarding this um one of the
issues with annexation if it were to
proceed is the fencing. So, um the fence
is the first line of defense against
predators and why fresh fence um has
been damaged by the city and that was
promised to be fixed back in 2024
and they're now just now starting to
work on fixing it and they confirmed
that that won't be done by the proposed
annexation date. um after annexation if
it were to proceed by fresh is limited
in what it can do to ward off predators.
Uh many like last resort solutions such
as use of firearms are not allowed
within the city and if um primary means
of protection fails, livestock is
defenseless. Um wer will have to will
have fewer option to defend livestock
from predators after annexation. The
current fence, even if it was fixed,
would need to be improved to make up for
these lost options. So, electric fence,
which is an econ economical option, it's
not allowed in the city without specific
exception. Why fresh does not have these
exception. Making a taller, better
fence, um better like defended fence
will cost about uh $50,000.
Um, I would like to add my family moved
in 1996 to America from Ukraine. Um, for
looking for a better life, for hope, a
better future. And I love that there's
farms out there that are looking out not
just for themselves. They're actually
looking to feed other people. And
they're allowing what, 50 other farmers
to sell their own pro product there at
their farm stand. Um, so it's it doesn't
make them any money. It feeds the people
of Wyoming and Colorado. Um, gives us
hope. And if there was something like a
famine, God forbid, like we will be
grateful for farmers who do the work and
allow us to have access to food. Thank
you,
>> Tatiana. You're amaz your English is
amazing.
>> Thank you.
>> Congratulations. Thanks for being here.
>> Thank you, sir.
Hello, Governor. I mean, I mean the
mayor. I'm sorry about that. Mayor and
the whole body of the of the people, you
know. Uh I'm Brian Pixley here and I'm
gonna point blank say I'm I don't want
you guys annexing the these poor people,
you know. I I constantly say on Facebook
constantly constantly, you know, don't
pass it, don't pass it. You know, you
know, the people are speaking, you know,
let people get what they want and let
let the let them have what they want is
no on on why fresh so zero. Thank you.
>> Thanks for being here.
>> Hi ma'am,
>> mayor and city council. My name is Vera
Booth. The growth of Yfresh and the hard
work of this family has clearly
demonstrated our community is seeking
local produce and products.
40 years ago, Shane Smith started a
farmers market in Cheyenne to encourage
locals to continue to grow food, to have
someplace to sell their extra, and make
Cheyenne more self- sustaining. All of
which are very wise. Now Cheyenne has
two farmers markets, but they're just
during the summer months and none on the
south side. Why is open five days a week
year round and is fueling our local
economy.
My concern and I think the concern of
the Nicely family is that their family
business upon annexation is subject
constantly to approval for one thing or
another and those regulations can
change.
The city rec responded with written
information and yet with each question
the city seemed to leave an open door
for themselves to approve or close this
business.
This has and will continue to be a
source of anxiety for the nicestly
family, the producers and the consumers
and the unknown additional financial
cost will continue to be theirs.
The reason that there were 147 questions
and responses
is that it the reason it took so much
time.
The reason that this has been a struggle
is because a farm and a city are two
different entities.
It's like trying to force a square peg
into a round hole.
The city wrote that non-conforming use,
which they were offering the wife, could
be lost by three reasons.
There's more than that. But they said if
they voluntarily cease the use of a
continuous period for a continuous
period of one year after which the use
may not be reestablished under such and
such a code.
So what if a disease decimates their
livestock or their crops or their health
problems and their family for a year? Do
you think they could begin again? I'm
sure that they could, but only with
approval.
The second way, and the city went out to
clarify this, any change in intensity,
location, or expansion of the operation
would trigger a site plan requirement
approved by the board of adjustment and
an unknown fee?
How can you grow a business without
changing intensity or expansion?
What if the city decides they want a
different use of this property, then
they just don't approve something?
Don't force annexation.
Let them stay county. They run a clean
operation because that matters to them
and to their customers. They know how to
do this. This is a wholesome enterprise
Cheyenne should be supporting. We
benefit from this pocket of county in
our city. When you try to convert a farm
to a city, it doesn't work for either
side.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
Welcome again.
>> I'm Donnie Carrer. Word three Cheyenne
Wyoming. Obviously, I'm uh in support of
the Wresh family. Hope the city council
I hope this governing body can still do
their best to work with this family. Um
but I want to talk about something that
I haven't heard anything or anybody
stand up here and talk about. It seems
like there's this rift between governing
bodies, civil servants, and its people.
We've heard I still to this day I
haven't heard one person stand up here
and support you guys. It's you guys as a
body at a governing body against all of
us. What does that look like to
everybody? Now, there's a lot of people
that probably don't follow politics.
They probably don't watch this as much
as other people, but I'm absolutely
appalled and shocked that we have a
governing body. And Mr. Mayor, I'm going
to call you out on it. When you sit here
and say that Robert's rules supersedes
Supreme Court constitutional law 1964
Sullivan versus New York Times to
criticize our representatives, including
if that use vuler language, regardless
if you like it or not, you work for us.
And I'm not going to sit here and go
into anything else. I'm trying to make a
point that the people have been speaking
about this for well over a month now.
I'm not saying that you guys have been
totally
nose or stick your nose up. I know that
you guys are doing work. But it's also
been very clear that you guys also had a
goal when you got into office, mayor.
You very clearly had a plan from start
until now that no matter what, hell or
high water, you were going to annex
these properties, that you were going to
annex these pockets. And when we can't
even clap, that's ridiculous. Clapping
takes up a few seconds. I get it. There
should be some decorum. But to sit here
and tell me that I can't criticize
somebody and that you want to take away
my right, it's the same thing that we
see when you don't listen to the right
of the people that are asking for this
annexation to stop. If I want to sit
here and say Pete Leborn's a snob, I'm
going to say it. If I want to say that
Mr. Wolf is condescending, I'm going to
say it.
>> And if not, then you can take me to
court.
>> And I'll really excuse me. This is my
this is my time, Mr. Mayor. With all due
respect, I have 52 seconds. The point
that I'm making is is you guys put a
rift even more. We respect that you guys
have a tough job. We really do. But when
you don't clearly listen to the voice of
the people, it pisses me off and I don't
have to cater or play counsel or play
governing with anybody. I'm a human
being. I'm going to speak what I feel.
Stop this. Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Hi. I've never done this before. Um, I'm
Colleen Shazitz. I've known Tommy since
we were in third grade, and we grew up
together in this great city of Cheyenne.
Um, and she's one of the kindest people
I know. I ask for transparency,
cooperation, consideration, and at the
very least more time for the nicely to
work with you and to you, for you to
work with them in a calm, clear manner.
Please don't pass this annex tonight.
Give this situation more time. Thank
you.
>> Thanks for being here. representative.
Well, we have all we might have a quorum
of Laramie Countyy's House of
Representatives here today.
>> Corporations, [snorts]
>> the corporations committee. Do we do you
guys notice this meeting or
>> Mr. Mayor? Thank you,
>> Mr. Brown. Welcome.
>> Gary Brown, House District 41 and
resident of W.
Um, had several of my constituents get a
hold of me in the last week or so. Very
concerned about this situation. Um, as
you know, my my district's in the heart
of Cheyenne. these people travel out to
Farm or Whitefresh to uh to do business
there and and they've been very
concerned about that. I had one of my
constituents wave me over today when I
was passing through the neighborhood.
And I won't use his language,
but he wanted me to come and express his
concern about this. And [snorts] he
said, you know, he he told me, he said,
Gary, he says, I'm really very concerned
about what's going on in this city right
now because it seems like we have
nothing to say anymore. and he said,
"Maybe what we need to do is a complete
change." And I told him, I said, 'You
know, that's up to you and it's up to
you to to to talk with your neighbors
like that or whatever you want to do.
But the thing is, this farm is part of
Cheyenne has been forever. And I heard
earlier, Mr. Bloom a concern about
possibly moving in uh there would be a
problem with moving in 40 head of
cattle. Well, if you know anything about
ranching and farming in Wyoming and
Colorado, you know that that land would
not support 40 head of cattle. It just
doesn't happen. So, that is a ridiculous
thing to even be bringing up. So, I
think that's a little bit beyond the
pale. So, my thing is we just need to um
step back, take a look at this, give
these people a chance. They've been
there for a long time.
just let them go on about their lives
and do the business they've been doing.
They support this city. So, thank you.
>> Appreciate you being here. Another
member of the corporations committee,
representative, welcome.
>> We do not have a quorum.
>> Okay, just checking. [laughter]
>> So, good to have you here.
>> Thank you. Um, and I just used 10
seconds on that, so remember that when I
go 10 seconds over. Good evening, Mr.
Mayor and members of the council. I'm
pleased to be here. My name is Anne
Lucas and I represent Wyoming's House
District 43 in the Wyoming legislature.
That includes parts of WS one and three.
I've heard a lot about this issue, of
course, not from just the media, but
from my constituents, from people all
over the city and the county.
What's happening here tonight is an
issue that goes to the heart of the
relationship between citizens and their
government.
What is happening here tonight is not a
boundary line on a map. It's about a
small local farm that's been serving
this community and my family, growing
food, supporting local producers, and
now facing the possibility of being
pulled into the city limits against its
will. And with that comes city
regulations, zoning restrictions,
possibly new taxes, and even the
possibility of criminal penalties if the
farm doesn't conform to city codes. That
should concern everyone. I think it
concerns a lot of folks here this
evening, and I've heard this again and
again and again, and so have you because
annexation is not strictly
administrative. It is a government
expanding its authority over people who
don't ask for it. The question tonight
is a simple one. Who does government
serve? The planning department does not
elect you. The machinery of government
does not elect you. The people elect
you. And the people affected by this
decision have been showing up meeting
after meeting asking you to slow down,
reconsider, and listen. I'm asking you
to do the same.
Property rights are one of the most
fundamental principles in Wyoming. When
government reaches out to take
jurisdiction over someone's land against
their wishes, it should only happen with
overwhelming jur justification, not
simply because it's convenient or
desirable for the city. In Wyoming, we
believe that if someone is working their
land, feeding their community, and
minding their own business, government's
first instinct should be to leave them
alone. Local government works best when
it remembers its proper role. You do not
work for the government. You work for
the people. And tonight I ask you,
please remember this who you work for
because the people of this community are
watching and they will remember whether
their city council stood with the
citizens or with the expansion of
government. As we say in the house, I am
on and against this. I encourage you to
be against this also. Thank you very
much. Thanks for being here,
>> Miss Johnson. Welcome.
>> Well, thank you, Mr. Mayor and City
Council. I would just like to say that
our Constitution allows us to own
property. The Fifth Amendment gives us
the right to own property. Whatever
regulations or zoning regulations you
put on this farm will be a taking. You
are taking away their ability to make a
living. It's going to cost them money.
It's one way or another. Whatever rules
you have is is going to influence their
their income and that's a taking
according to the fifth amendment. I I
just say this is not ready for prime
time and maybe a year or two can get all
figured out but I would put this on hold
for now. Thank you.
>> Thanks for being here.
>> Welcome.
>> Hi, I'm Richard Lyall. I live in the
incorporated area of the city of
Cheyenne. I am not uh a representative
of any organization or any organized uh
group.
>> Pull that microphone up, mister.
>> Oh, okay. I'm opposed to the annexation
for several reasons. First of all, the
city did not reach out to the residents
before they put together the uh plan of
an annexation.
They were working on this from 2022,
2023, 2024,
without talking to the affected
residents. Um there's a question as to
whether or not they've the city has
complied with the mandatory statutory
requirements of giving notice to the
residents and that the that notice
should include maps and other required
documents.
Um now the annexation plan should
be looked at
uh you look look at the within the four
corners of the written plan. It's not
what uh Mr. Bloom says or what uh
members of the council think or
speculate to. It's got to be in the four
corners of the plan written down
and
u
you can't just say conclusions the facts
there must be evidence stated that
supports the facts. Now this annexation
plan well one issue is protection of
wildlife.
The plan as stated in the uh
supplementary
um statement from uh city planning is
under discharge of firearms and
livestock protection.
Discharge of firearms within the city is
prohibited except in designated ranges.
Alternative wildlife and nuisance animal
control measures are available. Contact
information for the police department.
um was given to the uh uh property
owners.
What does that mean? Al what are these
alternatives? They're not stated in the
plan.
What are they? Poison?
No, that's not a good, you know, putting
up signs. Well, the coyotes don't read
the signs.
Look, they're trying to raise chickens
and provide eggs. You know,
you have to keep the coyotes away from
the chickens.
Now, I have a suggestion here. The city
could pass an ordinance which would
allow residents in an aggra designated
agriculture zone to use firearms if they
register in advance. So, they're not
just somebody coming into the
neighborhood.
that they specify what firearms they're
using, so they're not using a, you know,
an AK-47 or something, and that they can
only use them for the defense of against
predators, not for target shooting, not
to celebrate the Fourth of July,
you know.
>> Thank you, Mr.
>> That is something that could Am I up?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. I I would just like to uh say that
we all live in Wyoming and what we do as
Wyoming, we look out for our neighbors
and our friends and their welfare. Thank
you.
>> Thanks for being here.
>> Representative,
>> uh Mr. Mayor, members of the council, uh
Daniel Singh, representative from House
District 61. and I'm not a member of the
corporations committee. Uh but I just
wanted to take a little bit of time. Uh
I've spoken before about annexation and
uh in the time since that conversation,
I've thought a lot about this issue. Um
it's not as clear-cut as a a lot of us
would like it to be. There are simple
realities when it comes to the
administration of government services
such as uh you know the the main example
is public safety whether it's fire or
law enforcement and I recognize the
complexity of those issues and those
aren't things that will go away
overnight. Um, and and just to be
perfectly clear, I I would ask that uh
that this body consider tableabling this
motion as it's written right now, this
agenda item, uh, and give it a little
bit more time to bake in the oven. Um,
and I appreciate uh you, Mr. Mayor, and
Dr. Renie, and Dr. Aldrich, and uh, Mr.
Moody and everybody else who I've seen
during this uh budget session who made
themselves available to um share their
perspective on various issues with
members of the legislature on things
that would be impactful for the city.
And uh just know that when you guys
spoke to me, I listened and we ended up
with things that benefited our community
as a whole. And I'm I'm hoping that
we're able to work together on this. Not
in the spirit of us versus them, but as
we move forward to finding a practical
solution, we can walk together with a
policy that's our policy. That's a we
policy, not an us versus them policy.
And I'm hoping that we're able to do
that. Uh and really, I've been since
since the beginning of this testimony,
uh I could only really think about one
thing, and that was uh McDonald's. Uh,
[laughter] and uh, just uh, we had the
analogy with McDonald's and uh, I'd like
to say that, you know, when I when I go
to McDonald's, I'll go I'll drive
through the drive-thru and I'll uh, I'll
get myself a Big Mac. Okay? And, uh, if
I if I go in and I open the bag, I'm
back on my couch uh, and I open up I
take a bite of this Big Mac and they
forgot the sauce. What's going on? I I I
would be upset if I didn't have the
sauce in my Big Mac. And I'm afraid that
this policy doesn't have the sauce, Mr.
Mayor. Uh we need to work on it just a
little bit more. Uh table this for the
time being and uh we can find a
practical solution. I think that the
members involved are amicable to working
together and it just it really is a
matter of time. we can come out with
something that uh that as the entire
state looks as looks at us looks at
Cheyenne to find a solution how are we
going to move forward what are other
cities going to do when they find
themselves in similar situations I would
hate for us to hastily try to find a
solution that isn't quite there and I
ask for your favorable consider well yes
listen to the people yeah
>> so I went I went to McDonald's so we'll
finish that that that to commercial. I
had a cookie here for later from
McDonald's. So, thank you,
[snorts] sir. Welcome.
Jerry Ditto, Ward One.
I have a general disinterest in
politics. Up until two weeks ago, I had
no idea who the mayor or the members of
the city council were. However, I saw a
post on Facebook that got me interested
in this specific issue. And in order to
educate myself, I watched the city
council meeting that took place on the
23rd in its entirety twice.
>> Good for you.
>> To say I am disappointed would be an
understatement.
It is apparent to me that the city has
not taken into account the complexity
inherent in operating an urban farm. It
would be bad enough if a lack of
understanding were the only issue, but
it is clear that the city is unaware of
this ignorance.
This is not an insult, but rather a
statement of fact.
Councilman Lelaybornne remarked that a
question about whether leash law would
apply would apply to barn cats was not
and I quote serious. This question was
cherrypicked because it is easy to point
and laugh and pretend that it is naive
or ridiculous.
In reality, this question is serious
enough that there's an entire initiative
in the city code that delineates what a
community cat is and which laws
regarding pets in general do or do not
apply.
mocking a layman's lack of familiarity
with city code is not a good look.
Councilman Wolf remarked that a large
number of hours had already been spent
on this issue and that this time would
be better spent on the other, again, I
quote, 65,000 minus two inhabitants of
Cheyenne.
Not only is this statement a gross
misrepresentation of the number of
people that will be affected by this
annex, but again, it illustrates a
measure of ignorance. Councilman, this
is quite literally your job.
However frustrated any member of this
council might feel, I can assure you
that the nicely and their patrons have
been experiencing that frustration
tenfold.
It has taken time for the citizens of
Cheyenne to become a prize of the
situation, and every day more are
becoming aware. We will not stand idly
by while the livelihood of hardworking
law-abiding people is put at risk simply
because the city council is too
impatient to complete its annex before
the city code is updated to protect
their right to farm. There are 245,500
give or take words in the city code and
the word farm appears twice
in reference to farm machinery and its
exemption from registration
requirements.
The city is not ready for an urban farm
and the only responsible course of
action today is to delay this annexation
until such time as a city becomes ready.
Thank you.
>> Welcome.
>> Good evening, Mayor Collins and uh city
council members. My name is Steve Millia
from Cheyenne. And I would like to say
that I uh ditto owe everyone else who's
been talking against this uh annexation.
And Miss Nicely had mentioned something
that struck me, our western heritage.
And we have more data setters coming in.
And I think we're sort of losing that uh
western heritage. And we have a uh we're
not New York, we're not Denver, we're
not even Fort Collins. And we have a
blue moon project that came in here to
help contribute to our western heritage.
Well, we have a green shirt project out
here that wants to continue our western
heritage and I think that's really
important. So, the uh question would be
what's the hurry as far pushing all this
way through. So, we want to have a blue
moon project uh and we have a green
shirt project. Let's continue our
western heritage here with an urban farm
that people will come and say this is
really Wyoming. This is really Cheyenne.
We don't want to see all New York City
moving here. We don't even want to see
Fort Collins moving. We want to keep
Cheyenne as Cheyenne. I appreciate your
time and I thank you uh for my ability
to speak. Thank you,
>> Miss McCort. Welcome.
>> Hi, uh Chelsea [snorts] McCord again. Um
I hope that the amount of speakers, just
the sheer number, help illustrate to you
how important this is to the community.
Um, when annexing a territory, as you
guys probably well know, uh, Wyoming
statute 1512402
requires a few conditions to be met. The
first of those being, quote, "An
annexation of the area is for the
protection of the health, safety, and
the welfare of the persons residing in
the area.
I believe and I hope that it has been
illustrated to you throughout this whole
process that this annexation without
significant changes does not fulfill the
stipulation.
Annexation imposes on WFresh a number of
procedurally complicated rules and
regulations. To date, the city has not
yet faced the problem of incorporating
an urban farm. We truly appreciate that
they are willing to work to adapt,
modify, and explain the rules to us. We
as in WFresh are also willing to
compromise to try to fit within those
rules and stipulations. But that does
not dismiss the fact that those
compromises and those solutions have not
actually been put in place yet. We are
hearing from you guys. Trust us,
everything will be fine. And I truly
personally believe that it could be
fine. But there are things that
factually need addressed. I am more sure
about this now than ever having met with
the city department heads earlier this
morning. There is a potential to help
create something wonderful. But the
thing that we need to create that is
time. That is the one specific element
that is missing from this whole process
is time. And that is the thing that you
city council can provide for us.
We are not asking for stressful
treatment because we feel that we
deserve it. Um, incorporating an urban
farm was always going to present an
issue to you guys, whether it be now or
later. This is not a two-person issue
between the residents of the farm and
the city of Cheyenne.
It is a community issue. This is an
issue Cheyenne will continue to face as
it continues to outwardly expand and
ever increasingly butt up against rural
agricultural lands. So, let's just
address this now.
If you are listen, if you have listened,
you are aware there are problems. You
are aware that there is an issue with
annexing Wfresh as it stands today.
So if you choose to proceed, you are
ignoring those facts and you are
ignoring the loud voice of the public.
They have spoken. They support WFresh
and they are aware of these problems.
The entire purpose of you guys of the
city council is to listen to the voices
of your constituents and make decision
based on what is best for them and what
they want. So do that. Thank you.
>> Good evening ma'am. Welcome.
>> I've never done this before. So
>> pull that microphone down a little bit.
There you go.
>> Hi. My name is Carol Atkinson. The first
thing I'd like to say to you guys is
this is my first time. So, I may be
stumbling. I have been watching this
unfold and unfold. I never get out of my
chair. I never do nothing. Guess what?
It's time to do something. When my
country says it's time to eat healthy,
Senator Kennedy says it's time to eat
healthy. His fighter Mike Tyson, who's
in his corner, God wish we could have
Tyson here because these guys are our
Tyson. Okay? They want us to eat
healthy. They want us to eat food that's
not bought out of a grocery store that's
rotten by the time we get it home.
They want us to eat food that's not
sprayed with pesticides that nobody can
tell us what it is. I have a brain
injury and it's very important for me to
eat those kind of fresh foods. So when
you guys as you, whichever ones it is of
you, because I don't know which ones it
is, decide that you make the decisions
for my health, my well-being, the
children in our community, the people in
our community, I think you've went too
far. Okay. The other thing I have to
say, again, Senator Kennedy and Mike
Tyson are going after schools for the
way they are feeding our children.
why you as city council members are not
going after and supporting the people
that want to live better lives.
It's just a question you should ask
yourself and the mayor tonight when you
go home.
Thank you
>> for your first time. You did great.
Thank you for being here.
>> Good evening.
>> Hello.
>> Welcome.
>> Hi. All right. So, my first time also,
so I apologize if I mess up. Um actually
not a city resident. I live in the
county. Um, my husband and I own a
couple businesses here in Cheyenne. We
do a lot with our state.
>> Can you identify yourself for the
record?
>> I'm Hannah Fields.
>> Hannah, welcome.
>> Yeah, thanks. Um, so I've known the
Nicely for a long time. Not only are
they amazing farmers, they're amazing
people. Um, former foster parents as
well, which is a great benefit to our
community. Um, on top of everything they
do in the farming world. Um, I'm here
tonight to respectfully voice opposition
to the proposed annexation of the local
farm property. This land is more than
just open space on a map. It represents
agricultural heritage, local food
production, and a piece of our
community's identity. Annexing and
developing this land would permanently
remove farmland that has served our area
um and a lot of us for a long time now.
Um Mr. Bloom addressed the traffic
pattern in the area. And that does bring
up the question of has there actually
been a traffic pattern issue? Um just
something that came to mind. Um, I was
in Fort Collins with my children
yesterday and rough feed lot in Fort
Collins is just off of Harmony Road on
Ziggler Road in a very suburban area.
There's schools there, businesses there,
everything. Um, I can't say how many
cattle they have. I didn't stop to
count, but they have a sizable amount of
cattle on a property that's smaller than
what the Nicely have. I don't think they
plan on putting in a feed lot. Um, but I
do think it's worth noting that there
are ways for even cities like Fort
Collins to make this work and we're
Cheyenne and not Fort Collins,
thankfully. So, I think that there are
ways for us to make this work as well.
Um, growth and development are
important, but they should be balanced
with thoughtful preservation of the
spaces that make our community unique.
Once that farmland is gone, it can't be
replaced. I encourage the council to
carefully consider the long-term impacts
of annexation and to prioritize
solutions that protect agricultural land
while planning responsibly for the
future of our community. We're excited
to celebrate the Wyoming cowboy cowboy
culture, you know, as evidenced by this
big PRCA thing coming in. Um, but that
culture wouldn't have been possible
without the pioneers, the farmers, the
homesteaders, the business owners, and
the community. That is also worth
celebrating. Cowboys are great. So are
the rest of us. victory farms might be
making a comeback, you know, way the
world is going. Um, so why are we
blocking people who are paving the way
for that? These are the people that are
teaching the rest of us how to grow
gardens. They're teaching the rest of us
how to feed our families, how to raise
our chickens, how to do all of this. Um,
we're all Wyoming proud and that Wyoming
way of life is what we want for our
children. And that includes freedoms to
live how we feel is best for our
families, our community, and to use the
land we're stewarding to benefit all as
well does. Thank you for your time.
>> Thanks for being here.
Mr. Love,
[snorts]
>> Mr. Mayor, members of the council, my
name is Steven Love. I live in Ward One.
I'm saddened that we're here today. Um,
I think so many people have been
fighting really hard for this. Um, I
wish it could have been resolved before
now. I think the only reason that you
see the members of the public fill the
room today wearing green is because of
an overzealous agenda that is being
forced down the throats of citizens of
Cheyenne and the county alike. This is
not a partisan issue. This is not an
issue for one or two people. This is a
shining example of systemic overreach by
the council. The council as a whole, and
I know there has been members in
opposition, but as a whole has passed
woefully unpopular ordinance in the last
several months and years, not limited to
flock, cameras, administrative warrants,
and many others infringing on our
rights. Let's make history and put a
stop to that tonight. No one wants this
annexation for pocket 4. The nicely have
bent over backwards trying to provide
you with information about how they
could reasonably proceed, and that
information has fallen on deaf ears.
They were not just wanting a stay of
execution for WFresh so they could ask
questions. They were hoping to find a
way to survive as a business and a farm
with this annexation. Well, you answered
the questions and one thing seems clear.
Under the current rules and regulations,
they may not survive. And if they do, it
will be because of pure pure
determination and grit of their family
and community, not with any help, I
assure you, from this council. So, at
this time, I would ask that the council
remove pocket four from this annexation.
It was represented that there was there
would be time, money, and man-hour
involved in removing them. And the
subtext that it would be was that it
would be inconvenient to the city. To
that I say, good, fantastic. Do your
jobs. That is what we pay taxes for. We
would not pay taxes if it was easy. We
would get by on volunteer work. But it's
not easy. That's why city employees are
paid a salary to do the inconvenient,
difficult thing. If you can can't find
it in your heart tonight to do the
reasonable thing and remove this
property from annexation at minimum
delay this annexation
until zoning regulation that properly
completely and formally protects these
people way of life people's way of life
can be codified that is a formal
recognition of an urban farm zone and
the protections that it would entail the
current AG designation comes up well
short of what is needed to run a farm as
you vote vote tonight. Please consider
all the testimony you have heard from
your constituents and community members
from the county alike. No one in is in
favor of this ordinance. No one vote to
remove parcel 4. Uh vote for the
livelihood of the nicely. As Dr. Aldrich
has said, it's time to throw the baby
out of the bathtub. Thank you.
>> Welcome, sir.
>> Good evening, Mr. mayor, city council
members, city staff and audience. My
name is Glenn Connor. I live on 1304
Broken Arrow Road. I've been before this
panel here for many, many years. And you
can see the gray hairs on the mayor, but
you can see them on me, too. So, we we
buted heads more than once over
annexation. I've gone 26 years
annexation free. So, I just want that
stated for the record tonight. I know
the mayor's looking at me like, well,
maybe we should just step out the back
door here. But anyway, I take them to
McDonald's and buy them as shakes when I
do. So,
>> and they're green right now. They're
Shamrock Shakes. It'd be perfect,
wouldn't it?
>> There you go. Anyway, I'm here tonight
to support the farm. I feel that th this
farm is is one that uh you know, they've
been in operation for years. There's no
sense in in changing the the regulations
out out there and and forcing these
people to pay higher taxes, forcing them
to tie into city water and sewer. I know
eventually I'm going to have to. I'm
surrounded. I'm 75% surrounded right
now. The mayor's notes, I read the
mayor's minutes all the time. 75 to
100%. So, I'm 75% right now on Southwest
Drive. I'm I'm kind of out by the animal
shelter. So, you can see the dilemma
that I'm in, too, because I'm retired
now. You know, I'm looking at $14,000
tap fee, probably another six to $7,000
to hook up my water and sewer because
when I put my home on the property, I
didn't place it on the property where I
thought the city water lines and sewer
lines would come through. So, it's going
to be a big burden for me in the future.
People say, "Well, you can recuperate
that from the sale of your home." I
don't want to sell my home. I've lived
in Cheyenne all these years. I love this
community, you know, but I'm going
before a panel here that I never ever
had the opportunity to vote for.
Is that not unamerican? I mean, if it's
if if I'm wrong, somebody stand up and
tell me right now. But to me, I've I've
been before these people for years.
Would I become one of these members up
here? I have family members that may run
in the future. They're young now.
They've talked about it. But I I'm
looking at
why what's the big hurry? Dr. Ryan, you
you said, sir, that we're in a big
hurry. We have a time frame here. What's
the time frame and why do we have to do
it right away? I would I would work with
these people for a long long time and
have everything planned out. You you've
put the cart before the horse again. And
I've said that many a times down here.
You know, I I I just feel that let's
give them some time and look at this
from a standpoint of it's going to
affect them. I get three minutes. I have
20 something seconds left to convince
you to vote no tonight. And it's going
to affect them for the rest of their
lives. So, go home with that tonight.
You know, all of you, everyone in here,
go home with that. How's it going to
affect me?
Thank you for your time.
>> Thanks for being here again.
Go ahead, ma'am. Thank you.
>> Hello. My my excuse me, my name is Betty
Keatley and I've owned two businesses in
Cheyenne for about 25 years and I'm a
producer for White Fresh Farms.
In addition to everything that everybody
says about how great the place is,
there's the reality of the fact that you
have an agenda that you want pushed that
you came in that you wanted to create
absorb these pockets. Your constituents
in your city have shown you they do not
agree with your agenda.
Therefore, your agenda needs to change.
We could have a thousand people in this
building and we don't feel like we're
heard. They've shown up week after week
to tell you they do not agree. I have
not heard one person stand into any of
these podiums and say they agree with
your agenda.
So I'd like you to consider that when
you make this vote. Thank you.
>> Miss Woodhouse, Mr. Connor's here now.
You're here. I feel like it is old days.
>> It is.
We're back to 199 something. Uh Gabe
Woodhouse. I am representing Wresh Farms
and the Nisley's.
I I I think wonderful things have been
said tonight and I don't I could not say
them better really especially Glenn
Connor. I believe Gary Pew had the legal
arguments down, you know, so there's
nothing new to say there. But, you know,
today, you know, we well, first of all,
I want to talk about the questions, the
143 questions. And I wanted, you know, I
think some people misunderstood that
they were like willy-nilly questions or
not particularly important. They were
well organized. They were organized by
topic and and then they were sub
subtopics within them. Each one of them,
the Nisley's felt this is an important
thing to know. Well, some of them may
have been and were answered bulk in
bulk. Two or three could be answered
together, which is appreciated. But then
we got the answers last Monday and we
went through them as quickly as we
could. We reviewed them. We met on
Wednesday. We had a a long meeting where
we tried to identify and I did identify
nine major areas that we still had
questions about and um and we had a
great meeting today with the city. I
mean, they were very we we did have all
the people who showed up were very
respectful and gave us information
and some of the information that they
gave us was actually, you know, it's
still the kind of the cart for the horse
thing because like like adding in the
urban definition that but not quite in
the code yet. You know, it's going to be
in the code later, but it'll be we'll
follow it. You know what uh Mr. Bloom
said, "One of the great ones that we
heard is that there could be and will be
a proposal to have them allowed electric
fence. This is great. I mean, that
solves a lot of problems, but it hasn't
been done. You It hasn't been before
you. I know we have a sponsor for it,
but it's I don't know if it's written or
not yet, but you know, that's a that's a
good thing." So, um, there were several
items that still when I left, well,
another point before that. Um, oh, gee,
I'm running. Okay. Um, the the site site
plat, I mean, they put their heart and
soul into that. And they did it by
layers of each type like mulch and and
permanent structures and all that. And
and and Mr. Bloom thought it was a great
site plan. There's a few things that'll
be worked out, but you know, they really
dug down and did all the things they
need to do, but it was almost it's it's
a defense mechanism. Are is that all
there ever going to be able to do? You
know, what what exactly is going to roll
out after, you know, if this is annexed
tonight and those kinds of things really
there are so many things that just could
be addressed ahead of time and could be
taken care of that would allow them to
sleep at night. I don't think they've
slept at night for a month. You know,
it's very difficult for them. I mean,
they are worrying about the thing that
they've dreamed about, the thing that
they love, the thing that they live for,
just like we all have. We all have
things that we dream about, including
the mayor wanting to annex all the
county pockets. So, you know, you must
understand that. But, you know, it's
really I just feel like we need to have
some more time. We need to get some of
these things done and codified and so
there's not a question. They're in in
code.
So, please postpone
as long as you can. Thank you.
>> It's good to see you again.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening, Mr. Mayor, City Council,
Tamara Trillo, Ward One.
I've always asked for you guys to table
this since the beginning. We've actually
had this discussion back in 2022 when
you guys brought the data centers and
all of the Southside was coming here to
talk against annexation.
Um there's a couple things that I just
we already know the decision. If it's
already brought this far, then we know
where we're going. However,
you guys can table it. You guys can also
pull this parcel out. I know there was
discussion
um in the last meeting with uh
Councilman Labour when he questioned
about pulling this parcel out and the
city attorney said unique situation.
Well, let's remind of the unique
situation in February of 2021
when the city council approved the
annexation and reszoning of
approximately 532 acres owned by Lumis
Livestock
and ARP and um Hammond Hardware.
You guys were able to do it then with a
reszoning of about 258 to 260 acres for
heavy industrial and the rest to
agricultural re uh retention and then um
as of April 2025 an additional expansion
of roughly 200 acres was proposed for
annexation.
So there is already president to pull
out a parcel if you need to. Thank you,
>> sir.
Welcome.
>> Thank you, sir. Thank you for the time
to speak. I appreciate it. I have served
on multiple boards and I don't enjoy
being on your side of the table. So, I
and I know all of you are actively
trying to put effort in to make the best
decision for the city of Cheyenne. I
appreciate your time. My name is Cody
Smith. I've lived in Wyoming all of my
46 years. My family first came to
Laramie County in 1907. I'm very proud
of my heritage here in Laramie County. I
have three quick points. First of all, I
I assume you're probably starting to get
the idea, but I'm not sure the council
fully understands the community
surrounding this farm stand. I mean,
it's more than just an 8 acre plot of
land with some chickens. It's you the
people that come in there that can't eat
food out of the grocery store. I mean,
it's there there's a lot of them. The
people that market their farm products
through their through the farm stand, I
I don't know how many there is. There's
quite a few. We started, my wife and I
started an ice cream business several
years ago and it's actually turned into
quite a quite a big deal. We have 30
locations across Kimble, Scots Bluff,
Douglas. Cheyenne has been our hardest
place to be able to to sell stuff and I
think that's partly on the the number of
regulations and the corporate the
corporateness of Cheyenne.
But our ice cream business started in
the farm stand here. You know, we
started making in our home and it was
under the Wyoming Food Freedom Act. we
were able to sell it and it's grown into
a big thing and I think you know it with
the farm stand gone we wouldn't have
that opportunity have had that
opportunity or it would have been harder
so anyway I just want you to fully
understand the implications of a
decision tonight and the number of the
people will affect is is a lot second
thing is under the current circumstances
and Tommy and and may not agree with me
but I believe it will be the end of the
farm stand I mean it'll be death of a
thousand cuts regulation after regul
population over it may not be immediate
but over the next year or two it will
close. I mean they won't be able to
operate under the current set of
circumstances. So know that an an
accessession tonight will inevitably be
an end of the farm stand and the
community and the people that serves and
is whether you know if you don't like it
don't go there but for the people that
do go there it's a big part of their
life.
My third comment before I quit is my
challenge for you tonight is why does
annexation have to be a negative thing?
Why don't we not annex tonight, go back,
do our homework, and come back in
whatever amount of time so that it's a
positive thing for this annexation. Make
it a deal that these people would like
to be a part of the city. This is an
opportunity to join the city with all
the great opportunities we have rather
than be in this apparently quite
negative hard feeling situation that
we've developed. So anyway, thank you
guys for time.
>> What's the name of your ice cream?
>> Jos's crearyy.
>> Just had my first one, the chocolate. It
was amazing.
>> You did you? We're very glad to hear
that, sir.
>> It's good. Thank you.
>> Well, it's because of the farm stand.
So,
>> thank you.
David, welcome.
>> David Nicely, 200 Walters.
>> David, could you pull that microphone
down so it points at you?
>> David Nicely, 200 Walters.
I've been praying for you all tonight.
Um, I know making decisions are
sometimes hard.
Um
today we met with the city um department
heads, I think six of them and uh and uh
several of them were extra um good to
deal with. Um some were more neutral. Um
but
what I'd say is
I'd like to propose a way forward.
Um,
one uh, great man who did a lot of great
things said once, he said, "I don't pay
attorneys to tell me I can't. I pay them
to tell me how I can."
And I feel like the city council and the
city staff here to four have been trying
to tell us why we can't continue to do
what we've been doing in the way we're
doing them.
And the way forward I'd propose though
we've been almost mocked for 147
questions
is to have the city council and the city
staff put forward some questions for us
because what we discovered collectively
today in the first grand meeting if you
will between us and you all and that's
remarkable that in six weeks with
multiple meetings at the last possible
minute before the final vote, we have a
meeting to come to some agreement. And
we've been I I I haven't been begging
because I I don't beg, but I've I've
been imploring you to do that.
We discovered that some of the answers
that were given were given without
complete information is even to what
we're doing.
So, why not go back,
propose to us a list of 147 questions. I
I don't know where that number came
from. And we'll answer them because
we discovered today that you all are
annexing us and and you don't even know
what we're doing or how we're doing it
or why we're doing it.
Um, I don't know that they don't care. I
I I think it's it's a cruel system
and they believe maybe at least one of
you all believes that government could
be could should be just blind and blind
in its cruelty. A couple of you all have
told us to sell and move someone where
we're wanted.
Um
but the reality is um
we can have a great thing. Miss Ash and
I at the at the end afterwards
right at the final point she said that
our farm should learn to trans should
transition to learn to live in the city
and I countered and said the city should
transition with us and learn how to host
a farm. Somebody else said this can be a
great thing. You ought to be proud to
have a farm in your midst.
Um we could sell and move. We've been
offered money. Um the number one
objection we get um to our social media
posts is you could just sell and go
somewhere else. And it's not about the
money. Um honestly um you know to live
true to our western way of life. My wife
said it it's not going to cost you a
thing. Well, it's costing me something
and financially.
We're not making any money. I I think
we'll prepare a tax return that says
we're losing money. And I'm happy to do
that because I feel like God has called
us to the ministry of allowing people to
eat.
Um
I feel great about connecting with
people, serving people, loving people.
My wife, my wife can't get out of the
farm stand when she goes down there to
do something. Um, [snorts]
people are all over her asking her
questions about growing things, about
health, about her knowledge of biology
and science. Um, so we can have a great
relationship. Just my modest proposal is
do some homework. Ask us some questions.
I'm shocked. I I've sent email after
email after email imploring you all as a
city council
to interact and you by and large don't
interact.
Um I don't know whether that's because
you don't care, aren't interested, or
there's some reason.
Um beyond that I I don't frankly
understand. Finally, in your first
answer to our first question, the
question was why March 9th? And the
answer was that you have initiatives and
projects that would be held up. And I
asked Miss Ash about that today. And she
said, well, the staff is taking up so
much time dealing with this issue that
we feel like we need to get it out of
the way so the amount of time and cost
goes away. Well, with no urgency,
[snorts] a little more relaxation,
a little more homework, a little more
thought,
we won't be quite so defensive
and maybe we can come to some agreement.
Maybe some trust could be built.
And with a little trust,
we could get somewhere.
as it is. We're like two rail cars but
budding together cuz the knuckles are
closed and it will never go.
I can simply lift a pin and you can
simply lift a pin. Ken will tell you the
knuckles open. They'll merge together
and they carry a lot of weight. So,
let's do it. Go back. Do your homework.
Write 147 questions. Live live a little.
Write 152 questions. We'll answer them.
Ask what you want to ask. We'll ask you
why you're asking. You tell us.
That's that's respectful kindness. So,
let's do it. Let's do it. You know, I
might even object to the person who
said, um, don't an we're opposed to
annexation. I don't know whether I'm
opposed to annexation.
You know, I feel like a bride who's been
kidnapped, taken to the altar, asked to
say yes to marriage
without anybody trying to persuade me.
So, persuade me.
A little sweet talk.
>> Don't take me to McDonald's.
>> [laughter]
>> Anyway, thank you,
[snorts]
>> sir.
Wade Blunt, Cheyenne, Wyoming.
>> I'm sorry, I didn't catch your name,
sir.
>> Oh, Wade Blunt. I'm sorry. Wade Blunt,
Cheyenne, Wyoming. Um,
Mr. Mayor, members of the city council,
we have heard from our countless I've
lost count of how many people have
gotten up and spoke tonight. um anywhere
from uh
customers who regularly uh frequent
Wi-Fi to members of our legislative
body.
If there is questions or or if this if
this pro this process if there is still
so much doubt or so many unquestion uh
sorry unanswered questions
I implore you Mr. mayor and the city
councilors, step back,
take the time to listen to to the
nicely, please. Because again, we the
people
we the people vote. Well, I can't say I
I'm I live in the county, but people
have voted for for every one of you on
the body.
We the people and I ask just please
listen to the people postpone this do
some more work
because how when is enough if it's the
night if it's why fresh tonight
what's what's it going to be next next
year who who's who who do
where does it stop thank Thank you,
>> Jennifer. You have anybody online? Oh,
wait. Wait a second. Mr. Nicely's here.
>> I didn't see him hiding back there.
Welcome, sir.
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, members of the council,
>> as I said when I first appeared before
you all,
>> I apologize for interrupting you, but
can you introduce yourself for the
record, please?
>> I am Richard Nicely, son of David and
Tommy Nicely.
>> Perfect. Thank you so much. Um,
when I first appeared before you all, I
said that
think of us not as an ugly grain space,
but to think of us as a marriage or or a
marriage gift to Cheyenne.
But like any marriage, it will take
time. And so far, I feel like both
parties have been turning our plows into
our plows into swords.
Why can't we turn back to turning our
swords back into plows?
And I would first begin is if what I
hear from my parents is true, and I hope
it is true because they're my parents
and I don't want them lying to me.
[laughter]
is that while we have gotten some of our
answer some of our questions answered,
we have not gotten all of our questions
answered. And worse yet is that the an
some of the an answers that we have
gotten are worse than what we would have
thought.
I feel like to turn this back would be
either removing us from the annexation
or just a simple postponement.
You could just put one or two city
council members in and their whole job
is to just or not city staff. Their
whole job is to
answer our questions and to get us and
to answer our questions that work for
both us and the city. Because ultimately
in a marriage both parties have to put
in work and effort. If only one party
puts in work and effort, the marriage is
not going to work and it will ultimately
end in a divorce.
Now, in this case, we don't have an
option for a divorce and so both parties
will just die unhappy to the end of
their days.
Thank you for your time.
Jennifer, do you have anybody online?
Let's start there. Uh, Micah S, you can
go ahead and speak.
>> Uh, Micah Sutton, Cheyenne resident. Uh,
I'd like to speak on the site plan
uh that will be required of them.
Uh site plans must be resubmitted every
time things change from how they were
previously. Site plans can cost anywhere
from $100 to $1,800.
Regenerative agriculture requires
constant movement and change, which is
something that WFresh practices.
At least 80% of the buildings at WFresh
move twice a year or more. One example
of this would be their caterpillar
tunnels. uh they have two of those that
they move three times a year.
They would need to submit a new site
plan each time they are moved. That
would be a minimum for two tunnels three
times a year of $600
of yearly expenditure.
And those are not the only moving
structures on their property.
For WFresh, the entirety of the land is
used for many different agricultural
practices.
[snorts]
They are they layer one over another in
regenerative agriculture
and typical site plans are two pages and
relatively simple. The first submission
of Wish's site plan required 20 pages.
This illustrates the difficulty of
creating a single site plan, let alone
constantly changing or updating the
plan.
Please uh consider the public feedback
that you've received throughout these
many meetings and vote to
postpone this annexation. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Ma'am, did you want to speak?
Please come forward.
You were hiding behind the pillar. I
didn't see you till just the last second
there.
You You have to turn You have to turn
that on by pushing the button. That
light will turn green here.
Push it again.
>> Push it like you mean it.
>> There you go.
>> There we go.
>> Hi, council members. My name is Jerry. I
am here on behalf of my friends Roxy and
Casey who own Parcel 7 that is being
discussed in this annexation.
Um, one of the things that I think is
really awesome with them is they're
wanting to restore the barn on that
property.
was one of the original dairy farms in
this town. So, I really think that this
annexation is not
it's not something that's going to be
good for them. And I just I want to see
them being able to succeed on what they
want to do. And I think with the
annexation, it will put new zoning
restrictions, regulations on that
property. Um,
property rights and fairness matter
deeply in our community. enforcing
annexation on property owners who do not
want to be a part of the city setting
it. It sets troubling precedents, but
I'm just wishing that you guys would
reconsider and thank you for your time
and listening to the community.
>> Thanks for being here,
sir.
>> Please.
[snorts]
Uh my name is Dakota Titus, 2015 East
15th Street. Um [clears throat] I
prepared a small speech for you guys.
Um,
I'm not a public speaker, so I apologize
for the muttering.
>> Glad you're here.
>> Um, ladies and gentlemen, council
members, and fellow citizens, the United
States of America was founded by men who
understood something deeply about human
nature and power. They knew that liberty
is rarely lost all at once. More often,
it disappears slowly through small
concessions, quiet expansions of
authority, and policies justified in the
name of safety, convenience, or
efficiency.
Here in Wyoming, that principle carries
special meaning. The state was built by
people who valued independence, personal
responsibility, and local control over
distant authority. Wyomingites have
never been comfortable with power that
grows quietly without clear consent of
the people.
Benjamin Franklin warned us plainly,
"Those who would give up essential
liberty to purchase a little temporary
safety deserve neither liberty nor
safety."
Franklin wrote these words as a warning
because he knew that governments, even
well-intentioned ones,
are always tempted to expand their
reach. George Washington reminded the
young nation, "Government is not reason.
It is not eloquence. It is force like
fire. It is dangerous servant and a
fearful master." These words are not
anti-government. They are pro-liberty.
They remind us that government must
always remain accountable to the people
who created it.
And that principle matters today right
here in our own communities.
When citizens see expanding surveillance
through systems like flock cameras, when
they see administrative warrants that
bypass traditional judicial oversight,
and when they see communities facing
forced annexation without the clear
consent of the people that live there,
people begin to ask a simple question.
Who is our government serving?
Is the people is it serving the people
who elected it or is it serving the
convenience of government itself?
Thomas Jefferson reminded us the price
of liberty is eternal vigilance.
Vigilance means asking hard questions.
It means expecting elected officials to
vote in the interest of their
constituents, not in the interest of
political comfort, administrative
convenience or personal advantage. And
when elected officials forget that
responsibility
forget that responsibility, history has
always shown the same outcome.
The people remember who stood with them
and who stood against them.
John Adams warned us warned the nation
about the dangers of power when he
wrote, "There's danger from all men. The
only maximum of a free government ought
to be to trust no man living with power
to endanger the public liberty." The
founders designed our system with this
understanding. Power must always answer
to the people.
Wyoming has always had a frontier
spirit. Not the lawlessness of the
frontier, but the independence of it.
The belief that communities should
govern themselves, that citizens should
be heard, and that government exists to
serve the people, not manage them.
That belief is not outdated. It is the
foundation of our republic.
Thomas Jefferson put it plainly, "When
the people fear the government, there's
tyranny. When the government fears the
people, there's liberty." Which brings
me to the words that helped ignite the
spirit of the American independence. In
1775, Patrick Henry wrote before the
Virginia Convention and declared, "Give
me liberty or give me death." And those
words were not a threat. They were a
declaration of principle. Dakota, thank
you.
>> Yes, ma'am. You might have to pick that
microphone up and hold it because it
might be too low for you.
>> Just
work.
>> Uh, my name is uh Johnny Nicely.
>> My name is Johnny Nicely and I have some
simple words to say. I hope that one of
these speeches that these people have
told you will sway one of your hearts
and minds
to say no to annexation. Thank you.
>> Nice job, Johnny.
Jennifer.
>> Uh Jordan Weisdorf, if you can unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you. Jordan Wisdorf, can you guys
hear me? Okay,
>> we can.
>> Thank you for having me this evening.
Good evening. My comments are in
opposition to the annexation item before
the council. This annexation highlights
a deeper issue that many residents are
feeling. A growing lack of trust in this
body's decision-making. When annexation
moves forward despite sustained public
opposition to it reinforces the belief
that outcomes are predetermined and that
public comment exists to satisfy
procedure, not to influence results.
That concern is heightened by the fact
that this council is currently making
long-term decisions affecting new
residents while including at least one
member who was appointed not elected by
the voters. While I understand that
appointments may be legal allow legally
allowed, legality is not the same as
legitimacy in the eyes of the public,
especially when trust is already
strained. For many residents, this
annexation feels like another example of
decisions being made for the public
rather than with the public by a council
that appears increasingly disconnected
from those it represents. I want it
clearly on the record that opposition to
this annexation is not just about
boundaries or services. It's about
confidence. Advancing annexation under
these circumstances further erodess
trust in the mayor and this council and
deepens the divide between city
leadership and the constituents you
serve. Thank you.
>> Jennifer, do you have more?
>> Ken Williams, you can unmute yourself.
>> All right. Uh this is uh Ken Williams.
Uh, I live in the county and I am
disgusted at all of you except for Mark
and [snorts]
Mr. E. You. You guys should not do this.
Where is the win-win in this? There is
no win-win in this, Mr. Mayor. Zero.
Zero uh win-win. If you guys work with
these people, then there is a win-win.
This is Wyoming. And I've said this
before in front of the council when
Johnson was there about the uh plastic
bags. We are not Colorado. We are
Wyoming.
You guys gave 50 million $50 million
to help out the PRC. Why don't you give
some money? Why don't you guys give some
money to help the Nicely so they can uh
do what they do best? Mr. nicely. I
apologize for this council. This council
is out of order. Just exactly like the
mayor told you. I'm done.
>> Jennifer anymore.
>> Uh Ken Henderson, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Can you hear me now?
>> We can, sir. Thank you.
>> I appreciate the opportunity to speak
with you. Um, it's been my it's been
been my business to My name is Eric
Henderson. I am a resident of Laramie
with property interest in Cheyenne. Born
and raised in Cheyenne
and trust in government.
I don't think it's ever been less in
[snorts] our world.
And if you are not persuaded by business
coming from Colorado,
if you're not persuaded by the youth
that have spoke to you this evening,
if you're not sued by the unity these
people, the nicelys have have drawn
about, I'm going to I'm going to call
I'm going to call uh each one of you
individually and I and I I want the
opportunity to understand where you
truly come from.
It doesn't feel like Wyoming that I grew
up in until tonight. And I hear people
bound together for these great people. I
heard uh an area seven. I heard in area
four both of those the dairy the dairy
barn. I would ask you do not annex
either one of these two properties.
Not enough work has gone in
to justify
changing these people's lives forever. I
ask you to establish a trust.
Look, look to preserve
the history of what founded our country
and this these type of egg these type of
historical places around our town. Don't
change it. Don't don't make the legend
what it used to be. Let it live on
today.
I appreciate your consideration. Please
support these people who have asked for
your support to give them time. But I'd
ask you to preserve it long long long
forward as building my building
everybody's businesses has been uh my
entire business for in my entire career.
I would ask that you give these people
that opportunity. And I love the aspect.
I love the perspective that they should
want. Each of them should want to come
into the city. The benefits so outweigh
being in the county. That's the right
time for annexation. Thank you.
>> Anyone?
>> Uh Sarah, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Good evening, members of the council.
Thank you for this opportunity to speak
today. My name is Sarah Morgan. I'm a
holistic health practitioner and a
member of this great community in
Cheyenne. I live in Orchard Valley and
I'm here today to express my strong
opposition to the annexation of Wyoming
farms. Local farms are more than just
land. They are part of the health
resilience and food security of our
community. Access to fresh, locally
grown food plays an important role in
supporting public health. Many people
today are actively seeking food that is
grown close to home with fewer
chemicals, fewer preservatives, and
greater transparency in how it is
produced. When we lose farmland, we lose
that direct connection between our
community and the food that it nourishes
it. Annexing farmland for development
may bring short-term expansion, but it
can permanently eliminate agricultural
spaces that inc are increasingly
important for sustainable food systems.
Once farmland is gone, it is rarely
recovered. As a practitioner focused on
wellness and preventative health, I see
firsthand how diet and food quality
affect people's lives. Protecting local
farms helps preserve access to fresh
foods and supports farmers who are
working to produce healthier options for
our community. This decision is not just
about land use. It's about long-term
community well-being, environmental
stewardship, and protecting local food
systems for future generations. I
respectfully urge the council to oppose
the annexation of Wyoming farms and to
prioritize policies that preserve a
agricultural land and support local food
production.
I also want to point out an important
contradiction. Our state often speaks
proudly about protecting the western way
of life and supporting Wyoming
agriculture. At the same time, we see
policies and investments meant to
strengthen agricultural systems abroad,
including significant funding directed
toward international agricultural
development. Yet here at home, we are
considering removing productive farmland
from our own community. If we truly
believe in protecting
the western way of life and supporting
farmers that are com that commitment
should begin here by preserving the
farmland that feeds our community and
our neighbors and sustains our local
economy. Once let's see and then the
last thing I want to add is healthy
communities depend on healthy food
systems. Protecting local farms protects
the future health of our city. Thank you
for your time and consideration.
>> Thank you, Sarah.
>> Uh, Bobby Eer Moth Mothy, you should be
able to unmute yourself.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Thank you. I am Bobby Akamothy. Thank
you for pronouncing it properly. It
doesn't happen often. I am in ward two.
I have no dog in the game other than I
vote for my council member and my mayor.
I have a lot of questions. Why is
annexation being so pushed? Is it more
than a pretty map? Where are the
pro-anexation people? Cuz I have yet to
hear a single person say, "Yes, we want
this to happen." I have heard from other
property owners who are included in this
annexation said, "We don't want this."
Before it was open to public comment, it
was said 50% of the people want this.
Where are they? Where do they live? Do
they only own the land?
What do they have to gain from it?
They're not speaking up. So why are
their opinions so important?
The family who owned fresh owned the
land before the city encroached. I do
feel like as a property owner in the
city, we have to respect those who own
land outside of our city. When they
choose to sell the land, it should be up
to them. In Fort Collins, there is such
a farm that has since there were no
longer any family surviving family
members who wanted to work the land. It
became city property. And our children
here in Cheyenne go to Fort Collins to
learn about farming. in this Fort
Collins owned farm.
Yet we want to decimate this farm here
in Cheyenne which could grow and be such
a resource.
And again, where are the proanexation
owners? I would like to know where these
people are and who they are because I'm
pretty sure if we look down on it, they
are somebody who doesn't actually live
here. They only own land here.
Thank you for your time and please do
not annex this land. Have a wonderful
day.
>> Thank you.
>> Jennifer, do you have any more?
>> Mr. Miller, you can unmute yourself.
>> Did you like that?
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can, sir.
>> Um, for the record, this is Charles
Miller. I'm testifying remotely to
formally object to the third reading of
ordinance um PUDC25278.
I've listened to my neighbors tonight.
Uh Richard Nisley offered you a
marriage, but you are treating his
family farm like a fast food drive-thru.
It is a bitter irony that you casually
eat McDonald's cookies on the dice while
forcing a local farm into a marriage
with no option for divorce. Before I
enter my formal warning into the record,
I must correct Director Bloom. He just
testified that this farm is capped at 25
customers and requires a site plan to
exceed that limit. Please be advised
that under Wyoming Food Freedom Act
statute 1147103,
local municipalities are expressly
preempted from using zoning or site
plans to throttle direct to consumer
agricultural sales. What the planning
director just described as an ultravirus
act. It is illegal. I'm speaking via
audio tonight to form to enter a formal
legal warning into the public record.
the moment my time concludes. I will
transmit an email to the city clerk and
this council containing a document um
that's placing you on notice that an
affirmative vote tonight exposes the
city to immediate procedural liability
and litigation based on four fatal
flaws. Flaw statuto statutory voidness.
Wyoming statutes 151404 mandates the
city shall provide a written summary of
foreseeable changes to land owners prior
to the public hearing. Tonight, Tommy
Nicely, Michael Jordan, and Roxy Havvel
all testified they still lack clear
written regulations. Skipping this
mandatory prerequisites makes this
process void abonio flawed. Two,
material misrepresentation. Your
annexation report certifies service
costs based on generic residential data
for commercial agricultural operation.
It is mathematically and legally
impossible to accurately
uh price what you cannot even define.
This renders the report materially false
under statute 151402 which requires
annexations to be logical and orderly.
Fatal flaw three. Uh the grandfathering
trap. You have assured the public the
farm can continue as is. However,
Cheyenne UDC1311
explicitly states that if operations
cease for one continuous year, the right
is permanently extinguished. You are
placing a working farm on a 12month
death clock. Flaw 4, arbitrary and
capricious conduct. Under statute
15149B,
a court shall declare an ordinance void
if the action action was capricious.
Seizing land into a regulatory void
because the urban farm code doesn't
exist yet is a is the textbook
definition of arbitrary. We have been
here before in 2024. The Thomas Heights
settlement cost taxpayers $350,000
because the city ignored the facts.
Tonight, you are ignoring the law. Table
this item indefinitely. I am
transmitting my analysis now. Um, thank
you.
Anna Marie, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you. Can you hear me? Okay,
>> Anna, we can.
>> Okay. Um, I'm Anna Blessing and I'm in W
one and I stand with Wyoming Fresh. Um,
I I think as it stands and how you guys
have answered the questions
leaves I mean the way it's set it it's
going to destroy their business and it's
destroying a family farm um that gives a
lot back to this community. Um it will
also have effect on 40 to 50 vendors
that utilize their store to sell their
products. Um, I really hope that you
guys will reconsider and at the very
least delay this annexation. Um, they've
said they're not opposed to annexing,
but they just want more time to have
their answers clearly
um, answered or their questions clearly
answered and be able to work with you
guys and and form a good relationship.
But as it stands right now, I don't see
how that's going to work.
Thank you for your time.
>> Thank you, Anna.
>> Joe Pav Pavlica, I'm not sure. Uh, you
should be able to unmute yourself.
>> Thank you. Uh, this is Joey Rain Pavlea
with uh, Lucky Buffalo Farm Stand. To
annex or not to annex is not why I'm
speaking. What I am going to speak about
is the three hours that I spent with
Tommy and Chelsea yesterday.
The heart that we have for this
community is greater than anything
really that is going on here. We hold
space for people
so that we can make a living.
I would hate to see
this living being take away from this
family or really any family for that
matter. I'm a small business. We hold
space for over 103 vendors in our farm
stand. I know Wits End does as well. We
have 307 made plus we have summer
markets, winter markets. And all of that
is done out of love for our community,
our vendors, our farmers, and uh being a
small business owner,
it's all about
the feeling. you we get we get lost in
the politics, but what is created is
what I'd like for people to focus on as
well. It's not just um the rules and
regulations, although important. I'm a
business owner. I know that there's
rules and regulations and costs to a
business, but there's so much more to
that. And I'd like for you all to take a
step back and do what David and Tommy
has asked for. and and they've reached
out in Olive Branch and let's make this
a positive thing. Uh Cody Smith said it
very well. Why does this have to be a
bad thing? Let's come together as a
community and make this a good thing.
Thank you so much.
>> Thank you, Joy.
>> Adrien Crater, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
Adrien, are you there?
>> Yeah, I'm just unmuting myself.
>> No worries.
>> Yeah. So,
I don't understand
>> why the the whole annexation thing is
>> someone
a priority when you're not even keeping
up with scheduled projects that have
already been paid for like the stoplight
at Van Duran and Del Range. That's a
year past due, one year past due. But
then you want to put this family out of
business.
And Kathy uh Sigluaniano, she she said
pretty much everything I wanted to say
about the council right off the bat, but
I I'm just reinforcing why what is the
point of annexing these people's
business when you're not even keeping up
with the projects that are passed due.
[snorts]
>> Thank you, Adrian.
>> That's it.
All right. All right. Is there anybody
else here in the the room right now that
would like to come and speak before we
close public testimony and we give it
back to the council for their
opportunity to talk about it?
>> Yes, sir.
>> You got to come up to the microphone and
introduce yourself.
>> Are you going to Are you here to talk
about the annexation?
>> You have to turn the microphone on. Tell
us who you are. Okay. Um, my name is
Ronald Stringer and Welcome, sir. Um,
over there by Missile Drive where you
guys are annexing the bridge on Missile
Drive and uh uh of
the where the car lots road is, whatever
that name of that road is,
>> Westland Road.
>> There's six tons of trash underneath
that bridge in the creek. I've already
cleaned up three tons and they came to
hauled it off
>> and they keep dumping more trash in
there and it needs to get fixed. If you
guys are going to annex, you know, get
that problem fixed. It's in the creek.
Have a good day.
>> Thank you, sir. Thanks for doing that.
[snorts]
Anybody else?
All right, we'll close public comment
then and I'll go to Dr. Emmens for a
motion if she's ready.
>> Um, Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I
>> second
>> seconded by Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. Mayor M.
>> Okay. Would it be out of order if I
asked for a recess cuz um just a quick
recess because I have to go to the
bathroom. [laughter]
>> I concur.
We're going to we're going to take a
10-minute uh comfort break. We'll come
back at 9:00. Thank you.
>> When you got to go, you got to go.
Hey, ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to
bring us back to order, please.
Ladies and gentlemen, if we could bring
the meeting back to order, please.
Ladies and gentlemen, let's get back to
order, please. Thank you.
>> [snorts]
>> Did we lose Mr. Leborn?
>> All right, ladies and gentlemen, we're
back in order. Thank you very much. Hope
you enjoyed your comfort break. Um,
we're back to the uh uh the governing
body and I believe Mr. Moody asked for
the floor.
>> Yes. Thank Thank you uh Mr. Mayor
through you. Uh, Mr. Mayor, I move to
amend by substitute number 10 um
prepared March 2nd, 2026 8:22 a.m. If I
can have a second, I'll explain.
>> Second.
>> All right. We have a substitute dated
March 2nd.
Okay. Go ahead, sir. All right. Thank
you, Mr. Mayor. Through you. Um, this is
similar to last week, but is a little
different. It does take out a wire. If
you look at the uh second page there, it
does uh take out parcel 4 and then
renumbers it accordingly. Parcel six is
there. That's the old parcel 7. It still
keeps the uh two tracks there, one of
them being the Coca-Cola distribution,
but takes out the ad place, the dairy
farm. And I understand there's been a
lot of work by the planning department,
but we've heard from our constituents.
They do not want these properties
annexed and there's still lingering
questions about what an urban farm is.
It's not statue. It is policy and they
need time. This will give them plenty of
time and then we can even mend it to
where it will be desirable to be in the
city. And I ask for favorable
consideration.
>> All right. All right. I think I know
exactly what you guys are going to say,
but uh I'll ask you if you want to come
up, but uh
>> Miss Sigliano,
>> I'm sure you could read my mind. Um yes,
I would greatly appreciate and agree
with Mark's um amendment if that's what
it is. I'm not sure. Um, I apologize to
the dairy farm owners um for not
speaking on their behalf tonight as
well, but I am in favor of this. Thank
you,
>> Mr. Nicely.
>> Well,
I can obviously say that I'm in favor of
all
>> I got to ask you again just to remind
you to tell your who you are.
>> Hello. I am uh Richard Nicely. I am the
son of David and Tommy Nicely.
>> Welcome again, sir.
Um, I would just like to say that I am
of course in favor of all agriculture
and I believe that agriculture is the
fundamental for civilization
and as I think it is right now it is not
desirable for either um the one-third of
parcel 7 and parcel 4 which is us uh to
enter the city right now. Now, the city
can change that and I for one will
probably be keeping as much as an eye as
I can on that because I plan to die
here. I plan to raise my kids here. I
plan to marry here.
I use the word marriage and I will stand
by marriage
because ultimately marriage is consent
by the two parties. Now, the city has
already voiced their consent. We still
have not gotten our consent. So, for
right now, I would like to turn down the
betroal. Thank you. [snorts]
Don Odum, Ward Three. I would first like
to thank Councilman Moody through the
mayor uh for his thoughtful propos
proposal. I do agree with it and I yield
my time. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> I think it's pretty clear that Chelsea
knows.
>> Chelsea McCory, you're right. I know.
Sorry. I have it. Okay. Anyways, I I
think that it's pretty clear that most
people in this room are going to support
this amendment. Um, I wanted to speak in
particular about this option as opposed
to something like postponing. If we
postpone, we're just going to be showing
up here every two weeks and no one wants
to continue to hear my voice or everyone
else's voice over and over and over
again. Repeat the same things that you
have heard. Um, so this just removes it,
gives us the time to work through what
we need to. And then once we've worked
through all these things, which we want
to work through, it allows us to then be
annexed at that point. Um, regardless if
we're annexed tonight, I think that we
have a lot of motivation to continue to
work on bringing the definition of an
urban farm to Cheyenne. Um, so it's not
like this is not going to be a
possibility in the future. Annexation is
still possible. This gives us sufficient
time without having to just keep
reiterating points over and over again.
So, thank you.
>> David Nicely, 200 Waltersh. I'm sorry,
you didn't recognize me.
>> That's okay. Please.
>> David Nicely, 200 Walters. I think I've
mentioned before um because of what
we're doing um we're meeting people
regularly who want to do what we're
doing
and I think it's fact that if the city
continues to grow and I'm reading that
it will
that you're going to continually come
against folks who've started the same
thing or want to start the same sort of
thing that we're doing. So, it makes
sense,
as I said before, to figure out how we
can do
what we're doing within the city
and have a good relationship to define
this in a way that works, a marriage
that works. and and I'll go on record
and say that Richard's prom marriage and
um he's uh looking um so [laughter]
but [laughter]
and I'd be happy to to to grill her and
uh and review her financial statements,
but um
a good relationship with us
um
can be a good thing and it can make it
easier not harder
to go forward. So I'm just going to
maintain again the resources of the city
will be conserved by this.
Anyway, thank you
>> Mr. Love,
>> Mr. Mayor, Mr. Mayor, members of the
council. My name is Steven Love. I uh
live in Ward One. I'd just like to voice
my support of this amendment. Um there
was some concern, I believe it was the
23rd, uh the last council meeting that
this would create uh or a similar
amendment would create pockets. Um
however, I'd like to remind you that
somehow these were 100% surrounded. So,
we've already created pockets. We're not
creating pockets. We're just delaying
annexation for these. Um anyways, I
support the amendment. Thank you.
Jerry did a ward one. Excuse me, mayor.
Sorry.
Um I just think I think it's obvious by
the number of people that showed up here
tonight and voice their concerns. It's
apparent what the citizens of Cheyenne
want. They're fully in support of Wresh
and I would ask that you listen to them.
Thank you.
>> Don, welcome.
>> Donnie Carrer, um W three. Mr. Mayor,
city council. Thank you. Um, you see
what's going on here? Since this meeting
has started, man, it feels good that
we're laughing, not as council or city,
but as a community. That's how it should
be. When we started off this meeting,
Mr. Mary, you had some things you wanted
us to follow. I appreciate you guys
humoring me the last time I stood up
here, but this is what I like to see.
There's laughter. People are clapping.
We're not so divided as what everybody
wants us to be. You know, society would
say it's you guys versus us.
I pray that that's not always the case,
and I hope it's not. I really don't. I
know you guys are doing a hard job, but
I want this family to succeed. I want
the city to succeed.
And we kind of lose that ability when we
stop talking.
And we're still talking. We really are.
I don't have anything personal against
anybody up here. I might not like
certain characteristics no more than you
guys probably don't like my
characteristic or my swagger, but that's
that's so good when I look out here and
I see the representation, the green
shirts, the the comedic relief that we
all need.
And it's good seeing you guys laugh too
for the ones that laugh. So, I support
this. Thank you,
sir.
Dakota Titus Ward One. Um, I want to
thank you guys for having me up here
again. Um, and through you, Mr. Mayor, I
would like to uh I would like to thank
Mark for um opening up the opportunity
through this amendment um to really show
um the people of this great city um
those of you that are going to stand
with us and those of you that are not
going to stand with us and that insist
on standing against us. So, thank you,
>> Representative
Thank [snorts] you, Mr. Mayor. I'd like
for first to say
>> you know the rules. You got to introduce
yourself.
>> I certainly do. Uh Gary Brown, House
District 41 representative.
>> I'd like to remind us all that all of us
that are elected, we're here elected by
the people.
>> We're here to represent the people. And
that's should be [snorts] first and
foremost in our minds at all times. And
so I just want you to think about that
as you make your decision tonight. And I
would thank Mr. Moody for this common
sense um amendment that that he has
made. I think this is a real step
forward for us to look at this and and
do what's right for the people here and
do what's right for this family and and
to make it available for the community
to go forward with what we're doing
here. So, thank you very much,
>> Miss Woodhouse.
>> Gabe Woodhouse, attorney for Wresh and
the Nisley's. I just wanted to read, you
know, that 15146D
says, "No annexation shall create an
area which is situated entirely the
boundaries but is not annexed." So no,
you can't create a a pocket. But you
didn't. There was a pocket. You didn't.
The create means means what it means.
You did not create it. And if you don't
if you follow
uh Councilman Moody's amendment, you
will not be creating a pocket.
I heard some
misinformation about that last time we
were discussing it. So I It's not true.
We are not creating anything.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody else want to speak to the the
substitute before us which would remove
uh parcel 4 and the agricultural part of
parcel 7?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Charles Miller, you can unmute yourself.
Mr. Miller, you got that unmute button
figured out?
>> Can Can you hear me?
>> We can, sir.
>> All right.
Um,
let's see. Uh, for the record, Charles
Miller, um, I'm speaking in absolute
support of Councilman Moody's substitute
amendment number 10 to exclude parcel 4,
the WFresh farm. Councilman Moody just
correctly stated on the record that your
urban farm classification is not statute
but mere policy. Passing his amendment
to exclude the farm is the only way this
council can avoid the statutory
liability that I outlined in my previous
testimony. Um during the recess, I
transmitted my formal legal analysis to
the city clerk and the mayor's office.
But I must place three final pieces of
your own written documents into the live
audio record right now so that no one on
this das can claim ignorance before the
final vote. Um first, the map restart is
a legal fiction. If the city attorney
attempts to claim you cannot carve out
parcel 4 tonight without a total restart
of the maps, your own municipal history
proves otherwise. Your UDC appendix K
and your past actions regarding the High
Plains Business Park, Swan Ranch, and
the Sweetg Grass PUD prove you routinely
amend boundaries mid-process without
declaring the process void. You possess
the inherent legislative authority to
pass this amendment right now. Claiming
otherwise is an abuse of legislative
discretion designed to force the vote.
Excuse me. [clears throat]
Second, the hidden infrastructure plans.
Do not tell the public that annexation
changes nothing when your own engineers
are already mapping their dirt. I am
looking at the official Waltershide
Boulevard reconstruction plan. Your
engineering blueprints explicitly target
this property, literally labeling it
fresh on the schematics. Table six of
that plan demands 1,23 ft of their land
for additional rights of way. Page 33
dictates installing 1,310 linear feet of
24in storm sewer pipe and a massive
drainage network directly impacting
their boundary. You are trying to annex
them now to force them to surrender land
for citywide infrastructure later. Your
written confession to stripping state
rights in your official written
responses to the farm's 143 question,
specifically question 123. The city
explicitly wrote that the Wyoming right
to farm and ranch act quote does not
appear to cover the activities of
Wfresh. You have put in writing your
intent to strip their state protected
agricultural rights the moment they are
annexed. Councilman Councilman Moody has
just handed you a legally safe exit
ramp. Take it. Pass substitute number 10
and exclude parcel 4. If you vote to
defeat this amendment, the legal
analysis sitting in your inboxes right
now will serve as exhibit A in district
court. Thank you.
>> Jennifer, do you have any more?
>> All right. Anybody else in the room?
All right, hearing none, we'll let turn
it to the council now. Uh, comments for
members of the governing body.
>> Mr. Esel,
>> Mr. Mayor, on and for the substitute.
As I said last week, when the owners of
those two parcels are comfortable with
everything going forward, then I'll be
comfortable with everything going
forward. Uh, I've tried to, uh, do some
things recently to help them. Uh, I've
offered to take a dump truck full of
compost out to the farm free of charge
for them using council contingency
money. I've offered to bring the mayor's
youth council out there to help them do
some planning and cleanup.
Uh so we do want them to succeed
but I do I do believe they need more
time. So on and for the substitute.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Um thank you Mr. Mayor. Uh through you.
Um
at the risk of being accused of being
condescending.
Um, come on guys.
>> And uh
I would um I I would like to compliment
the nicelys um on their young son and
daughter. Um I just had a wonderful
conversation with Richard and and
Richard I only have one piece of advice
about public speaking. If you're talking
about the episodes in life that you're
really looking forward to, I wouldn't
start with I plan to die here.
>> [gasps]
>> So,
um
I'm going to vote in favor of the
substitute.
Um
and we've listened now to
a hundred witnesses over the course of
several meetings.
Um, the man who really persuaded me was
the man who owns Jos's Ice Cream, uh,
which I love. And if you haven't had
their coffee ice cream, you're missing
something. [snorts]
Um, you know, I wasn't elected. I was
appointed.
Uh, but I have tried to listen to all of
you. I know there are lots and lots of
efforts that the city has made and and I
appreciate
all the efforts uh Mr. Bloom and his
staff and the chief of staff and the
mayor and everybody else who spent time
on this. My thinking about it has
evolved. Um, I had a an initial
encounter with the Niclley's um that um
was kind of an hour of yelling at each
other and then we kind of settled down
and uh were able to talk. Um but
all of you think that all of us up here
are
coldhearted. Uh we disregard what you're
thinking. Um you distrust us. I it pains
me to see that. Um but I um I think the
time has come to
see how the nicities can continue as
residents of the county and if they want
to come into the city at some point
we can entertain that. Thank you Mr.
Mayor.
Miss Leborn.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I have a couple of
questions for the uh sponsor of this
substitute. Um, am I correct?
>> May I proceed?
>> Please ask them. [clears throat]
>> Am I correct in understanding, Mr. Moody
that with the removal of these uh from
the U ordinance
that would be the end of uh
any sort of
consideration or f future action in
regard to this issue before us. that be
over with until such time as it could
conceivably re be restarted by someone
somehow.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you,
uh, yes, sir. Um, as I'm aware, if we uh
don't annex them and we put it out, I
think it's a two-year wait, but I could
be mistaken, Mr. Mayor.
>> Um, I don't believe that that's the
case, Mr. Moody. Um, that's only if uh
if they're not a pocket.
>> Okay. But but you would have to start
the process over.
>> Thank [snorts] you,
>> Mr. Labbourne.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Well, this has uh
certainly been a uh
unique situation and one that I think
has uh educated a lot of people. I hope
it's educated some other people besides
me.
But I speak against this uh substitute
for one reason.
We've made this progress that we heard
tonight.
I know that there was a meeting today
that I wasn't aware of till I got came
down to the meeting tonight where these
issues were discussed. I believe I don't
want to put any words in Mrs. [snorts]
Nisley's mouth, but she seemed to
suggest that uh there was communication
and uh certainly knowing all that's
involved here, I believe that it's only
appropriate that we continue to work
this process through, if we drop it,
where do we go where do we go back to
it? Who's going to want to start this up
again?
yet. Um,
as I've maintained throughout this, I
think it's important that we work
through this issue so that not only can,
uh,
their farm continue in the city, but
that we would have that ability to
regulate other similar operations,
which seems reasonable to me anyway.
>> [snorts]
>> So I don't believe that this is the
proper approach. I believe that it
taking some time here. Um whether it's
uh there are some legal a lot of legal
questions getting raised here that uh
may or may not be correct. Um,
but I believe that it is correct
for us to continue down this road
and I I would surely like to see us
come through with some sort of agreement
that would that would work because I've
heard it suggested that that was
possible.
And again, I just really feel like we
would be [snorts]
putting this out there. I I can't I
can't believe that anyone would uh
particularly these two parcels would
come forward with a uh
request for annexation.
I mean, so then then where are you? Um,
so I I totally believe that uh
there's some good energy in this room
and and some good ideas, but basically
going
and ending this at this point. Not to
say that it can't be ended later,
but this discussion, this knowledge,
this learning, we never faced anything
like this before.
And uh I think that it's important that
we
continue to some sort of a resolution
that is more
recognizable as a benefit not only to
the people who are here tonight but to
the city as a whole. Do we understand uh
some of these factors better? I
certainly do. And uh [snorts] I do I do
want to uh
apologize. I
probably popped off when I shouldn't.
And uh but I'm [snorts] not the only one
that did that.
Let's let's get together. Let's work
this through
and let's let's find a way to have a
farm in the city. Let's find a way to
allow other people to follow their
efforts with their property.
But, uh,
I really believe that we'd be better off
to resolve this.
And it seems to me from what I heard at
the meeting today, which evidently
in involved uh just about everybody that
was responsible
and I understand that uh there is the
opportunity to further clarify
the elements in the UDC. So I speak in
opposition to this as an end. I think we
need to follow on through to a
conclusion that benefits
both
our
people that [snorts] make our policy and
and I I do want to close with this, Mr.
Mayor. Um these annexation actions that
we took over the past several years that
weren't nearly so controversial because
they didn't have this type of an issue
were to the long-term benefit of this
city as we grow. So, um I think it's
important that we
continue the spirit I'm seeing here at
this hour and um move on to work through
those issues and clarify in the code
exactly what it is we're talking about.
Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mayor Collins through you. Thank you. Um
I um
am going to um be a yes vote tonight on
this uh sub proposed substitute. Um I do
want to set the record straight on a few
things. One, um the comment was made
earlier by Mr. Nisley. I believe that um
there had been not much response from
the council members. Um I believe that
every time I've been contacted I've
responded and I want to make sure that
um we don't paint every the entire
council with the same brush. Um I also
Mr. Love mentioned uh throwing the baby
out of the bathtub. Actually I don't
think I ever said that. I think I said I
you shouldn't throw the baby out with a
bath water. Um I would never advocate
throwing a baby out of the bathtub. Just
want to make sure that got correct
corrected. Um, and there was also a
comment made that there has been no one
in opposition to this. And you're
correct. I have not seen one person at
these meetings in opposition to this.
However, we did receive an email this
week from someone who believes that this
land should be this should be annexed.
So, please know that um, and I
understand that that's one person, but
you know what? Each of you are one
person and one person deserves to be
heard just like everybody else. um
because at the end of the day we
represent all constituents and so um if
you were that only one person I would
want to hope that we would be listening
to you as well. Um there was also a
comment made that there's uh farmers
markets only on um during the um summer
there actually is a winter farmers
market. So I wanted to make sure that
people knew that. Um there was also a
comment made about affected residents
not being not being noticed um by Mr.
Lyall. Actually, I believe that we have
followed all of the notification
policies for those that are being an as
are being annexed. Um, to my knowledge,
that's a question we commonly ask of our
staff. Um, there's also a question about
predator predator control and that no
solutions were given. If you look at
question number 34, um, that actually
there were, um, I believe five or six
given there. Um,
so I just want I I want the other last
thing I want to say is I know that in
talking with Tommy and with David Nicely
that they're not opposed to annexation.
What they've been asking for this entire
time is more time. If this even if this
substitute fails tonight, I still
believe there is a way forward um and a
way to continue this conversation. Um,
so I don't think that um the urban farm
idea is going to go away. I think that
this council will continue to proceed
with that and um I believe that and as
my commitment to Tommy was on Friday
when we spoke Friday afternoon, I will
continue to work with this um family to
address the issues and concerns they
have um should this annexation go
forward. So um I will be a no vote. I
may I will be voting for the substitute
tonight. Um and if it's not successful,
I will be hoping to be able to delay
this or postpone it so that we can
continue the conversation.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. secret.
>> I'm going to vote no on the substitute
because I believe there's uh other
actions coming up that would uh perhaps
postpone and keep the action moving
forward as Councilman Labbornne
discussed.
I would hate to see this just stop u
because it's it's going to happen again
and I think we need those ground rules.
I need I think we need to develop those.
So, if we vote for the substitute, it
all goes away. If the if the substitute
fails and we find a way to uh postpone
at least a portion of it, um I think the
action keeps moving as Councilman Labour
once again said. So, I will be in no
vote on the substitute and I will
um consider the um postponement if it
comes forward. Thank you.
>> All right. Anybody else?
All right, we have a substitute for us.
Oh, Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, uh, Mr. Mayor through
you and thank everybody for your
testimony. I just urge my colleagues to
vote I. Our constituents are saying take
them out. This will not affect the other
parcels. We heard it will not create a
county pocket.
So, I do urge my colleagues to vote I.
You know, let's just take the do part of
seven out and all four out just to make
it easier and give them time to define
what urban farm is. Thank you, Mr.
Mayor. Anyone
else?
All right. The motion before us would be
to remove
uh parcel number four and the
agricultural part of number seven. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> I. Those opposed?
>> No.
>> May I see the hands of the nose, please?
Dr. Renie, Dr. Emmens, Mr. Crave, Mr.
Leborn, and myself. The motion fails.
Um, we're back on the main motion.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Mayor Ash,
>> I would uh move to divide the question.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> We have a motion to divide.
>> Mr. Motion to divide is non-debatable.
>> Right. And I'm guessing Dr. Aldridge,
your motion to uh divide would be to
remove um seven, the agricultural part
in number four
>> and four. Yes. Okay. Thank you.
>> So that's Michelle Aldridge and who was
the second? Dr. Ring. Oh, Mr. White.
All right. The motion is to divide uh
removing item number or parcel number
four and the agricultural part of number
seven. Um and we'll consider those
separately. All those in favor of motion
to divide, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> I see the hands and the nose.
We got Mr. Crave, Dr. Rainey, Dr.
Emmens, myself, and Mr. Leborn.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. That motion also fails. Mr. Mayor,
>> sir, I uh move to amend um very uh easy
amendment. Uh let me give you guys the
sheet before I and if I can ask for a
second, I'll explain. Very simple.
Mr. Moody, you have the floor.
>> Yep. Uh, so what I want to do is um
[clears throat]
motion is in uh page four and for
everybody in the public substitute be
page three on section seven right before
the end. It says that this ordinance
shall be in full force sound effect is
publication crossout's publication say
March 10th, 2027.
Is there a second?
>> I'll second. For the sake of discussion,
I need I hope we'll have an explanation.
>> Mr. Moody, would you like to explain?
>> Yes. Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through
you. So, we heard at the uh public
services meeting that to delay it. We
could not do it for certain parcels.
This does it for the whole ordinance
just to be fair. So, that is why I'm
bringing this up because there was an
attempt to bring us up public services.
This is for the whole ordinance to delay
it by one year. Give them a chance to
define what urban farm is. Give a chance
to define other questions that are not
answered out 143.
And that's why I ask for your favorable
consideration.
>> All right, we'll go back out to the
audience. Um the motion is to delay the
full force and effect until um March
10th of 2027. Mr.
as I understand the amendment
um it's a future effective date
which is effectively declaring us
married whether we consent or don't
consent on a future date and I object to
that as disrespectful to my rights to
say yes to matrimony
um it's just it it doesn't at that
point. There's no incentive for the city
to work with us and to persuade us. It
simply drags out
the discussion.
The legislators here spoke tonight
asking for a delay of a year. This is
not a delay. This is a future effective
date. we may never get to the point
where we want to be married.
Um, and so I think it it's a worse
amendment than
simply
approving it
and then dealing with the consequences
of of approving it. So I'd speak against
it um as worse for us. Um, so that's
that's my thoughts.
Miss McCord,
>> Chelsea McCort, Ward One. Uh, first a
quick appreciation for Councilman Wolf
and for Councilman White for uh
listening to us um in what we are trying
to express. Um, this proposition to be
clear, I think is better than just
proceeding with annexation full force.
But I don't think that this is still a
great solution. Um, but the way that
this solution is proposed is you're
coming to us and saying trust us. We
will continue to work with you to make
sure these things are codified. We can
try to trust you. But in asking us just
to not be annexed, we are doing the same
thing to you guys. We are saying trust
us. We will continue to work with you to
develop urban farming.
So if you're going to ask us to trust
you, you need to also trust us. And so I
I guess I'm neutral on this to be honest
with you because I do think it's a
better pro uh option than just straight
up being annexed with problems very
clear and very present.
But it also isn't a guarantee on our
end. And it also what if something comes
along the line and it's a more nuanced
issue that takes longer than a year.
There's a lot of problems with it. So
thank you
Mr. Mayor, members of the council. I'm
Richard nicely so that the mayor doesn't
have to remind you. [laughter]
Um
I would and I would like to break out of
the bond of filial devotion to my father
in that
I would reiterate basically what Chelsea
had just said but in I feel as this is a
lesser of two evils because if we are
going based off of incentive structure
then if we're straight out annexed right
away then there's also no incentive for
the city to answer our questions per se.
Um whereas if there is a delay maybe of
a year and I would consider that going
off of incentive there might be a little
bit more incentive or if not then
if you believe in natural human goodness
then either way they both
can succeed
And
I
I essentially would re reiterate to like
say that I am not a saying what my dad
is saying. I am a separate human being
>> sir.
>> Jerry Ditto ward one. Um I don't agree
with the idea that um a postponement of
this annexation would preclude any
further discussion. Um uh both of the
nicely and have expressed a willingness
to continue working with the city. David
said, "Send us questions. Give me your
questions." He's expressed a willingness
um almost an eagerness to continue
working with the city. And I think to
suggest that delaying this annexation
would preclude continuing to work
together is disingenuous.
Um
this is better than passing the motion.
Um in my opinion, it would give them
time and they wouldn't be in violation
of any number of things immediately. Um
and so I'm in favor of this. Uh,
it's unfortunate that the parcel wasn't
removed, but I'm in favor of of this. I
think it's better than proceeding.
Thank you.
>> Yes, Jennifer.
>> Uh, Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Press space.
>> Testing. Testing.
Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Um,
for the record, this is Charles Miller.
I'm speaking in absolute support of
Councilman Moody's new amendment to
delay the effective date of this
ordinance to March 10th, 2027.
First, to the city council because you
just defeated the surgical option to
remove the farm. This one-year delay is
your last remaining shield against the
statutory liability sitting in your
inboxes. Director Bloom confessed on the
record today that the urban farm
classification is uncodified policy. You
can legally not cannot legally annex a
business into a regulatory ghost. This
delay gives your staff the time to
actually draft the law and fulfill your
statutory duty under 151404
to provide written foreseeable changes.
Second, my message is to David and Tommy
nicely. If this council passes this
delay tonight, do not spend the next
year trying to fit a round peg into the
city's square hole. Do not wait for the
city to trap you in a home occupation
definition that permanently caps you at
25 customers a day. Use this year to
permanently shield your property. David,
you testified earlier tonight that God
called you to the ministry of allowing
people to eat. I advise you to make it
official. Use this year to legally
charter your farm stand and community
gathering space as a neighborhood
assembly and an agricultural ministry.
Director Bloom already admitted on the
record today that the city's land uses
are very broad and that the city does
not specifically define a church beyond
a general assembly. Use the city's own
broad UDC definitions to secure robust
first amendment protections.
Furthermore, formally structure your
operation as a private Agra educational
facility to protect the classes you
teach. And finally, ensure every single
transaction is explicitly anchored to
the Wyoming Food Freedom Act, which the
state legislature guarantees is exempt
from local lensure and permitting. Uh,
council, pass Councilman Moody's delay
to 2027. Give yourselves a year to write
the actual code. David and Tommy, take
the year and make yourselves legally
untouchable. Thank you.
>> Jennifer, do you have any more online?
Anybody else in the room want to speak?
All right, we'll go back to the
governing body. We have a motion before
us that would delay the full effect,
force in effect until March 10th of
2027. Comments, Dr. Aldrich,
>> Mayor Collins, um through you. I am
going to be a no vote on this tonight. I
believe there is a better way forward.
Um I agree with the nicely that this
just puts them in an untenable position.
Um and it does remove the motivation um
from both sides to come to some sort of
an agreement. Um so for that reason I'll
be a no vote on this amendment with a a
proposed amendment to follow.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Uh Mr. Mayor you base something nicely
say urge my colleagues to vote no. Thank
you.
>> Sounds like that's the end of that. All
right. So we have a motion before us.
the full force in effect March 10th,
2027. All those in favor, please signify
by saying I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> This unanimously uh fails and we're back
on the main motion.
>> Mr. Mayor, I would like to make an
amendment.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> uh Mayor Collins, I would like to amend
um this uh ordinance with a a postponeed
date certain um 3 months from today. Uh
which would be whatever that is. uh June
9th. Um
it according to Robert's rules of order,
I believe we can do a postpone of a to
date certain. Um it does require a
higher threshold of numbers of votes um
for that action. So that would be my
amendment.
>> Second.
>> Let's see if we can find that date for
the next that council meeting.
>> Um
June 8th.
>> June 8th. Sorry. June 8th.
>> Yep. Would you uh
>> I will amend my amendment to be June
8th.
>> And are you okay with that?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Second.
>> So, we have a motion to um to postpone
uh this amend this whole ordinance to uh
June 8th of 2026, giving us three months
to work on it. Um we'll go back out to
the audience. Um
>> can I do my justification?
>> We'd love to hear from you. Yes. Um,
Mayor Collins, the reason I'm asking for
a three-month uh postponement is I think
that that will give us enough time to
get the fence finished that needed to be
repaired. That it will also give us the
time to get the urban farm um definition
codified. And I believe that it will
give us time and motivation to get um
the questions that may remain or have
sprung up from the answers answered um
before that time when we would then um
postpone reconsider this and we would
have an opportunity to vote on it again.
>> Roxy, did you want to speak?
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Yes.
>> Can can I ask for clarification?
>> Yes, ma'am. The sponsor. So, are you
saying that we that they would be
annexed and go we would set the whole
annexation for all law all the
>> Yes, for three months. Yeah.
>> For all pieces that we've been dealing
with
>> the entire ordinance
>> for three months. Okay. Thank you,
>> ma'am. Welcome back.
>> My name is Roxy Hobble and I'm owner of
track number seven. I just wanted to let
you guys know that postponing this and
everything that you guys are doing, just
this the stress, I have not been able to
sleep for the last month that we have
been dealing with this and putting this
off for another three months. Just I I
can't even imagine what's going to
happen to my health then. I've had to
increase my blood pressure medication
because of this. My whole life is in
shambles right now. And you guys just
act like this is nothing to you and that
we're a pocket. You guys didn't even
understand how our land was separated.
Like I just I don't understand what you
guys's motive is for this. Like just
just
>> David.
>> Yeah, I'm part of the club, too. David
Nicely 200 Walters. I had to increase my
blood pressure medication. Um but I got
this t-shirt. Um,
>> no, I appreciate the the spirit of the
amendment. Um, but
three months means that in the next
three months, I'll have the opportunity
to prepare business tax returns,
personal tax returns, and deal with
meetings with the city. And as I
envisioned the meeting today with the
city, um I could envision five more
because we got through four questions
today. So three months
to
her point um Roxy's point is not enough
time
um because
we won't be able to plant a crop this
year. and the folks that uh look forward
to us planting a crop.
You didn't know it um because the
legislative process is cruel. You you've
kept us from farming. You've kept us
focused on this. You've kept the urgency
on.
I'm asking for
a postponement to allow us to consider
things not urgently in crisis mode at
the risk of our health.
>> [snorts]
>> but in a
relaxed, cordial
environment.
So, I'd urge that the maker of the
motion and the second um amend it
uh to one year or divide the two parcels
out if the other parcels, but they're
being forced to, so I don't understand
why they'd be in a hurry. Um, but if
they are, divide us out and give us at
least a year with a threemonth delay
before we begin the discussions and
we'll the city can do its homework and
we can do some homework and preparation,
but 3 months is is just more um and I'm
not suggesting that you all are cruel,
but that the process is cruel and and
that would be more cruelty. Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am. Welcome back.
Hi, Laura Lee here in Cheyenne, Wyoming.
As a nurse, I strongly recommend that
you don't tax these people anymore for
three months. Um, I as a consumer, I've
witnessed extreme stress, extreme
and we've just heard from the other
female that's in this and what all it's
doing to her and I I can witness what
it's doing to these two. Um, and so I
feel like they would need a lot longer
than three months. And again, if there
could be peace and not such a hostile,
stressful environment, I'm just
advocating for the health. Thanks.
>> Welcome back, Chelsea.
>> Chelsea McCord again. Uh, firstly, um, I
think we definitely appreciate the
spirit of this proposition, the the
intent to give us, um, more time to work
through some of the big issues. Uh but I
do think three months is not really a
sufficient amount of time. Um perhaps it
allows us to do things like repair the
fence but there's still a lot of
codification that will be required
additional meetings. Um I mean we Bloom
had mentioned the site plan that I had
prepared. Um I have been working on that
literally for 3 days straight and uh you
had a couple times to take some breaks
for lunch but people can testify I was
up till like 1 or 2 a.m. trying to work
on this. So the the thought the daunting
experience of trying to do this for the
next three months is literally
untenable. There's no way for for a
working farm for a volunteer to be able
to do this. We appreciate it, but I
don't think I'm not in support of this.
>> Yes, ma'am.
Hi, I'm and
um
I think you've had three years you've
been working on this annexation process
and today today they had a meeting with
representatives.
That is ridiculous. You have not done
your homework. You do not know what
you're annexing. So why are you putting
people through this?
Most of you sit here. I've been watching
you. You're not even paying attention to
what's going on.
>> That is so disrespectful.
>> I'm glad you have notes.
and to say that
it will not work out.
What do you want from us? From them,
from these people you're forcing
annexation on.
So many people have spoken here
personally
who are affected and those that I'm not
affected but I'm affected as a human
being
and to have them being thrust into this
situation. This is not their wheelhouse.
They have been forced to come up to
speed so quickly
with minimal help from this council.
From what I'm hearing,
forcing anyone to do anything that they
do not wish to do
is inhumane.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Nicely.
>> Mr. Mayor, uh, members of the council,
uh, Richard Nicely, I'm the son of David
and Tommy Nicely. Um, I would just like
to say that I given time to further
think about it, I don't even think a
one-year postponement is time enough.
two years
and maybe six months in between six
months between we start discussing this
again gives dad time to rest. Gives mom
time to rest. Gives me time till I get
to summer break when I don't have to
deal with Dante's 11th circle of hell
every day.
Um
and um
two years and up I'd say is best because
if we are not get on the train of
marriage if we are not going for a
marriage of love then we shall go for
the political marriage of most of
medieval Europe in fact most of
human history in that
we're betroved from the time we're born
to a person we barely know and we're
given 10 years to work it out. I'm not
saying 10 years, but I believe that a
postponement of two or more years is
plenty of enough time. It means that the
city doesn't have to focus on this. It
means that mom and dad don't have to
focus this on this as much. And it
ultimately means that while it was
forced on at least one of our part on at
least on one party of us,
we can live with it. And if we do not
die happy, we can die
content.
Thank you. I better get some sleep
because I have school tomorrow.
>> Representative.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor and Council. I'm
Steve Johnson. House District 8. And I I
got to just really push the point. This
is your fifth amendment gives these
people the right to own property. You're
going to stop him from planting a crop
that would be three months away that he
would sell. You that is a taking. You're
taking his livelihood away from him. You
cannot give him just three months. You
need to just put this on hold and stop
it. Thank you,
>> Jay.
>> [snorts]
>> Jerry Ditto, Ward One. I
want to recognize uh Mr. Moody u for his
attempt to listen to the family and also
Mr. Wolf and Mr. Lebornne um especially
I don't know when the last time was I I
heard a politician apologize for
anything. Um, so I really appreciate
that and I think that can go a long way
towards rebuilding trust with the
community. [clears throat]
Um,
3 months is nothing in terms of time.
one of the initial uh, reasons why
people were asking for a proposal at the
last meeting uh that I watched was to
answer the questions to answer the
questions. Um, I think it's important to
note that you ladies and gentlemen have
I don't know how many collective years
of experience reading city code and
interpreting city code, writing city
code. You have any number of staff that
works for you to do these things.
There's three people here, the Nicely.
And I Well, they've hired a lawyer and
uh Chelsea essentially who are helping
them. And
uh the amount of hours that they've had
to expend to catch up, as it were, on
their knowledge of city code, um I think
is unreasonable. I think to to try and
change the law in 3 months is not
reasonable. Um, and
I think it's important to note that the
citizens of Cheyenne are not going to
get quieter. We're going to get louder
about this. So, um, I would
for this amendment, I'm I'm neither for
nor against, but I would just remind you
that this is not something that's going
to go away. It's going to get louder and
exponentially. So, thank you,
>> Miss Sigliano.
>> Mayor and City Council, Kathy Sigiano.
Um,
like the last speaker, I'm not sure if
I'm for or against this necessarily. Um,
I would, I guess, say whatever the the
two parcel owners agree to is what
should probably happen. Um,
I guess I just have a question. And my
question is, do you guys even care?
Because I know Mr. Nicely
interjected and said that he thinks that
you do.
I'm physically shaking right now because
I'm so annoyed and irritated and sad
that
Mark's amendment asking for two parcels
to be removed and none of you could do
that. you would get the rest of your
annexation.
So my question is do you care? That's my
question.
>> Tommy
>> Tommy nicely to Waltershide
Wresh Farm. Um I have a few questions
and and one I did want to state um I
guess I have I can't speak to Dr.
Aldrich, right? I speak to you. I'm so
sorry.
>> Okay.
>> Um I'm on low sleep. I'm very stressed.
Um, you're right, Dr. Aldridge. You
didn't know about this probably till the
first meeting. Um, we have
reached out to the mayor, the city
staff, to Charles Bloom three and a half
years ago. And then maybe a year ago, we
did reach out to our council members
just in Ward One. Technically, they
weren't
um our representatives, but we did reach
out. So yes, the majority of this
council was not made and um Wolf even
gets I mean he wasn't even in that
position when we first reached out. So I
did want to clarify that you're right,
not all nine and I'm trying not to
wallpaper everybody in this. Um and I
don't know if you're aware but we have
such a short growing season. Um,
one of the biggest money makers, and say
that loosely because I farm, is
tomatoes. And I have I'm more than a
month and a half behind that. I can't
start I mean that that has hurt me
financially fairly well. Um, other crops
I can probably handle that kind of
impact. Um,
I'm also concerned about the three
months. I want to reiterate, I
appreciate trying to find a solution,
but please listen and please understand
that just and and you did a good job,
Dr. Aldrich, of saying every two weeks
coming back is is just going to be
torturous. Um, maybe not to the extent
that Richard does, but he does have a
flare for the dramatic. Um
but like the three months in your
response from the city and let me read
this. Um delay would also reduce and
possibly jeopardize the necessary
headway available for county election
offices to meet key deadlines related to
the upcoming 226 primary election,
including ballot preparation, mailing
and precinct setup timelines that are
established months in advance of
election day. Relatedly, delay creates
potential county election concerns
regarding ballot secrecy in these small
isolated precincts. So, not only do I
want to be the poster child for spending
six months in jail for a zoning
ordinance violation, but I also don't
want to be the poster child for
democracy's death. I mean, I'm just
asking you guys to please proceed
carefully and properly. Like I really
thought that civics was you government
does their homework. They come up with
some ordinances so business can operate
clearly
and
and then it's open to public comment.
You accept feedback
and then it gets adopted. Um, I am so
confused by why
we're doing it backwards. I I don't
understand. Can somebody please
understand? I'm just a farmer.
[snorts]
I don't get it.
Honestly, I don't I don't get it.
That is a question. It wasn't a
rhetorical question. I'm I'm I'm wanting
to understand and I don't want to stand
in the way of progress, but I also don't
want to lose my livelihood.
Um,
we hear you, Tommy.
We hear what you're saying.
>> Ms. Woodhouse. No, I'm just I've never
>> Mr. Hill
>> Tamra Hill Ward One. We already know
where the decisions are going by the
vote that was made on the when we were
trying to get the parcels out. I'm
highly disappointed in you. I'm highly
disappointed.
very bad considering I mean maybe if
their last name was Lumis
we would have been able to do it. I'm
just [clears throat] going to refer back
to February of 2021 when it was done for
the Lumises.
>> Go ahead. Now,
>> hello. I'm Carol Atkinson. I want to
thank one of your city council members
for apologizing. Thank you. I appreciate
that because when I stand back here and
this is my first city council meeting,
I'm seeing a lot of stuff that really
makes me want to throw up right in my
mouth. We You guys are telling us we
have to follow a certain decorum. Yet
you guys don't follow the same. You got
council members sitting over there
acting like he's asleep. You got other
council members rolling their eyes that
this is not the time or place. All this
does is anger more and more and more
fuel. Okay. So, with that being said, I
don't understand. There's got to be some
sort of ulterior motive here that you
guys want their property. If not,
let them come and annex you. Let let
them take your livelihood because that's
exactly exactly what you're doing. I
owned a business in this town for three
33 years. I employed
hundreds. I am ashamed to think that you
guys want to put a family out of not
only business, but they probably have
loans on their land. They're going to
default.
And whose fault is that? They didn't ask
for you guys to want to come in and want
their land.
This is their land. It's not our land.
Okay? That's been something that's been
brought up very much in in the
Washington Congress. Not everybody owns
a piece of my land. Not everybody owns a
piece of your land. And I sure they had
wouldn't want to own a piece of their
land when they are being treated like
this. You're taking away everything that
they hold value, everything they hold
firm to their soul.
And it's like it's no big deal.
I guarantee you if someone would have
come in and said, "Patrick Collins,
we're going to annex you, your city,
whatever, whatever business you had,
we're going to annex you all of a
sudden." I understand you were in the
city. I get it, but you wouldn't have
liked it. Nobody does. They bought that
land with the express purpose to become
farmers.
That land should be grandfathered and
allowed to stay exactly what they bought
it for. What nobody told them at that
time. Oh, in three years from now, the
city's going to want your land. So,
don't buy this one. Buy one out east.
Buy one out west. That's not what
happened. But it seems to me like when I
look at some of you guys in the face and
I respect what you're trying to do. I
don't respect the way you're trying to
take away the livelihood the Don't shake
your head at me, sir.
Mr. Leborn.
>> Okay. So, I don't respect the fact that
the medical issues you're putting on
this family.
What happens if one of them, God forbid,
something happens to them? Which one of
you guys are going to look in the mirror
and say, "I
had a hand in what happened to them?"
And with that being said, everybody look
in the mirror. None of you guys would
want what you're doing to them. Thank
you.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Hi guys. Um Hannah Fields again. Um I'm
not a lawyer. I don't play one on TV. I
just have a couple maybe suggestions. Um
could we explore alternatives such as a
phased annexation plan? Um an
agricultural preservation agreement,
conservation easements, or zoning
protections that maintain the farm's use
while still allowing the city to plan
plan responsibly for growth. Um, this
[snorts] approach would give the council
the opportunity to balance long-term
development needs with the preservation
of this valuable farmland and the
community character. Um, not just them,
but I guess the dairy as well. Thank
you,
>> Mr. Brown.
>> Gary Brown, representative House
District 41.
I've been sitting back here thinking,
and the thing I keep thinking is
motivation. What is the motivation?
what's going on here?
And I hear I've heard this is going to
hold up projects, other other things
going on. And then I think about what we
we're in a legislative session
and Friday,
Mr. Mayor, I seen you up at the at the
legislature at the House lobbying votes
on
on a veto override that we were looking
at doing. And I was told
that it had to do with affordable
housing.
And I'm asking a question to myself, is
all of this related?
I have to wonder. I have to wonder.
Is all of this related?
And I'm folks, we don't know,
but if we keep our eyes and ears open,
we will know.
>> Mr. Brown, I'll answer that question,
sir. Absolutely not. Um, the project
that we're doing is up off of Del Range
in Converse Boulevard and so it has
nothing to do with that.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Just for the for the record, sir.
>> Mr. Mayor, I will I will accept that for
now.
>> But I think we'll keep our eyes and ears
open.
>> Was that trust but verify, right?
>> Miss Woodhouse.
>> Gay Woodhouse for the Nisley's and
Wresh. Oh, I um you know what? I really
appreciate the way you are trying to
solve this issue. You know, I'm so
impressed and you know, I know each one
of you personally and some of you I know
a lot better than others, but I I know
that you are not trying to steamroll
this thing. I really do. And especially
by, you know, some of the amendments and
the discussion that's already been had.
I can see that you're trying to work
this out and I do appreciate it. And I
did appreciate the attitude of the the
uh city departments that were
represented at that meeting today. And
you know, one thought uh you know, I I
thought maybe the 90 days would work
too, but I wasn't thinking about farming
because I don't not farming. You know, I
can't even grow anything. So, but what
about eight months? You know, it would
put them after the farming season. They
would have a couple months we could
start working on more meetings like we
had today. And we could in the meantime
be working on some of these like the
electric fence issue and some of the
further definitions and codifications of
the urban farm. We could have those all
nailed down and then when it comes in in
8 months it might not even be a big
deal,
you know, but we just need more time. I
honestly thought 90 was good but I it's
not and for reasons that I didn't
understand either. Thank you,
>> Mr. Love,
>> Mr. [clears throat] Mayor. Uh, members
of the council, uh, Steven Love, Ward
One. Um, unfortunately, my generation,
we don't really get prescribed blood
pressure medics, and we usually stick
to, uh, anti-depressants and sedatives.
Don't have any of those tonight, but uh,
after this meeting, I may have to look
into it. Um,
uh, I guess I have a question for you,
Mr. Mayor, can I ask Dr. Aldrich, the
sponsor, a question through you?
>> You can ask me a question. Yeah, we'll
give an answer for you.
>> Um, my question is, uh, would you be
willing to commit this evening to the
cotification in that three-month period
of an urban farm zoning or however that
would um happen?
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins, for you, I would
definitely be willing to do that and I
believe that we could we would have
enough time to do that. Um but please
know that it it takes five of us or six
of us to pass anything. Right. So um
while that may be um an intention on my
part and I think that the staff would be
able to work on that with us and I had
asked uh Mr. Bloom that at the committee
meeting um how long he thought it would
take. Um
he he believed that it could get done
but it would it there are projects that
they're delaying while they work on
this. So, um I guess that really becomes
a Mr. Bloom question. Can we process it
through our staff that quickly?
>> Mr. Bloom, can you answer? Can we get
through planning commission and uh and
the ordinance process for a uh UDC text
amendment to uh codify an urban farm?
And I don't know where the calendar is
on that, sir. You'll have to help us.
>> Mayor, members of council, yes, they
could be done. Um it would divert a lot
of staff resources. So any pending
projects would probably be delayed um
that work on internally. We have a
landscape code that's been in the works
for a while that will take a backseat.
There's historic horse racing. There's
uh the adult businesses. Everything on
the unified development codes um annual
review work plan and most importantly
the comprehensive plan that we have
budgeted for this year that will
continue to take a delay.
>> Um Mr. Bloom, do you feel like you have
the um the wording for an urban farm at
this point that um you you feel is ready
to move forward?
>> Mayor, members of council, there are a
lot of different elements that would go
into this for the urban farm definition.
Yes, we do have a definition. However,
there's other elements of municipal code
that we need to run through with the uh
title 8 where animals are where we have
to look at the amount of livestock or
space and acreage needed for livestock.
Um there's other elements we had
identified that were part of part of our
work plan that include looking at paving
requirements for agricultural uses. uh
we've already in investigated that
lightly, but we would need to do the
code amendments as well. Uh basically,
we've we've looked at our paving or
surfacing requirements for parking lots
in areas where parking isn't used very
often. So, like places of assembly,
churches, and stuff where it's only on
Sundays, do you need to pave all of your
parking lots? Uh this uh discussion
brought up the idea that hey, we should
look at this for open space. We've
looked at it for other areas like um
well sorry for agriculture in this this
uh location. We've also looked at it for
open space applications as well.
Everything can be done but it would take
a little bit of rearranging. Um it is
coming at a time when we do have some
known staff absences that are are coming
up. So we'll really have to dive in and
see what what it would uh look like to
get that on schedule.
>> Mr. Bloom. Is there a timeline that you
feel would be appropriate?
>> The mayor through to the to the council.
This is the timeline that we have for
any ordinance. Uh just a general one. So
it' have to reverse engineer and
backtrack. Um it takes six to seven
weeks for it to go through the governing
body approval process depending on if
there's a fifth week in one of the
months. So that's just about a month and
a half. um it has another week uh that
would have to go in front of the
planning commission. It's your eight
weeks, two months. Then we have required
publication dates and notice that are
required uh under our ordinances, which
that's about uh 10 business days prior.
So, we're looking at two and a half
months. We would have to have everything
essentially drafted uh within the next
week and a half. Um and we would have to
have it drafted in a way that there are
no disagreements um and no proposed
amendments or changes. Um so
>> so what would your preferred timeline
be?
>> Our preferred timeline at minimum would
be at least 6 months which would be able
to give us the um ability to draft
um some standards, try to break them. We
try to break all of our our unified
development code amendments that we do.
Um, and then we would continue to move
forward,
but 6 months would probably be the the
best. We prefer longer um because we
would have to postpone some current
actions that we're working on right now.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Bloom.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> yes.
>> If if I just might add, you know,
there's an an additional element of
review. Um, all of that will have to
come through my office. We'll have to
look through it. We'll have to make sure
that all the conforming amendments
between the EDC and the code and you
know all the the varying things that we
would have to make sure that we we dot
and cross. Um so I think more time is
certainly better. Um we don't want to do
anything um
fast. We want to do it right.
>> Dr. ology. Would you consider a little
bit longer period of time to uh to allow
them to farm and to give staff time to
do that? I'm hearing someplace between
six and eight months.
>> Mr. White is Mr. I'm sorry, Mr. White is
uh I think working on an amendment and
and it would be November 9th for eight
months.
>> Great. I was going to offer to my
colleagues an amendment to the
amendment. Sir,
>> second.
>> Uh, Mr. Moody, thank you for seconding.
I'm I'm giving my justification for
doing this. Um, Miss Woodhouse had whom
I have great respect for, um, proposed
eight months and that is what I'm going
to propose. Um, I think, uh, I
originally supported the 90 days. I
didn't think about the farming season,
Mrs. Nicely, my apologies to you. Um,
Miss McCort, who is probably a de facto
city employee at this point. Um, but I
think this gives both staff
uh the time to uh get this process in
order. It gives the nice lease the
flexibility to conduct their farming
operations for the season and then uh
continue and and this is really the main
reason folks continue the positive
conversations that have taken place. We
heard from Mrs. nicely. Who ma'am, you
have the patience of Job. Um, much
appreciated.
Who [clears throat] started off this
conversation a long time ago tonight by
saying that the meeting today was very
constructive.
We heard the same thing from the nicest
representative, Mrs. New, Mrs.
Woodhouse, who again, all the respect in
the world for her. And so to my
colleague Mr. Leborn's point, I think
it's very important to maintain
the positive,
constructive conversations that have
been started and to continue them on
into what I hope will be a mutual
resolution. Additionally,
um it was uh indicated to me late last
week that uh the folks at the uh Wyoming
mediation program which is housed within
the uh Wyoming Department of Agriculture
have knowing Mrs. Paulie having gone
through that program, being a part of
some of those mediations, I've seen the
uh the hard work and the trust that can
be built and maintained uh through that.
Maybe that's an option over the course
of the next few months. But it's been
said tonight, trust is a two-way street.
I completely agree with you. I want to
find a way to work as positively and as
constructively with you as we possibly
can. Staff has put in
yman efforts, tons of hours to to be
collaborative.
And you know, normally I don't speak for
my colleagues. Um it's not my place.
It's not my style. But I firmly believe,
and I'm going to say this to all of you,
I firmly believe there is not one person
sitting up here who wants Wyoming Farm
Fresh to go away. I really believe that
with all my heart, and I'm willing to do
whatever it takes to build a bridge, if
you will, knowing that it takes it takes
two to tango. And so, uh, I hope by, uh,
amending this for eight months allows us
to get to that point.
>> Mr. White, this also, um, helps with the
conflict with the county, um, clerk in
her elections. It doesn't help with the
secrecy part of the the ballot. We'll
still have some small precincts that
might you might be able to tell how
people voted, but uh, this will be after
the election, so we'll be able to start
it'll become effective then. So, that
would, I think, help with that. All
right. I know what the answer is. Go
ahead.
>> Um I don't know if I can still speak to
the initial amendment. Um I don't think
my time was up that the clock kept
ticking. But um if I could say, I think
eight months is maybe the minimum, but
from the sounds of it, the city needs a
year. So maybe consider that. Um, I
guess my biggest concern also is that,
um, in eight months you're not going to
see all these green shirts out here. You
know, people are going to lose interest.
And I'm worried that um
I'm worried that you know the city will
see that as
you know even that there's no commitment
to I'm sorry there's no formal
commitment to codifying
um what an urban farm is and how the
protections that are needed for these
people.
>> Mr. Love, what you heard was a council
person say that she will sponsor the
ordinance to bring that forward. I'm
sorry, I misunderstood.
>> And so, uh, it'll take six, uh, people
on this DAS to do that, but I think
there's a commitment to, uh, to do that
from this body.
>> Okay. Um, I think that's all I had. Oh,
and if I could apologize for misquing.
Uh,
>> I I like the way you said it.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. So, we have an amendment to our
amendment, which would change the three
months to November 9th, which is eight
months. Um, so it's a date certain on
the annexation, but that gives us time
to work through the details, codify the
things that were were discussed and the
things that I've heard here tonight. And
so, um, I'm looking for any comments
from the, uh, the audience. And David,
it is a, uh, um, I guess it's it's a
it's a wedding or a marriage. U, but at
least we have some time to work through
the details before.
>> I
>> You need to turn your microphone on,
please. I understood that the motion was
a date certain on a vote on the
annexation.
>> It's not a date certain on the
annexation, but a postponement of the
vote. Uh,
>> that's not the way I took it. It was a
date certain on the annexation.
>> A date certain on the postponement.
>> Okay, I stand corrected.
>> So, I would speak in favor of the date
certain [snorts] on the postponement.
Um,
appreciate 8 months to uh
recover, to remove the crisis
atmosphere,
to lower the cortisol, to allow the
homework to get done on all parts.
Um, and
maybe we can make beautiful music
together.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> [snorts]
>> Roxy Hobble part or track number seven.
I just have a question with since our
farm like we don't actually have a farm
but our property is different from
theirs. How is that going to affect us
with postponing it eight months? Like
are we still going to be able to have a
say in anything or is it just eight
months and then we're annexed or are we
getting annexed tonight? So, Roxy, as I
understand it, um on November 9th, this
will go back to the uh public service
committee and it'll be back on third
reading here, um at the city council
after that. So,
>> Okay. And we'll have notification of
everything happening and be able to show
up and everything.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Okay. I mean, I'm not sure we're going
to notify you because I don't know that
we would do that, but uh uh it's part of
our normal sequence, but we'll try to uh
keep you informed and you're going to be
part of the conversation as we work
through these issues uh through that
time frame. So, yeah.
>> Okay.
>> I mean, our goal, I believe, and we've
talked about this, is to make sure that
your dream of uh fixing your barn, which
I think is going to be beautiful, and
your ability to have your your livestock
and and the things that you want to do
uh would be able to move forward
unimpeded. I mean that that's our goal,
right?
>> Y
>> yeah, we want you to be able to sleep.
>> Yeah. I don't sleep. It's been a
nightmare.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah, sir.
>> Uh Dakota Titus Ward one. Um I just want
to speak in um
I'm definitely for this amendment. I
definitely agree with um [clears throat]
what Mr. Nicely said here. Um
yeah, I'll cut it short. Thanks.
Really?
>> Yeah.
>> We're gonna get to know each other
pretty well.
>> I know, right? Um Chelsea McCort again.
Um first of all, I'd like to say that I
do accept my new position as a city
employee. I'm willing to discuss the
stipend. Um but I I do think that the I
do want to appreciate again for working
with us. Uh I think the eighth month is
very doable and I really do think that
we can help create something good. So, I
would really encourage to vote on the
amendment of the amendment or wherever
we are in this thing. Um, because we
want to work with you guys and we want
to make something great and we want to
help you guys be able to continue to
incorporate urban farmlands and and in
regards to Roxy, I don't know if she
left or not. Oh, hi. You're there. Um,
that that I have definitely been in
contact with her to make sure that we're
also looking at how what we're
discussing with you guys applies to her
land as well. So, thank you. Anyone
else?
>> Jerry Ditto Ward one. Um I would just
like to speak to I I think the
frustration or some of the frustration
that we've heard comes from um just a
lack of communication that we see from
some council members. And I I wouldn't
say that I don't think that those
council members are listening, but um
even when Mr. Caggrave and Mr. uh labor
spoke that they were going to be in
opposition. Um they gave the reasons why
they thought so and they explained
themselves and I think that people are
appreciative of that of that and feel
respected and communicated with and when
um other council members are silent and
there's still opposition and makes
people feel like they're not being
listened to. Um
whether that is true or not um uh I'd
like to thank Mr. quiet for his his
proposal to um wait another eight
months. And as Miss Woodhouse put it, um
you know, I'm not great at basketball. I
wouldn't presume to tell LeBron James
how to play basketball. And if if you're
not a farmer, if you don't have
experience farming, you you can't begin
to understand what is required of these
people on a daily basis and how their
timelines work. Um, so I think giving
them more time is the only acceptable
solution here and I would um urge you to
continue to do that. Thank you.
>> Jennifer, I saw you had your hand up.
>> Uh, Mr. Williams, you can unmute
yourself.
>> I don't think that the council really
listened to anybody tonight. I really
don't. I mean, you you you guys and and
I know I was hot last time and I've kind
of I've kind of cooled down, but how
many people how many people have talked
to you guys tonight? You work for us,
maybe not me because I live in the
county, but I talked to every county
commissioner today and they're all
against this. Every one of them. Every
one of them. you you guys are not
listening to your constituents.
And you know, I don't know if this is
out of line, but I want a mayor that
cares about Cheyenne. I do. I want a
mayor that cares about Cheyenne. I moved
here in 2018 and I moved from Colorado
and I am totally against anything like
this. Anybody that is forced to do
something, that is disingenuous.
That is mean and that is nasty. And for
you guys to roll your eyes and you know
just just don't listen to everybody that
has spoken.
You're you're not listening to the
people who elected you.
I you know I want somebody in there that
cares that cares about the nicelys and
cares about what is going on.
We are a western we are in the western
United States. We are the cow. We are
the cowboy state, right? So let's start
treating let's start treating everybody
with respect
and let's stop let's stop this. You guys
should have annexed both of those lands.
Those people are not sleeping. They have
high blood pressure. What is wrong with
you people? Honestly, what is wrong with
you? Why do you want their land? That's
what I want to know. Why do you want
their land? Do you want to put a road
through it? I mean, what do what do you
want it for? You know, you exactly what
you're going to do. You guys are
disingenuous and I am disgusted. I am
glad that my county commissioners are
behind the nicely because you're not
other than Mark Moody.
I'm done.
Anybody else?
>> All right.
>> Uh, Mr. Miller, I'm going to un You
should be able to unmute yourself.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> We can, sir.
>> Um, this is Charles Miller. I'm stepping
in as an independent auditor to address
the extreme legal danger of the
parliamentary confusion currently on the
floor. David Nicely is exactly right and
the mayor's language referring to this
delay as a marriage tonight is legally
fatal. Let me be absolutely clear. There
is a massive legal difference between
postponing this vote for eight months
and voting yes tonight to pass this
ordinance with a delayed effective date.
If you vote yes tonight, you are not
pausing the process. You are officially
passing a statutoily defective ordinance
and instantly locking in your legal
liability. You cannot legally pass a
broken document today and promise to
work out the details over the next eight
months.
>> Mr. Miller, um the the motion before us
is to postpone for eight months. It's
not to annex in eight months. It's to
postpone and it will come back to this
governing body to uh to continue the
process. So just just as a point of
information, sir,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes. On that point of information, are
we on Mr. Moody's ordinance that this
line?
>> No, sir. We're on um beyond that. We're
on Mr. White's ordinance.
>> No, Mr. White's ordinance was amend Mr.
Moody's ordinance from on the date.
>> No, no. We have a we have a motion by by
Michelle Aldrich and second by Mr. Moody
to delay the date certain of three
months. Okay. And we have an amendment
to uh that for eight months.
>> So,
>> um can you still hear me?
>> We can, sir. Oh, okay. Um, so I'm just
going to go ahead and continue because I
believe where where I was at was
extremely relevant here. Um, but let me
be absolutely clear. There is a massive
legal difference between postponing this
vote for eight months and voting yes
tonight to pass this ordinance with a
delayed effective date. If you vote yes
tonight, you are not pausing the
process. You are officially passing a
statuto statutoily defective ordinance
and instantly locking in your legal
liability. You cannot legally pass a
broken document today and promise to
work out the details over the next eight
months. And your document is broken. A
citizen testified tonight that because
your municipal code bans the discharge
of firearms and agricultural electrical
electric fencing, this annexation forces
the farm to build a specialized predator
defense uh fence costing $50,000. Under
15142C,
your annexation report must include the
estimated infrastructure costs required
of the property owners. Your report
completely omits that that $50,000
mandate. If you vote yes tonight, you
are passing a resolution of compliance
based on materially false financial
data. Why are you trying to rush a false
document? We have your written
confession. In your official response to
the farm's question number one, your
staff admitted this rush is to meet
quote 2026 primary election ballot
preparation timeliness. Sacrificing a
family farm to meet a county printing
schedule is the textbook definition of
arbitrary and capricious action under
Wyoming statute 15149.
Finally, do not hide behind the excuse
that you cannot carve out this parcel
tonight without restarting the entire
map. Your own UDC appendix K proves you
routinely amend boundaries midprocess
for corporate developers like Swan
Ranch. You have the inherent legislative
authority to to divide this question
right now.
>> Mr. Mayor is up.
>> A point of order,
>> sir.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Your time's up.
We don't. You're talking about things
that aren't pertinent to the motion that
is on the floor, which is to postpone in
its entirety the whole decision on
annexation.
>> Mr. Wolf, address that to me and I'll
make
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor.
>> And I I find that you're right. You your
time is up, Mr. Miller. Thank you very
much. Anybody else?
Jennifer.
>> Uh, Sarah, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Hi, Sarah.
>> Hello, Sarah Morgan. Um, thank you again
for allowing additional public comment.
I'm in full support of Wild Farms, and I
just want to respectfully ask the
council to slow down and really consider
the long-term consequences of the
decisions you're making tonight. Once
agricultural land is developed, it is
almost never returned to farmland. And
that makes this a devastating this
devastating decision permanent for our
community. I grew up here. This farm is
part of my life and my memories. My son
and I buy pumpkins there every
Halloween. And store eggs cannot compare
to the nicle eggs. This farm is part of
what makes community feel like home.
Places like wild farms are not just
pockets of land on a map. They are where
families make memories and where kids
learn where food comes from and where
traditions in our community continue
year after year. When we lose forms of
farms like this, we don't just lose
farmland. We lose a place of identity
and shared history. Please consider what
this place means to the people who grew
up here and to future generations who
deserve the same experiences. I also
implore you to please look into factory
farming and what exactly the food is in
your fridge. I I implore you to please
research how dangerous these factory
farms are and what a good great
opportunity this wild farm is for our
community. I would also like to ask you
a question. How would you like it if
your sanctuary, your pride, your body of
work was being threatened by greedy
overheads? I want to respectfully ask
the council to please consider this
decision because when you're making the
decision on the livelihood of a human
being, it takes a extra amount of care
and consideration. I strongly urge the
council to take additional time to
evaluate the long-term effects not just
on the nicely but on urban farming as a
whole. Please consider everything that
you've heard tonight. This is the
community speaking and really sp we're
spending hours here tonight to try to
ask you guys to hear us. So we
appreciate the eight months and we
really hope that this can be a positive
outcome for the nice leaves and all
urban farms to come. Thank you.
>> Jennifer, do you have any more?
>> Mr. Henderson, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Thank you, Jennifer. Again, my name is
Eric Henderson.
And as I listen to the concessions,
sadly,
in my observance of these concessions,
it's the nicely. It's track 7, track 4
concessions to the city. Respectfully,
uh, city planner, uh, Mr. Bloom
indicated the city would need 6 months
reasonably.
That's 6 months before the Nicely family
or the other track with the dairy farm
uh being renovated. That's that's 6
months before they get to see what the
city has presented for them to fully
consider. Then they are getting by a
friendly amendment two months for a
total of eight months from tonight. but
not truly an equitable amount. If you're
truly looking for fairness in going
forward, six and six seems most
reasonable
uh with respect to all parties, all
stakeholders. And it's most concerning
that
a lot there was not an action of good
faith taken by council tonight when
voting on a previous
opportunity to carve out these parcels.
That was a true opportunity for
concession to truly work together
and and it was bypassed.
And there's a trend there's a trend
to set all of the testimony aside
tonight.
Passionate, heartfelt,
actually most dynamic, most incredible.
I couldn't be more proud of my Wyoming
neighbors, my Colorado neighbor who came
from from south to speak on behalf. This
is unprecedented. I don't know in my
entire life that I've ever known there
to be such beauty and kindness from
people supporting a green machine
continuing to bring fresh products to
Wyoming. And this is something that
should be preserved. And I' I'd implore
you guys to consider
matching the request of 6 months by city
staff to 6 months for the families that
own these parcels that would be dearly
affected forever forward. Thank you,
>> Mr. Henderson. I think one of the things
that uh I'm hearing from this governing
body and from staff is we're not going
to wait till six months before we show
it to them that it's going to be a
collaborative effort from now till then.
And then at that time we'll be ready to
uh to have uh an ordinance that would go
through our process or the pro they'll
be through that process by that time. Um
so I appreciate your comment. Thank you.
>> Mr. Mayor, point of clarification,
>> the Moody amendment substitute failed on
a 55 vote, so it wasn't bypassed.
>> Jennifer
>> Patty Thomas, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
Patty, welcome.
>> Patty, are you there?
>> Yes. Good evening. Can you hear me?
>> We can, ma'am. Thank you.
>> Oh, good. Um, good evening, Mr. Mayor
and council members. I am Patty Thomas
and I live in Ward One. As your
constituents, as a taxpaying registered
voter resident of Cheyenne, I would like
to ask the council members some
questions. I expect that some of you
will step up and answer my questions.
First of all, I know there are some
lawyers on this council, so I would
expect that you are familiar with the
Constitution of the State of Wyoming.
>> Yes.
>> I'm Yes. Article one, the Declaration of
Rights, Section 7, where it specifically
states, "Absolute arbitrary power over
the lives, liberty, and property of
freemen exists nowhere in a republic,
not even in the largest majority.
In case everybody isn't aware of the
definition of arbitrary, it refers to
decisions, actions, or judgments based
on personal whim, random choice, or
impulse rather than reason, law, or
evidence. It implies a lack of
consistent, fair standards, and often
indicates an unfair, irrational, or
tyrannical exercise of power.
Those are pretty tough words and I
absolutely need to know how when our
state constitution
says that we are safe, that nobody can
just come and boss us around, that
nobody can take away our liberty and our
pursuit of happiness.
How did this this annexation ever get
this far? Who who who
can answer my questions?
You know, ma'am, there's a a state
statute that uh um says that when a
property is 100% surrounded by the city,
uh it can be brought into the city. And
that's the uh the statute that they're
working off of to uh to do this
annexation before us this evening. Uh
15142, I think, is where it starts. And
it goes through like about 15 or 16. Uh
I think that answers your question.
I don't I don't feel that it does. I I
feel that
every the council is playing fast and
loose
with their positions.
I don't think that you're giving
credence to the people that you work
for.
I
I I I honestly feel from I I I didn't
grow up here. I I moved here a couple of
years ago and I left the state where
this sort of these shenanigans happened
on the regular. I didn't expect this to
happen in Wyoming, which is one of the
reasons we chose to move here. Um
the I feel as though a lot there's a
this annexation reeks of impropriy. I
believe that people plan to personally
profit from this. I don't
see a good ending if this farm is
annexed into the city. There are other
properties in the city that are
completely surrounded that have not been
annexed. Perhaps the council could focus
on those personal properties before they
go after the livelihood of why fresh.
Ma'am, if you just um in 2022 we
started, we had over 100 properties that
were 100% surrounded. We're down to
seven parcels. Uh we've been working on
this since 2022 and they're literally
down to the last seven parcels. So we've
been annexed over a hundred of those
parcels um to date. And so um you're
right, there's seven parcels left and
they're all in this annexation.
Thank you for your comments. Jennifer,
do you have any more?
Uh,
Mr. Crater, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Welcome back, Mr. Crater.
>> Yeah, the second time I've spoken to the
first time I asked questions and I
didn't get an answer. Uh, I just got,
"Is that it?"
Period. So, there's more questions. Why
are you trying to annex this
uh
when you can't take care of
the city, the the property that's in the
city already. Uh there's several several
projects that are years behind. Um, why
don't we work on
catching up with the past due projects
before we take in more
land um, and put these people out of
business? And this is a question and I'm
waiting for an answer.
>> Well, sir, I don't think anybody in this
governing body wants to put them out of
business. And uh,
>> well, you are. You are. That's what
you're doing.
Is there anything else you'd like to
say, sir?
>> I just said what I had to say and you're
not answering my question.
>> We appreciate you being here this
evening. Thank you.
>> Jennifer, do you have anyone else?
Anybody else in the governing body like
to speak or excuse me, in the audience?
All right. So, the motion before us,
we'll go to the city council then. The
motion before us is to delay this for
eight months. I believe the date Mr.
White came up with was November 9th and
at this time would open it up to the
governing body.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. So, just for
clarification, we would start off where
we're dropping where we're stopping. We
I'm sorry. We would start where we're
stopping tonight. Is that correct?
Madame Clerk, I think we it' go back to
the finance committee would not
>> go back to committee.
>> Public service committee, excuse me,
>> would be assigned.
>> It would go back to Mr. Mayor through
you. Public services committee one more
time, but that would not be the date of
November 9th. November 9th is a city
council meeting day.
>> Yep. And so it would be assigned at that
time to public service committee a week
later and then it would be or would it
go the week before? Which way would you
do it? If mayor through you, if the
postponement is for the third and final
reading to be held on November 9th, it
would the I my understanding is public
services would be the week before that.
>> Okay. Does that answer your question,
ma'am?
>> No. Um, Mr. Mayor, so it would go to
public service, then it would come back
here for just the third reading.
>> It'd be on third and final reading
again. Yes, ma'am.
>> Okay. I just want to make sure that
we're all very clear that it would go to
third reading then we don't start all
over again.
>> Correct.
>> Um so thank you, Mr. Mayor. And then I
would also like to just add I didn't say
why I didn't why I voted no on the last
vote. Um because I don't think it's
necessary for I mean if people say what
I think I don't just chime in
unnecessarily.
Um, but I do want to say that there is
not, and I agree with Mr. White. I don't
try to do this for everybody. There is
not a person on this council that wants
Why Fresh to fail. Not a one.
Nobody's taken over their land unless
there's some secret conspiracy that none
of us know about. Number two. Number
three, the whole goal is to allow them
to continue to operate the same business
they have with the potential to grow it
as a city in the city. It is not to
close them down. Nobody has ever gone
into this discussion with the idea being
to close them down. That's that's just
not true.
So that's number three. So I want to put
that out very clearly. The idea that we
don't care about this is just
preposterous. We we could make this a
lot easier. Mr. Nicely's blood pressure
medicine went up. My heart palpitation
medicine went up. So I get it. This is
not easy. We have had people say more
than one that they feel like the
annexation should go through.
I get that there are people on both
sides of every argument and we have to
respect that. I respect the fact that
you all have taken time out of your
lives to come do this and to stand up
and make a statement. That's not easy
and we appreciate this. But please, if
nothing else, do not walk away from here
thinking nobody cares because that is
absolutely not true and you don't know
everything we've done behind the scenes.
Nor do you need to know that. But please
know we care about this business and
these people. Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I um first and
foremost I was by doing the original
amendment um I was not trying to be um
thoughtless about doing a three-month
amendment. I uh felt like that was a a
doable amount of time. Um not
understanding and not being a farmer.
And I wanted to say I think Tommy got up
when you said I'm just a farmer. Don't
ever sell yourself short for being just
a farmer. I think that that's a an
important and noble task. Um but um I
would urge my colleagues to vote in
favor of this um postponement a date
certain um for the November um dates. Um
and so I'm hopeful that we will be able
to utilize this time effectively and to
make really good uh a really good urban
farming ordinance for our community that
will benefit many more small businesses
to come.
Dr. Ry.
>> Yeah. Mr. Mayor, I wanted to clarify
we're voting on the motion to po to
postpone until November
9th
>> or the amendment to postpone till
November, not the main motion at this
point.
>> Sir, that's correct.
>> I'll wait to I'll save my comments for
the main motion.
>> Thank you. Mr. Moody, did you have
something you want to say? Mr. Secret,
Mr.
>> Mr. Mayor. Yes.
>> If we vote to postpone, do we take up
the main motion?
>> No. No motion. But the motion is to
amend to
>> Right. And we have and we have we'll
have another We have a motion to
postpone. We're amending the motion to
postpone. So
>> Okay. So that I know where we're at.
>> Y
>> the motion the original motion is to
postpone till some date. Mr. White's
motion to amend was to postpone till
November 9th. Correct.
>> And that's what we're voting on now.
>> We're voting to postpone till November
9th.
>> Okay. Okay. I thought we were voting
just change the date and then we would
vote vote to postpone.
>> I think effectively that is what we're
doing. Yes.
>> Okay. So, is this my only alternative
option?
>> No, because we're going to have to go
back. We're changing the date and then
we have to vote to
>> That's what I just asked.
>> Okay. Maybe I should I didn't understand
your question.
>> And it's tired.
>> I know. We're all We're all tired. I'm
really hungry and I get kind of kind of
spacey when that happens.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. So we are voting now just to change
the date as Mr. White suggested.
>> Correct.
>> And then we will vote to postpone.
Correct.
>> Thank you.
>> I believe that's the process.
>> Okay,
>> Dr. Emtts.
>> I'm so Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I'm sorry.
I just want to make sure that Miss Hub,
Miss and Mr. Hubble are on board with
this.
You don't want us to just do it
tomorrow,
>> right? But you don't It would be I'm
sorry. It would be better to wait eight
months than to do it now.
>> Okay.
>> Mr. Leon, did you want to speak?
>> I want to vote.
>> All right. Anyone else? All right. The
motion is to change the date on the
postponement from June 8th to November
9th. All those in favor, please signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right. That's approved. Now we're
back on the postponement uh which is now
November 9th. Any other comments? Dr.
Rainey,
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you. So, I've been one
of those that have had here sat here
silently and listening. Um,
and I will state right now that in
November I will vote to annex and I've
been a supporter of annexation because
honestly in my opinion nothing is really
going to change as long as the nicely
um and the hobbles continue with their
business or what they plan on doing.
It's not going to change. Our
regulations are similar to the county
regulations. If you're in compliance
with the county regulations, then you'll
be in compliance with ours. So,
honestly, I think that in a year from
now, you will still be in business. You
will still be working. And I also
suspect that none of you will come in
here and say, "Oh gosh, maybe we weren't
right."
And lastly, I want to say I have held my
tongue because I've looked on I've seen
the messages message boards online
that the lies, the misinformation, the
attacks on some of my colleagues and I
don't trust you. If I tell you what I
really think, I'm afraid it'll be posted
somewhere and with a personal attacks on
me. So that lack of trust goes both
ways. And generally, I don't trust you
probably any more than you trust the
rest of us.
>> Please, please, please,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Please, please. Port, you guys. Please.
>> Please. Thank you. All right,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Sir,
>> I was honest with people and that's the
result I got. So, I think it confirms my
fear,
>> Mr. Leborn. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> [clears throat]
>> I hope everyone that stayed and everyone
who watched at home and all the people
that are interested
[clears throat]
think about what they saw through this
process.
Because what they saw through the this
process was
democracy at work where opinions are
shared,
where policies are made, where specifics
of the law are interpreted and acted on.
This is what a compromise is about.
This is what we do.
And
I'm really
believing that what we have here
as has been pointed out
when this comes to fruition and and one
thing I particularly want to point out
is that
while fresh has uh an exceptional
attorney here that thoroughly
understands the law, our code um and all
the process that we're going to go
through. It's not
some farmers uh being bewildered by a
system that's impossible to understand.
Um and certainly that's the the right
thing for someone to do when they have
an issue like this. But this is success.
This is us listening.
This is us coming up with a way to keep
this farm in business to work through
these issues with some experienced
people like uh the mediator. I mean,
but I got to say,
I don't know if anybody's interested in
my feelings,
but I think I'll tell you anyway.
I wouldn't be here if I didn't care. I
know who the people that live in this
town are. I know what they tell me day
and night.
And if you think we're disrespecting
our efforts here, keep in mind we have a
whole agenda to complete here tonight uh
after we after this is over.
and probably and I can definitely tell
you with some issues that are
maybe not quite the same like this, but
they're also important.
So, I can tell you this. I'm proud of
this council and I'm proud of the people
that that worked through it with us,
that stuck around and didn't just insult
us and leave because it's going to be
worth it. And I personally, and I'm sure
I'm not alone, look forward to the day
that I can go out to the farm and
purchase some of those food stuffs
because of course many of us agree that
there are national, international,
corporate issues that are very, very
harmful to our culture and to us. So, I
think we worked out something pretty
good here. And I hope everybody will be
back in November when we finalize it
because
[clears throat]
this is the way it works. Everybody has
their say. We listen. We compromise.
And we're going to have a result here
that I
I've said enough. Thank you.
I want to speak to our legislators for
just a second. You know, I appreciate
you coming tonight. You know, one thing
I think that's uh different between our
meetings and your meetings are um
everybody gets a chance to talk
on every issue. Um I don't know how many
times I was there this year and the
chairman said, "I'm sorry, I'm out of
time. You don't get to speak." And um so
I appreciate you only have 20 days and
you have hundreds of bills to do and and
it's not possible uh to do that, but um
we just spent three and a half hours
talking about a really important issue.
Everybody got a chance to talk.
Everybody got a chance to be heard. And
uh I think this is what makes local
government such an effective thing. And
um you know what I heard a lot today was
you need to listen. And I go to the
legislature a lot and I speak to the
corporations committee and the revenue
committee and I walk out of there and I
don't get what I want, but I don't think
you didn't listen. I just don't think
you agreed. And I think that's okay. Um,
you know, and so no matter what comes
out of this process, you know, I think
people were listened to, you know,
hopefully respectfully got a chance to
say what needed to be said. And I think
that that's a really important thing.
And I've never walked out of your
corporation committees thinking you guys
didn't listen to me. I gave you my best
shot and you know if I if I had a good
enough argument you voted yes and if I
didn't make the argument you voted no
but that doesn't mean you didn't listen
right and I hope that that's you give us
the same respect here no matter what
happens um three and a half hours of
time is a lot of dang time and um
we didn't we didn't cut anybody off
everybody got a chance to speak and uh
and that's how the process works and so
um I appreciate you guys being here this
evening and hopefully you get to see
local government at its best Um,
>> we we've got it, sir. We're still we're
still on the first page. So, anyways, I
really appreciate everybody being here
tonight. Anybody else in the governing
body want last minute comments?
>> Okay, Mr. Moody.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor. Threw you.
Just want to thank everybody for public
comment. Just know though, I'll continue
to be a no because people oppose this
annexation. And I do apologize for the
uh other amendment. I should have
conferred with Nicely. Thank you. And
Mr. Moody, are you opposed to the the
postponement, sir?
>> No. No.
>> Okay. Just making sure I understood. All
right, folks. We're going to vote. The
motion is to postpone until November
9th. Um, that means it'll come back to
the committee the week before and then
it'll come back on third and final
reading on November 9th. And at that
time, the governing body can postpone,
pass, or or it can fail. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed.
>> The unanimous uh motion is approved to
postpone. We'll see you all back in your
green shirts at the end of October.
Why don't we take a fiveminute break,
give everybody a chance to uh go home
and we'll continue our uh our agenda
right afterwards.
>> Yeah,
[laughter]
but you got a lot of time to work on.
>> Yeah. Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. Oh, no. Oh,
yeah. I'm all over that.
>> Thank you so much. Really appreciate
that nicely.
Thank you.
>> I'm impressed.
>> Such a good job.
>> Go to the bathroom, I guess.
>> [laughter]
>> Hello.
>> Taylor says hi again. He was messaging
me. He's like, "You still there?" And
I'm like, "Yeah, who all's there?" And
I'm like trying to list. He's like, "Oh,
say hi to the people I know." And I'm
like,
>> "Okay."
So,
Yeah.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. There's some really
great there's a lot of really good
examples.
Don't give up on us.
But I want
the first
I'll be the first to come in here and
say we were wrong.
You're watching
Ladies and gentlemen, if I could get you
to take your uh your conversations out
to the lobby. We want to get started
again, please.
If I could get you guys to take it out
to the lobby so we can get started, I'd
appreciate it. I'd like to call this
meeting back to order. [snorts]
You're fine.
[snorts]
>> Ladies and gentlemen, could we get the
council back in? Let's uh let's get
started.
Do we have a quorum? One, two, three,
four, five, six. Three, six.
>> Madam clerk, would you read the next
item, please?
>> Number 11. Ordinance third reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne establishing the zoning
classifications of AG agricultural MR
medium density residential CB Community
Business and LI Light Industrial for
land annex to the city of Cheyenne
generally located east of I25 south of
the intersection of Westland Road and
Missile Drive north of West and East
Allison Road and east of and adjacent to
North College Drive.
>> All right, ladies and gentlemen, we
cannot annex or zone property that's not
in the city. We just postpone that. So
by by law we have to postpone this and
so I'm going to uh sir
>> I would just like to say um point of
personal privilege uh thank you um for
eight months of reprieve u opportunity
to work together um and exercise some uh
confidence that uh the city staff and
the city council um having heard us will
do that. So, I appreciate you and the
process tonight and I just wanted to go
on record saying thank you
>> and do me a favor, plant some stuff so I
can come buy some because if you don't
plant some, I can't buy it.
>> Please.
>> That opportunity is what we've been
asking for for six weeks. Thanks for it.
>> Appreciate you.
All right. I'm going to go to Dr. Emmens
for a motion on number 11.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service commit committee is to
approve on third and final reading and I
so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave.
>> I would move Collins to postpone to date
certain to November 9th.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Dr. Olives and Mr. Crave.
>> Um I don't think we need to discuss it
because we can't do it. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. All right. The motion uh
to postpone till November 9th is
approved. Next item, please.
>> Number 12, ordinance, second reading,
repealing and replacing ordinance number
4603 specifying the monthly storm water
runoff management system in accordance
with section 13.32.050
of the municipal code of the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, and providing a
revised effective date.
>> Mr. Love, then you can go home.
>> Mr. Mayor, members of the council, um my
name is Steven [clears throat] Love. I
live in Ward One. I know you've heard
from from me a lot this evening. Um this
is something that uh I think is very
important. As uh Mr. Leborn had said, um
this is something that affects a lot of
a lot of people in our city. Um anyone
who's a homeowner or owns a business
essentially. Um I support repealing
ordinance 4603. Um, just recently there
was an article published in Cap City
News about the youth exodus from
Wyoming. In that Kaylee Hollyfield is
quoted saying, "Wy's economy and our GDP
is in a long-term either stagnation or
decline." I would have to agree from my
lived experience.
So, in an economy that's limping that is
limping along, thanks in part to
overreach by out of touch bureaucrats,
why then would we impose fines on our
citizens for literally having a roof
over their heads?
I implore the members of the city
council to vote yes on repealing
ordinance 4603 as soon as possible.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Anybody else in the audience?
Hearing none. Dr. Oh, no. It's not the
doctor. It's Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve on
second reading and I so move.
>> Second by Mr. White.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Escoel. Move to amend by substitute
dated February 25th, 2026.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved by Mr. Escoel, seconded
by Mr. Moody. Um,
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> sir,
>> just so the public understands, the
substitute repeals the funding mechanism
in its entirety.
>> Thank you. Took it right out of my
mouth. Um, anybody in the audience want
to speak to the substitute before us
which uh gets rid of the uh ordinance
that does the fee?
>> How about from the governing body?
>> Hearing none. All those in favor? Oh,
Mr. Wolf.
>> Uh,
>> you dismissed.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> yes.
>> Um, I voted no in committee on this. Um,
and I don't think we should do it. Uh, I
think it signals signals an abandonment
of our commitment to uh work on storm
water. Uh, I'm going to be arguing
during the budget process and uh that we
ought to be uh allocating a significant
amount of money to um fund
u a continuation of the storm water
process. During the committee, I um I
asked uh city engineer uh Cobb to speak
uh the chief of staff um and um and Mr.
Brody. Uh, I understand that there was a
legislative process that seemed to have
uh resulted in the this motion, but
frankly I I think the legislative
process is totally absolutely never
going to help us.
We are kidding ourselves if we think
that the legislature is going to develop
a storm water funding mechanism that
would be of any benefit to the city of
Cheyenne. we're going to have to do this
ourselves.
Uh repealing this also raises
significant issues with our ongoing
litigation. Uh I see Mr. Day here. Um
it's a wonderful pleasure to see you and
welcome to the city council.
Uh for those who haven't met Stuart in
person, I've known him considered him a
good friend and a superb lawyer uh for
25 years or so. and he now represents
the city of Cheyenne. Um in our u in
this litigation that we have uh
involving the Terrell Chevrolet. Uh
there are complicated questions involved
uh in storm water. Uh but I um I think
it uh is absolutely not in our interest
to repeal this. I would urge the body uh
not to go forward with it. I don't do
this to uh to uh criticize at all uh the
discussions that were held with the
legislature. Um but I frankly think
those discussions will result in nothing
productive. Um and um we won't get a
stream of income out of it which has
been the whole basis for that
discussion. Uh we have invested enormous
time in this uh uh the BOPU uh Mr.
Cobb's office, the city attorney's
office, and all of you over the last
year who invested time in in developing
this program. And I wasn't here for any
of that, but I've watched all of your
actions. And we've had this cascade of
of events uh which I could recite for
you if uh if if you can't remember all
the things that have happened just since
I joined the council on storm water. Um
so let's not abandon that. Let's not
let's not repeal this. Let's move
forward to try and understand all of the
storm water issues in details, how it
affects our uh litigation posture of
whether or not we think that the storm
water program um can even move forward.
There's been a lot of discussion about
uh maybe uh plans to modify it. And I
realize there are two separate uh
ordinances uh 4602 and 4603.
Um, and this is only repealing the fee.
Uh, but um, they're
intimately and integrally related. And,
uh, I would, um, I would urge you to
vote no on this motion, this
ordinance.
>> Dr. Re,
>> Mr. Mayor. Um, for those of you that
follow the legislature, there were
several bills in the legislature this
year
that um
that were directed towards Laramie and
Cheyenne specifically
and we generally had a target on our
backs because of that. And this is one
of the big reasons.
Um, we were able to defeat all those
bills in the legislature and with the
help of of some allies
and when we finally defeated the last
one, several of the people that helped
us
um said turned to myself and to the
director of WHAM and said, "Okay, we've
gotten you this far. We promise we will
make it an interim topic. We will work
on it in the interim. And in fact, Mr.
Mayor, it is storm water is the number
one topic that the select water
committee will undertake. [snorts] Um
they said, but but don't um
but you know, please help us give us a
little bit of of credibility by [snorts]
re repealing your fees at this point.
And um Laram is in the process of doing
that. That's why I asked brought this
amendment forward. Um we can take
whatever position we want, but we do
have some friends in the legislature and
if we um do not repeal our fees, we're f
we're pretty much telling them, you
know,
stick it. We don't believe you. And I
think we will burn some bridges that I
don't want to see burned.
If I could add to that too, there's a
couple of cities in the in the state um
I wanted to add that there are three
communities that this affects also.
>> Yeah, they've been doing uh storm water
fee for in some cases more than 40 years
and the uh the ordinance or the
ordinances the the laws that were coming
from the legislature would have also
affected their communities and their
ability to continue their programs. And
so for [snorts] us to uh to continue to
fight at the legislative level at the uh
the cost of those communities and their
40-year programs um you know I think I
think it was reasonable for us to hold
this one back. The legislature has
promised to make it their number one uh
topic and they have in uh select water.
Um, and we have some great programs with
water and sewer that, um, you know, I
think the Board of Public Utilities has
used over the years very effectively.
And what they're talking about doing is
doing something similar to that for
storm water where we'll be able to have
a, um, a pot of money that we can go to
the legislature and uh, it'll it'll take
a match on our part, but we'll be able
to go after those dollars in order to
make our program robust and uh, and
protect the community the way that I
think we all want to do. And so I while
I'm frustrated that we're going to have
to take a uh some time off on this until
they figure out uh what that funding
mechanism is, I think it's the best
thing for the state.
>> Dr. Alders, did you have a comment?
>> I did. Mayor Collins, I just um I think
it's it's no secret that I have been um
I've always supported that we need a
storm water utility um some sort of feed
that we would be able to uh maintain our
storm water uh system with. Um I my
disagreement had been that we had not
done it by going out for a vote of the
public, but I wanted to recognize um
that there has been a lot of staff time
put into this project pro process over
the last two years by our city engineers
office by our BOPU um just trying to get
the billing system set up for that has
been an over a yearslong process. Um so
while um I think that we need to be
people of our word and while the
commitment was made to the legislators
that um by our leadership that this
would um be repealed and they would take
it up as an interimm topic. Um, I think
we need to make sure that we um honor
that word and that um when this is all
said and done that um we figure out a
way to fund this. Um, and if we um have
to do it ourselves, we'll have to do
that. But I'm hopeful that there will be
some sort of an outcome um because
there's this need across the state.
We're not the only community that needs
help with storm water maintenance.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> [clears throat and cough]
>> Mr. Mayor,
I speak for and against
[snorts]
this action.
>> You can't do both. [laughter]
>> Well, I I speak on
>> and against this motion. And
>> okay,
>> in case anybody's confused about why,
I'd like to get into why a little bit,
Mr. Mayor.
Why do we need
storm water management? Why do we need a
fee?
It's something that is so far beyond the
control and understanding of the Wyoming
legislature
that this is the height of absurdity.
The problem
is climate change.
The problem is global warming.
Global warming that gave us this winter
we just had that was non-existent.
The driest, hottest winter
that's ever happened here.
That's a big change.
And it affects the closed system of the
earth.
And the result is, as I'm sure we all
are well aware,
is flooding,
massive,
dangerous flooding. Whether it's on the
coast coming off the ocean, whether it's
in Texas or New Mexico in the desert,
when it comes, it comes.
And it comes much stronger
than it used to.
So the
flood of 85 40 years ago
magnify that and this isn't just my
opinion.
These are the scientific facts developed
at the Encar facility here out on Happy
Jack Road.
Okay. a world center of climate study
that has absolutely documented and
proved what we're living through. And
I'll also point out that tonight
we are uh facing a red flag warning out
in Laramie County of fire danger.
Uh
maybe you remember that midwinter fire
we had not long ago.
This is the tremendous change that we're
living through.
This is the tremendous change that calls
on us to effectively deal with this
problem.
And of course, we did have those two
elections in the early 2000s that uh the
voters turned down this uh storm water
utility
and in all the discussion that I heard
about this and I wasn't certainly privy
to a lot of it
and I'm sorry that we didn't get more
information as it progressed but I know
how the legislature moves along.
The point is that in all that
discussion,
it was about legalisms.
It was about is it properly in uh title
16 as a storm water utility or is it
properly in title 15 as a fee that we
can invoke that we work diligently to
do?
And what happened?
We were sued.
What happened? We heard this outcry from
the people or the entities
where the water runs off, whether it was
the airport or the school district or
the railroad,
leaving us evidently with a choice
perhaps someday, which is no choice at
all, of uh funding this on the back of
the property owners and residents.
I mean I I want to acknowledge this
members of the council.
We are going to have to figure something
out
and it's not going to be this.
But if you expect a select water
committee who has to deal with many
other issues to come forward with
legislation to the body uh that we had
quite a few representatives here uh
tonight
for a really serious mega appropriation
that would assist municipalities across
the state with their storm water. That's
absurd beyond ridicule.
That's just so so you have this
political
uh
back and forth or game
up against what we know.
We know that flood is coming.
We know that we've grown and we're not
prepared. We know those channels aren't
getting cleaned. We know that when it
happens,
the devastation,
I can tell you, has an economic effect
that uh is very detrimental.
This isn't just about money.
This is about people's lives.
So, I hope [clears throat] I've made my
point, and that's why I'm going to be
voting no against uh
backing up and abandoning something we
worked so long and so hard for that has
such an important
fundamental health and safety
fact in it.
And I I don't I don't think all of the
representatives that were here or that
are up there in the legislature
are going to have much to say when that
flood happens.
I don't think there's going to be any
explanation that will be worthwhile, but
I do appreciate the idea that
we can at least begin now with some of
our reserves
to uh see what we can prioritize and
work on because um and if if anybody'd
like a grand tour, I'd sure be glad to
take them on it. We we don't really
notice I think and I think that's
important here.
The public doesn't notice and I don't
know if we pay enough attention to those
choke channels.
Those trees and that
jungle down in the uh channel
shouldn't be there and it's expensive
and difficult to remove. And that's just
part of it. And we have, of course, I'm
sure we all aware and remember all of
the plans that we have underway with our
various consultants, whether it's uh out
east at the uh Kowanas Park or whether
it's on the entire Dry Creek stretch. Um
we're studying it. We're spending the
money on that, but where are we going to
get the money to pay for it? So, um
it's a bitter bitter
evening, but uh I'm definitely believing
that uh appeasing the
legislature with such a absurdity is
not in the best interest of the city.
Thank you,
>> Mr. Escoel.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. through you uh was
mentioned that it's going to go to the
select water committee and they have
three different accounts that they can
draw from. Uh the first one is for small
projects which this obviously is not
going to be. Uh the second one is
reclamation projects and the third is
large projects like reservoirs and dams.
Uh just in passing, I asked our city
treasurer if she could give me what the
balances were in those accounts and
trying to navigate through the
legislative website. She couldn't find
them.
Uh we'll we'll find them by the time
finance committee meets next week, but
uh the amount of money that they would
have to appropriate
uh
would probably take all the money that
in all three of those accounts. So they
would have to come up something
completely different kind of like what
when Gillette did their uh Madison water
project up there and and even bigger
than that, I think. So that's my two
cents worth.
>> Dr. did you have another comment?
>> I do, Mr. Mayor. I mean, first of all, I
I know some of my colleagues I don't
disagree with anything my colleagues
that have spoken in opposition
um have said I and I
with the makeup of our legislature, I'm
a little skeptical as well. I do know
that some of the people that have even
um one of our state senators that from
Laramie County that voted against
against us in the legislature said no I
promise you we'll work on this and we'll
try and get it fixed. I've two of our
representatives has said they're you
know they said we'll get it fixed and
they said that might mean coming up with
money and they said we'll work on that.
Um,
and oh, I did want to clarify. I didn't
make a promise that Cheyenne would
repeal it. I made a promise that I,
being only one vote of 10, would work on
repealing it. So,
um, but I think it again, we have we
have promises from some of our
legislators and some that have been
staunch supporters of Cheyenne.
um that they will do their best for us
and I really honestly believe we should
give them that opportunity and I will
conclude by saying that if we do not do
this all those bills will be back at the
minimum we will be required to have an
election
and we know how that's gone in the past
and then if we collect and probably I
think Laram's had to refund one month's
collections already, which would be a
nightmare. Um, so if we collect any
money and we have an election and we
lose it, we would have to refund
anything we collected.
So I don't know that we want that
headache either. And I again, if I
didn't say it already, I I really want
to apologize to our engineering
department and the board of public
utilities because I understand the huge
amount of work they've put into this.
Um,
but that's the political reality. So,
thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> I Mayor Collins, I have a question.
>> I'm wondering if um anyone can tell us
approximately how much money we've
already invested in this process
um to prepare for the storm water
management system user fee. Um, I know I
believe that there was an employee
full-time at BOPU that was working on
the billing system and I don't know what
additional costs have been to the city
already that we will not be able to um
recoup um if this is passed.
>> Mr. CBP, can you tell me from the
>> mayor? I'll I'll simply try. I mean, I
this is just a ballpark guess. I mean,
if you think about this in terms of over
a we had it really was almost a
three-year period. So, even if you said
10% of the time that Mr. Bay had, my
time was probably about 5%. Um, you
know, you're looking at 5% of our
salaries over a three-year period. So, I
mean, [snorts]
quarter of a million dollars um roughly
um plus what BOPU had. And then what we
we did pay a couple of consultants to
look at these. Um so that is my best
guess, ma'am.
>> Plus the consultant who did the uh the
aerial work and
>> Yes, sir. That Yes, sir.
>> And Dr. Aldridge, I'm not sure that
we've lost all that. We're just we're
going to have to take a little time off
and let the legislative process go
through and then get some clarity on
what the what we can and cannot do. So,
>> thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> Anybody else?
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, Mer. Very briefly, [clears throat]
most folks don't understand the need for
this. Uh we had a consultant that
completed a 186 page report and that's
just on dry creek. The culverts are
collapsed and rusted.
They cannot transmit water. The bottom
of the creek beds are full of trees and
overgrowth. The water cannot get through
there.
Um, we have over 400
detention ponds throughout the community
that we don't know if they work.
Nobody's looked at them in decades.
I mean, the size of this problem is
very hard to understand. And and I'm not
even talking about Crow Creek. That's
just Dry Creek. So, it's a massive
problem that we need to get started on.
Um,
I hate to I hate to support this
tonight, but I understand the political
realities. Um,
I I just hope we can come back to it in
some form because if we have that major
rain, we're going to lose our major
retail district. It'll be gone.
We'll lose most of downtown.
It'll be gone. I mean, that's just the
reality of it. So, thank you, Dr. Amits.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. So,
looking at my political crystal ball,
um I believe that the legislature will
take this on and they'll discover what
you all discovered in the last however
many years you worked on this, that it's
incredibly complicated, it's huge, and
it's incredibly expensive.
And then I'm hoping that they will say,
"Okay, now we get why the fee is
important." So I I guess that's why I
feel a little bit better about this
about supporting
um this ordinance
because I I they're they're going to
realize it's too big for them to wrap
their brains around or enough money. um
the fact that we're going to keep the
infrastructure in place.
If we were going to scrap the whole
infrastructure, I would say absolutely
not. But we will be a step ahead because
we'll have the infrastructure. As I
understood it, we didn't have all of the
funding pieces worked out anyway.
Um, and the idea of having to pay back
um
um fee pay back those fees I just think
is bad on so many levels. So um I guess
I that's why I think this is
one of those bitter pills to swallow.
>> Thank you.
All right, we have a a substitute before
us that would uh suspend or excuse me,
repeal the uh storm runoff fee. Um, are
you guys ready for a vote?
>> All right. All those in favor of the
substitute, please signify by saying I
>> I
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> Now, Mr. uh Wolf and Mr. Labour knows
the substitute is adopted and we're back
on the main motion. Comments from
members of the governing body on the
main motion
>> hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed?
>> No.
>> The ordinance is approved on second
reading as amended with Mrs. Lelaybornne
and Wolf voting no.
>> Number 13. Ordinance first reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne. Classification for
land located north of West College Drive
and east of South Parsley Boulevard from
PUD Harmony Valley Planned Unit
development to NR3 neighborhood
residential high density.
>> We'll send this item to the public
services committee. Number 14, ordinance
first reading, amending the official
zoning map of the city of Cheyenne,
changing the zoning classification for
land located south of West Allison Road,
west of Waltershide Boulevard and north
of Grand Harmony Boulevard from PUB Pud,
Harmony Valley Planned Unit development
to NR3 neighborhood residential high
density.
>> Will I sign this to the public services
committee? Number 15, ordinance, first
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne, changing
the zoning classification for land
located north of Allison Road and west
of Waltershide Boulevard from AG
agriculture to NR3 neighborhood
residential high density.
>> This one will also go to the public
services committee. Number 16,
ordinance, first reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
northwest of the intersection of East
29th Street and Central Avenue from MR,
medium density residential to NR2,
neighborhood residential, medium
density.
>> Dr. Emman, you're going to be busy.
Public Services Committee
>> number 17, ordinance, first reading,
vacating Frank Court and small and a
small segment of a previously vacated
alley north of Rock Springs Street, city
of Cheyenne, Laramie County, Wyoming,
located east of North College Drive and
north of Rock Springs Street.
>> This one will also go to the public
services committee. Number 18 resolution
authorizing the mayor and city clerk to
find sign a final plat for village
cooperative city of Cheyenne Larmy
County Wyoming located north of Prairie
Avenue east of Powder House Road west of
Rutter and south of Story Boulevard
postponed from February 23rd 2026.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
Anybody want to speak to this uh final
plaid of the village co-op?
>> Hearing none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Oh,
>> number 18. Ma'am,
>> sorry
to wake back up. Uh, Mr. Mayor, the
recommendation of the public service
committee is to adopt with staff
recommendations and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. Comments from
members of the governing body.
>> Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The resolution is adopted
with staff recommendations.
>> Next item is number 20 on page four.
resolution authorizing the submission of
an Americanore senior foster grandparent
program application to Americanore on
behalf of the governing body of the city
of Cheyenne for a three-year
continuation of funding for the youth
alternatives foster grandparent program
and related support items.
>> Anybody in the audience want to speak to
this grant application?
>> Mr. Esabel.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to adopt and I so
move.
>> Second by Mr. Moody.
Comments from members of the governing
body. Dr. Aldridge.
>> Yes, sir. Well, five hours ago it seemed
like a really good idea to pull this
off. Um, [laughter and clears throat]
however, I did want to just make sure
that people understand that this is um
is a grant that really is heavily
utilized and benefits our uh local
schools. I had the opportunity to have
two senior um foster grandparents um
when I was teaching at Triumph in our
child care center where they rocked
babies all day long. And um it was an
amazing opportunity for those um babies
and those young women to have those um
older women as mentors and um really as
grandparents for their children that
many times were um absent from their
lives. So, um this does not require a
city match and um I just think it's an
amazing opportunity to um bring these um
seniors in our community in and utilize
them in our schools and in our Head
Start programs. And um just want to give
a shout out to our senior foster
grandparent program that these I I don't
know if people know this, they get paid
like a 125 an hour and they get a free
lunch at a free school lunch. Let me
just say that. free school lunch each
day that they work. Um, so they're, um,
angels in little red vests running
around the school. But, um, pretty
amazing program. So, thank you.
>> Anyone else? I think we all say amen to
that. All right. All those in favor of
the resolution, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The resolution is
adopted.
>> Number 21. resolution authorizing the
Cheyenne Board of Public Utilities to
execute a grant agreement with the
Wyoming Office of Homeland Security for
federal emergency management agency
rehabilitation of high hazard potential
dams funding and to authorize the
director of the board to execute all
related documents.
>> All right. Anybody in the audience want
to speak to this uh uh request by the
port of public utilities?
>> Hearing none, Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to adopt and I so
move.
>> Second. Seconded by Mr. White. Comments
from members of the governing body.
>> Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> This uh grant agreement is uh
authorization is approved.
>> Next item is 26A on page five.
Renewal applications for existing city
liquor licenses, retail, restaurant,
limited retail, resort bar and grill
licenses, micro brewery, brewery,
satellite distillery, special malt
beverage and winery permits filed with
the city clerk's office.
>> We thought we'd make you feel good about
being here till closing time.
>> Huh?
>> Alf, welcome, sir.
>> Brian Gregoric, Alf's pump and package
liquor.
Oh my god. Dr.
Michelle,
I just love you. I said to her, why
would you pull us off that consent
agenda? And so there might be other
people out there, but before you say
anything else, I just got to say I've
had Alf Pub for 18 years. I had the
Redwood before that for five years. I've
never had a violation, but by God, if I
have one in the future, and I sat here
all night, I want you to take that into
consideration.
>> Well, give me some grace.
So, no, I appreciate everything council
does, but I told Susie from Outlaw
Liquors, I said, I got to get up and
tell Michelle thank you very much for
pulling us off that consent agenda.
Thank you guys for everything.
>> Appreciate you being here. Anybody else
in the audience?
>> Hello, Mr. Mayor and members of the
council. I am Cameron Brown, a member of
war 2, currently residing here in
Cheyenne, representing Chiba Hut uh here
off of Atkins Street. Uh kind of the
same sentiment. Uh thank you all for
your patience today. It's been a
wonderful display of what democracy
should be. Um especially at the local
level. So thank you all. And I would
also like to add um on behalf of Chahut
uh we appreciate being considered for
you uh uh business here as well as we
appreciate everybody's support.
Thank you. Hope business is good.
Anybody else? And again, it's almost
closing time. You feel right at home,
sir. Um, anybody else in the audience?
All right. Hearing none, Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve. And I
so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. Comments from
members of the governing body. Dr.
Aldridge.
>> Well, first and foremost, publicly
apologize because I uh never anticipated
it would be this long. Um, but you may
have gained a new customer. I may start
drinking after tonight. So, [snorts]
um, but I did want to say I I asked for
this to be pulled off the agenda. Um,
it's always concerning to me and of
course it's like, you know, preaching to
the choir here because um, none of the
entities that um are the entities that
really need to have this addressed to
them are not here tonight. So, um I
think that when these compliance buys
are done and um they're failed, I think
it's a very serious consideration. Um I
had a former student who w did the
compliance buys. Granted, he looked like
I thought he was a substitute teacher
when I first saw him in the hallways. Um
he looked like he was 25 years old. Um
and I think that's kind [snorts] of the
point is that a lot of times these
compliance buys um may they may very
much look like an adult. Um, but sales
to minor I take very seriously and I
would hope that as um business owners
and as liquor license holders that you
take it seriously as well. We had 18 um
failed compliance buys last year here in
Cheyenne. Um one entity that had failed
two of them um is no longer in business.
And I I just think that it's really
important that we stress that um you
know having a liquor license is a
privilege and that um quite honestly um
making sure that um we're protecting the
youth in our community is hugely
important. So thank you for those of you
that um do your jobs and your employees
do their jobs well. They're tips
trained. They follow the compliances.
They they're checking IDs on everybody.
I'm always quite honestly I have to tell
you that I'm always flattered when
somebody checks my ID. Um especially
since I'm usually drinking iced tea.
It's like okay knock knock knock knock
knock knock knock knock knock knock
yourself out card me um but um
appreciate you guys and what you do um
please help us keep our miners safe.
>> Anybody else
hearing none? Motion is to approve I
believe it's 95 or 98 liquor licenses.
All those in favor please signify by
saying I. I
>> I
>> those opposed. Uh the retail or all the
liquor renewals are approved.
>> Number 27A voucher report.
>> Is there anybody in the audience or in
the governing body that would like to
speak to the vouchers?
>> Next item, please. Announcement of a
public hearing to be held March 23rd,
2026 at 6 o'clock p.m. in city council
chambers, 21101 O'Neal Avenue, Cheyenne,
Wyoming and via electronic conference
meeting for a bar and grill liquor
license application filed with the city
clerk's office for Mongolian Bar and
Grill. Doing business as Mongolian Bar
and Grill, 1637 Stillwater Avenue, Sweet
C, Cheyenne, Wyoming. Other business.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience would like to speak to us under
other business?
>> Mr. Mr. Hanley, you're going to have to
be very succinct tonight, sir.
>> Okay.
We appreciate you being here again, sir.
>> Mayor, uh Ted Hanlin, Ward 2. I had a
lot to say about flot cameras tonight,
but I'm not cruel, so I'm not going to
say all that. I waited this whole time
just to make an announcement that I
think is important. Uh first of all,
since the last meeting, uh Captain James
of the Cheyenne Police Department
invited me to the station to learn about
the cameras. Of course, I accept it. I
appreciate him very much. I think the
city's very lucky to have Captain James.
Uh, but I also wanted to recommend that
everybody attend the flock safety
community meeting on March 11th at 5:30
at the Cheyenne Public Safety Center.
The more we know about the flock
cameras, the better debate we can have.
That's all I've got. I'll see you soon.
>> We'll see you Wednesday night, sir.
Anybody else in the audience?
How about from the governing body?
Okay, tell them they got to be quick.
No, I'm teasing. Who is it?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Um, I just uh uh this is Charles Miller.
Um, mayor, council, uh, for the final
record tonight, earlier this evening,
you used a point of order to cut my
microphone the second I began exposing a
mathematically false financial report.
But censorship does not cure statutory
voidness. My full unredacted legal
warning is already sitting in the city
clerk's inbox legally binding you to the
$50,000 infrastructure omission under
Wyoming statute 15142C.
You just voted to postpone this to
November 9th, but you need to understand
the legal trap you just walked
yourselves into.
Dr. Emmen specifically asked for
clarification on the record tonight to
ensure you quote don't start all over
again. By freezing this ordinance at the
third reading rather than dismissing it,
you have legally anchored your future
November vote to the exact same
defective annexation report currently on
file. You preserved your own poisoned
paperwork. Furthermore, your claim these
next eight months are to work in good
faith with the Nisley family. Uh yet
when asked if they would be notified of
meetings regarding their own livelihood,
Mayor Collins answered on the live mic,
"I'm not sure we're going to notify you
because I don't know that we would do
that." You cannot claim good faith when
your own Waltershide Boulevard
blueprints are actively targeting
over,200 square feet of this farm for a
24-in storm sewer. and you admit you
might not even call them when you when
you discuss it. You have not saved
yourselves tonight. You have simply
start started a 240day countdown. Use
this time to write the actual law
formally amend your defective financial
report and adhere to the Wyoming Food
Freedom Act. If you attempt to pass this
frozen, broken document on November 9th,
your own quotes from tonight's
transcript will be used to secure a
declaratory judgment on November 10th.
The citizens of Cheyenne are not going
anywhere. They will see you in the fall.
Thank you,
>> Jennifer. Do you have anyone else?
>> All right. How about from the governing
body?
>> Hi, Mr. Mayor.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you.
Um, Mr. Mayor, I just wanted to
recognize one of our uh city employees
and IT, Abigail Penhollow. She did a
really good job and very professional in
fixing my computer. So, Mr. Mayor and
Council, I just want to recognize her
for doing a really uh good job. Thank
you, Mr. Mayor.
Anyone else?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um, Mayor Collins, I just wanted to
remind everyone that we will have the W
three council and coffee on Saturday se
um Saturday, March 21st from 9 to 11 at
Dosbog um over on the east side. So, we
hope to see people there.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> All right. If not,
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Yes, sir.
Mr. Mayor, pursuant to Wyoming uh
statute section 16-4-405A,
I move that the governing body meet in
executive session to consider or receive
any information classified as
confidential by law.
>> Second. Seconded by Mr. Escoel. Um it's
non-debatable. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right, folks. Um, I just want to let
you guys all know that when the when the
meeting is done, we're just going to
adjourn and go home. There'll be no
other business of the governing body.
So, we appreciate you sitting through uh
dang near six hours worth of uh of
meetings and we hope you have a great
evening.
>> Thank you.
>> Sorry.
And with that, we'll ask everybody